<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

    <title>CIMI Clinical Statements</title>


    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Purpose of this section:</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>To illustrate a more traditional method of modeling using CIMI's structured data tree approach which can then be compared with the Analysis Normal Form approach.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction to CIMI Clinical Statements </title>

        <para>
            The CIMI Clinical Statement Model is described in this chapter. This model uses a traditional structured data tree approach which can then be compared and constrasted with the ANF model.
        </para>

        <para>
            The central focus of the CIMI Reference Model is the CIMI Clinical Statement. A CIMI Clinical Statement represents structured electronic communication made about a patient typically documented as an 'entry' in the patient record. For example, a CIMI Clinical Statement can be used to represent the following statements made about a patient.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Patient has diagnosis of congestive heart failure.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Patient has a family history of breast cancer.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Patient has a goal of smoking cessation.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Patient has an order for Physical Therapy.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Patient has a lab result of Serum Sodium equals 130 mEq/L with delta flag.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Patient had an appendectomy.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            CIMI Clinical Statement, shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_cstatement_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, has a ‘topic’, ‘context’, and ‘metadata’.  The ‘topic’ is the clinical entity being described.  The ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which the ‘topic’ should be evaluated.  Finally, ‘metadata’ which is not an attribute, but is only meant for illustrative purposes to represent the collection of metadata that is associated with the clinical statement: the who, where, why and when information.
        </para>

        <para>
            CIMI adopts a compositional approach rather than inheritance, where a particular topic and context are added to a CIMI Clinical Statement.  But topics and contexts themselves are defined with inheritance. This is the same general approach taken by ANF except for the following differences.  CIMI defines the topic as a structured tree where ANF defines topic as a post-coordinated Snomed expression.  Both CIMI and ANF define context as a structured tree, but ANF has alternatively named 'context' to be 'circumstance'
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_cstatement_0135">
            <title>Clinical Statement</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/clinical_statement.png" format="png" align="center"  width="150%" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">Topic</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The ‘topic’ is the clinical entity described by the Clinical Statement. A few examples of topic include clinical assertions, evaluation results, and procedures. For each of these topics the information described is quite different. Therefore, CIMI describes topic types that contain the appropriate attributes to describe the required information for the given topic. The number of topic types will change as CIMI progresses. Currently the allowable topic types are EventTopic, ProcedureTopic and FindingTopic which has suptypes of EvaluationResultTopic and AssertionTopic. 
                    </para>

                    <para>
                    	In ANF, these various structured trees representing the topic will all be represented with Snomed post-coordinated expressions. Some CIMI uses of topic will be illegal in ANF.  For example, if CIMI modeled using EvaluationResultTopic with a coded result in the Context, this would not be possible in ANF because ANF does not allow coded results.  Instead, this would need to be modeled in an AssertionTopic style with the result moved into the topic to be representable by ANF. 
                    </para>

                    <para></para> <!-- DO NOT REMOVE - Adds a space between above text and list below -->

                    

                    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>ProcedureTopic</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>FindingTopic</para>
                            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>EvaluationResultTopic</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>AssertionTopic</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">Context</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which the ‘topic’ should be evaluated. CIMI describes context types that contain the appropriate attributes to describe the required information for the given context. The number of context types will change as CIMI progresses. Currently the allowable context types are EventContext, ActionContext, and FindingContext.  ActionContext has subtypes with examples including RequestContext, OrderContext and PerformanceContext. FindingContext has subtypes with examples such as PresenceContext, AbsenceContext, and GoalContext.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                    	ANF has alternatively named 'context' to be 'circumstance' but it serves the same function in both models.  A major difference is that ANF only allows quantitative results whereas CIMI also allows coded results.  Another difference is that ANF describes all quantitative results as a range.  This allows ANF to describe presence and absence using this quantitative range, thus eliminating the need for many of the CIMI contexts describing presence and absence
                    </para>

                    <para></para> <!-- DO NOT REMOVE - Adds a space between above text and list below -->

                    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>ActionContext</para>
                            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>RequestContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>OrderContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>PerformanceContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>FindingContext</para>
                            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>PresenceContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>AbsenceContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>GoalContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        ‘metadata’ is not actually an attribute of CIMI ClinicalStatement, but is intended here to represent the various attributes in clinical statement that represent metadata about the clinical statement. This includes attribution information relating to the statement itself such as who authored, verified, recorded, or signed the statement or more informally, the who, where, why, and when information. Other attributes of this nature are recordStatus and encounter. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        
    </section>

    <section>
        
        <title>Examples Using Topic and Context</title>

        <para>     
          Earlier, descriptive examples of textual examples of clinical statements were given.  Here we will represent a few of these examples using the CIMI Clinical Statement ‘topic - context’ paradigm.  In <xref linkend="cimi_msg_cstatement_chf_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, the example for “Patient has diagnosis of congestive heart failure” is illustrated. The topic has been declared to be of type AssertionTopic stating “assertion of congestive heart failure”, and the context has been declared to be of type PresenceAbsenceContext stating “Known Present”. What may not be apparent in the figure is that when the topic is declared to be of type AssertionTopic then all the attributes of AssertionTopic are available for use. However, in the figure only the attribute named 'topicCode' is shown for clarity.  
        </para>

        <para>
          In <xref linkend="cimi_msg_cstatement_order_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, the example for “Patient has an order for Physical Therapy.” is shown. The topic has been declared to be of type ProcedureTopic stating “procedure of type physical therapy”, and the context has been declared to be of type OrderContext. Again, the majority of attributes for ProcedureTopic and OrderContext are not shown for clarity.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_cstatement_chf_0135">
            <title>Patient has diagnosis of congestive heart failure.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/clinical_statement_chf.png" align="center" format="png" width="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_cstatement_order_0135">
            <title>Patient has an order for Physical Therapy.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/clinical_statement_order.png" align="center" format="png" width="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
          StatementTopic and StatementContext are both collections of attributes and have the following characteristics:
        </para>

        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <para>They are reusable components that can be assembled to form clinical statements. For instance, one can coordinate the ProcedureTopic with the ProposalContext to represent a ProcedureProposal statement. Alternatively, ProcedureTopic may be paired with OrderContext to create a ProcedureOrder statement.  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>They represent groupings of attributes aligned with the SNOMED Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT) Concept Model. For instance, ProcedureTopic is aligned with the SNOMED CT Procedure Concept Model. PerformanceContext aligns with the Situation with Explicit Context Concept (SWEC) Concept Model.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>They provide for a mechanism to state presence or absence of a finding as well as performance or non-performance of an action. For instance, the pairing of ProcedureTopic with NonPerformanceContext allows for the expression of a procedure that was not performed.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section>

        <title>CIMI Topic Patterns</title>

    <para>
        Topic Patterns include all the attributes required to fully describe a clinical entity. The topic patterns CIMI has developed to date include FindingTopic, ProcedureTopic, with FindingTopic having children of AssertionTopic and EvaluationResultTopic. They are shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_topic_hierarchy_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/> and are described in the following sections. Each of these topic subtypes contain a collection of attributes that describe the given pattern.  These patterns provide the foundational structure for detailed clinical model (DCM) archetype instances that can be visualized at <ulink url="http://models.opencimi.org"><citetitle>http://models.opencimi.org</citetitle></ulink> 
    </para>

    <para>
        ANF does not create its own topic patterns, and instead relies on Snomed post-coordinated expressions to represent the topic.  ANF operates under the principle of separation of concerns, and believes that terminology should be a separate concern from the ANF Statement data structure and it's properties.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_topic_hierarchy_0135">
        <title>Topic Hierarchy</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/topic_hierarchy.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section>
        <title>AssertionTopic</title>

        <para>
            The first CIMI topic type described here is the AssertionTopic pattern with its included attributes, as shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_assertion_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>. Not shown in the previous diagram is that AssertionTopic has been further refined with subtypes.  ConditionTopic, shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_condition_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/> is a child of AssertionTopic which is used to represent clinical findings such as the presence (or absence) of a condition in a patient. For example:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Assert the presence of chest pain.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Assert the absence of chest pain.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Assert the presence of edema.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>


        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_assertion_0135">
            <title>AssertionTopic</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/assertion.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="40%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_condition_0135">
            <title>ConditionTopic</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/condition.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="40%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

         <para>
            The assertion pattern for a clinical statement is as follows:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                topic.topicCode = a code representing what is being asserted (i.e., “rash”, “auto accident”, “hypertrophy”, etc.).
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                context.contextCode = a code representing presence or absence.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section>
            <title>Assertion Hierarchy</title>

            <para>
                The full hierarchy for AssertionTopic is shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_assertion_hierarchy_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>.  AssertionTopic serves the following purposes: (1) it provides the core set of assertion attributes that are relevant in assertion of presence and absence; and (2) it is the parent type for the more specific assertions such as ConditionTopic and FindingSiteAssertionTopic. If additional attributes are identified as required to properly model assertions, they would either be added to one of the existing assertion types or a new type could be created with these attributes. This modeling decision would be based on whether adding these attributes make sense for existing assertions or only for a new subset of assertions. Typically an attribute is added to the parent class if that attribute is relevant in all the subclasses derived from the parent class. If an attribute is only relevant in some of the subclasses then the attribute is introduced in these subclasses. This ensures that a class does not have an attribute that is incongruent and thus requires that attribute to be frequently constrained out. As an analogy, CIMI wants to minimize the design practice that would create an Animal class that contains arms, legs, and wings and then create an instance of a dog that constrains out wings since dogs do not have wings.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_assertion_hierarchy_0135">
                <title>Assertion Hierarchy</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/assertion_hierarchy.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="60%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Assertions</title>

            <para>
                Assertions affirm or deny the existence of clinical conditions, diseases, symptoms, etc., in the patient.  As just described, different varieties of assertion may extend an existing AssertionTopic class with any additional attributes necessary to fully represent this new group of assertions. Example 1 shows examples of clinical statements using the AssertionTopic class for the topic, and Table 2 shows examples of clinical statement using FindingSiteAssertionTopic for the topic.  These examples show the ‘topic.topicCode’, ‘topic.result’, and ‘context.contextCode’ for each, with the addition of any extra attributes from the chosen topic needed to describe the clinical statement.  Context will be discussed in depth later in this document. For now, be aware the chosen context is a full class with many attributes but here we are only showing the context code attribute that is common to all context types.
            </para>

            <example xml:id="cimi_example_1_0135">
                <title>The patient has diabetes mellitus type 1 which was diagnosed at age 24</title>
                <programlisting>
    Diabetes Mellitus (Assertion Instance)
        topic.topicCode: Diabetes mellitus type 1 (disorder)
        topic.ageAtOnset: 24 years
        context.contextCode: Confirmed present (qualifier value)
                </programlisting>
            </example>

            <example xml:id="cimi_example_2_0135">
                <title>The patient does not have diabetes mellitus type 1</title>
                <programlisting>
    Diabetes Mellitus Absent (Assertion Instance)
        topic.topicCode: Diabetes mellitus type 1 (disorder)
        context.contextCode: Known absent (qualifier value)
                </programlisting>
            </example>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_diabetes_assertion_0135">
            <title>Diabetes Mellitus Assertion</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/dm_cimi.svg" format="svg" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_tubular_bsounds_assertion_0135">
            <title>Tubular Breath Sounds Assertion</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/breath_assertion_cimi.svg" format="svg" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>


            <para>
                Note, in the CIMI alignment with the SNOMED CT concept model, the AssertionTopic pattern corresponds to the Finding hierarchy as inflected by the Situation hierarchy. 
            </para>

                
            <para>
                Note AssertionStatement.topic.topicCode is not part of this construction. It is modeled with the fixed term “assertion” and is as semantically inert as we can manage.
            </para>

            <para>
                Other attributes may also inflect the semantics; e.g., an AssertionStatment.topic.findingMethod that would align with the concept model’s Finding.findingMethod.
            </para>

        
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Finding Site Assertions</title>

            <para>
                A FindingSiteAssertionTopic is an assertion about a finding found on the body. This assertion is a “design by extension” assertion because it contains the additional attribute findingSite that is used to capture the body site affected by the condition. The FindingSiteAssertionTopic encourages post-coordination as shown in examples 3 and 4, and intentionally aligns with the SNOMED CT Clinical Findings concept model.
            </para>

            <example xml:id="cimi_example_3_0135">
                <title>The patient has a femur fracture in the right leg</title>
                <programlisting>
    FractureAssert (Finding Site Assertion Instance)
        topic.topicCode: Fracture of bone (disorder)
        topic.findingSite.code: Bone structure of femur
        topic.findingSite.laterality: Right (qualifier value)
        context.contextCode: Confirmed present (qualifier value)
                </programlisting>
            </example>

            <example xml:id="cimi_example_4_0135">
                <title>The patient has a stage two pressure injury on the right ischial tuberosity</title>
                <programlisting>
    WoundAssert (Finding Site Assertion Instance)
        topic.topicCode: Pressure ulcer stage 2 (disorder)
        topic.findingSite.code: Skin structure of ischial tuberosity
        topic.findingSite.laterality: Right (qualifier value)
        context.contextCode: Confirmed present (qualifier value)
                </programlisting>
            </example>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Evaluation Result</title>

        <para>
            The second topic pattern we will discuss is EvaluationResultTopic which is used to document a characteristic of a patient or a clinical value being observed. An EvaluationResultTopic may hold the name of a test in the ‘topicCode’ attribute (e.g., “heart rate evaluation”, “serum glucose lab test”, etc.) and the resulting value of the test would be represented in the context ‘result’ attribute. Viewed another way, the EvaluationResultTopic topicCode holds a question (e.g., "what is the heart rate?", "what is the serum glucose?") and the context ‘result’ holds the answer. Any clinical statement such as a laboratory test, a vital sign, or a questionnaire question that fits this pattern of a question and a resulting value is modeled with the EvaluationResultTopic pattern.
        </para>

        <para>
           The evaluation result pattern for a clinical statement is as follows:
        </para> 

        <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                topic.topicCode = what’s being evaluated (“heart rate”, “serum glucose”, “breath sound”, etc.).
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                context.result  = the result of the evaluation  (“72 bpm”, “100 mg/dL”,  “rales”)
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>


        <para>
            The following is an isosemantic comparison of the evaluation result pattern to the previously described assertion pattern using blue eye color as an example
        </para>

        <variablelist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role='bold'>Assertion</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                topic.topicCode = blue eye color
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                context.contextCode = present
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role='bold'>EvaluationResult</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <itemizedlist mark='bullet' spacing='compact'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                topic.topicCode = eye color
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                topic.result  = blue eye color
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para>
            Like Assertion, Evaluation Result corresponds to the SNOMED CT concept model. The EvaluationResultStatement.topic.topicCode attribute corresponds to the observation being evaluated. 
        </para>

        


        <section>
            <title>Evaluation Result Hierarchy</title>

            <para>
                EvaluationResultTopic currently has two subtypes; LaboratoryTestResultTopic (which includes additional attributes necessary to describe laboratory tests) and PhysicalEvaluationResultTopic.
            </para>

            <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_evaluation_result_hierarchy_0135">
                <title>Evaluation Result Hierarchy</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/evaluation_result_hierarchy.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="60%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>


        </section>

         <section>
            <title>Modeling in the Constraint Layer</title>

            <para>
                This section will use LaboratoryTestResultTopic, which exists in the Reference Model Layer, to further describe modeling in the Constraint Layer. There are different categories of laboratory tests that differ in their resulting data type, such as quantitative labs and nominal labs, where the former would have a Quantitative result and the latter would have a Coded result. For the different lab categories there is not a need for new named attributes to be added in the reference model layer, but only a need to constrain the result to the appropriate datatype.  Since a new named attribute is not required, the style CIMI has adopted is to create subtypes in the constraint layer, where in this case an ADL Archetype would be created for both QuantitativeLaboratoryTestResult and NominalLaboratoryTestResult.
            </para>
       

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Evaluation Result Subtypes in the Reference Layer</title>

            <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role='bold'>LaboratoryTestResultTopic</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        LaboratoryTestResultTopic contains attributes specific to the lab evaluation process. These include information about the physical process (e.g., specimen) plus process management information (e.g., status).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role='bold'>PhysicalEvaluationResultTopic</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        PhysicalEvaluationResultTopic contains attributes specific to the clinical evaluation process. These include information about the physical examination process (e.g., patient position, body site).  
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>


        <example xml:id="cimi_example_5_0135">
                <title>The patient’s skin turgor is friable</title>
                <programlisting>
    SkinTurgorEval
        topic.topicCode: Skin turgor (observable entity)
        topic.evaluationProcedure: Inspection (procedure)
        context.result: Fragile skin (finding)
                </programlisting>
            </example>

            <example xml:id="cimi_example_6_0135">
                <title>The patient's systolic blood pressure is 120 mmHg</title>
                <programlisting>
    SystolicBloodPressureEval
        topic.topicCode: Systolic arterial pressure (observable entity)
        topic.evaluationProcedure: Auscultation (procedure)
        context.result: 120
            unitsOfMeasure: Millimeter of mercury (qualifier value)
                </programlisting>
            </example>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_breath_sounds_evaluation_0135">
            <title>Tubular Breath Sounds Evaluation</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/breath_evaluation_cimi.svg" format="svg" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
             <xref linkend="cimi_blood_pressure_eval_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/> and <xref linkend="cimi_blood_pressure_complex_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/> are both Evaluation Result style representations of a systolic blood pressure.  In the first, where CIMI has a simple topic, the style is very similar to how it would be modeled in ANF.  But in the 2nd figure, which has a complex topic, CIMI represents this with named properties in a tree structure.  ANF, on the other hand, would put all this structured topic complexity into a post-coordinated Snomed expression.
        </para>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_blood_pressure_eval_0135">
            <title>Sytolic Blood Pressure Evaluation</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/blood_pressure_cimi.svg" format="svg" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="cimi_blood_pressure_complex_0135">
            <title>Systolic Blood Pressure Evaluation with complex topic</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/bp_complex_cimi.svg" format="svg" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

            
        </section>
            


        <section>
            <title>Guideline: Assertion versus Evaluation</title>

            <para>
                Any evaluation model may be transformed into an assertion model. Conversely, any assertion model may be transformed into an evaluation model. Some more easily than others.
            </para>

            <para>
                The general guideline is if it is natural to think of the concept as a noun, as a condition or state that exists in the patient, model as an assertion or set of assertions. If the statement about the patient is thought of as a name/value pair (i.e., a noun representing the attribute and an adjective representing the value), such as “hair color” = (“black”, “brown”, “blonde”), then model it as an evaluation. However, it is important to note both styles are allowed and the true determinant of their use is whether a result for a given criteria other than true/false or present/absent is specified.
            </para>

            <para>
                This discussion highlights the importance of isosemantic models. Even if one model or set of models can be agreed upon as the preferred style (e.g., assertion models for “bradycardia” and “tachycardia” instead of an evaluation model with “bradycardic” and “tachycardic” as values), inevitably there will be use cases (e.g., data entry, messaging, reporting, etc.) for the other model and a need to identify use cases where different modeling patterns describe semantically identical phenomena. These patterns are isosemantic. An essential (as of now unfulfilled) requirement is for a mechanism of identifying isosemantic models, managing isosemantic groups, and transforming between them. We expect a great deal of this work to be facilitated by the semantic underpinnings of the models supporting the ability to classify the content of two models and determine their logical relations (equivalent, subsumed, disjoint).
            </para>

            <para>
                It should be noted the Assertion vs. Evaluation topic is solely concerned with the structure and schema pattern used to capture clinical information. Choosing Assertion vs. Evaluation patterns has nothing to do with whether the information being captured is subjective vs. objective. 
            </para>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>ProcedureTopic</title>

        <para>
            Procedure models are used to represent actions taken related to the care of a patient such as a cholecystectomy, peripheral IV placement, delivery of a warm blanket, dressing change, ambulation, patient education, etc.  The CIMI ProcedureTopic, as shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_procedure_hierarchy_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>,  is a base class for a number of specializations such as surgical, imaging, and laboratory procedures. The CIMI Procedure Model is aligned with the SNOMED CT Procedure Concept Model when such an alignment exists. 
 
        </para>


        <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_procedure_hierarchy_0135">
                <title>Procedure Hierarchy</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/procedure_hierarchy.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="60%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>



    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Context Patterns</title>

          <para>
            When a Clinical Statement is defined it will be modeled as a combination of a topic and a context. The ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which the ‘topic’ should be evaluated. Specializations within the context hierarchy, shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_context_hierarchy_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, add important attribution information for the situation being described.
          </para>

                    <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_context_hierarchy_0135">
                        <title>Procedure Hierarchy</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/context_hierarchy.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="60%"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>

            <para>
                The StatementContext abstract class has the following specializations:
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role='bold'>FindingContext</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                The FindingContext class aligns with the SNOMED Situation with Explicit Context for findings and provides the context for either the EvaluationResultTopic or AssertionTopic of a clinical statement. For example, a context about a finding may state that the finding was present or absent.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role='bold'>ActionContext</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                The ActionContext class aligns with the SNOMED Situation with Explicit Context for procedures and provides the context for the topic of a clinical statement. For instance, a statement about a procedure may specify the procedure has been proposed, ordered, planned, performed, or not performed. Each action context, in turn, has its own lifecycle. An example of the PerformanceContext class is shown in <xref linkend="cimi_msg_performance_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>.
         
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    
                </variablelist>

                <figure xml:id="cimi_msg_performance_0135">
                    <title>PerformanceContext</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/performance.jpg" align="center" format="jpg" width="60%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

    </section>


</section>


   


</chapter>









<!--  


    <section>
        <title>CIMI Topic Patterns</title>
        <para>The topic patterns CIMI has developed to date to include Assertion, EvaluationResult, and
            Procedure. Each of these topic subtypes contains a collection of attributes that are
            appropriate to describe the given pattern. These patterns provide the foundational
            structure for detailed clinical model archetype instances (ref
            https://issues.osehra.org/secure/attachment/15835/cimi_modeling_quality_guide.pdf ) </para>
        <para> </para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/topic_hierarchy.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="jpg" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <section>
            <title>Assertion</title>
            <para>The first topic type described here is the Assertion pattern and its included
                attributes, as shown in Figure 6, “Assertion Pattern”, which is used to represent a
                clinical finding. This pattern is used to assert the presence (or absence) of a
                condition in a patient, for example:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>ChestPainAssertion asserts the presence of chest pain</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>ChestPainAssertion asserts the absence of chest pain</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>EdemaAssertion asserts the presence of edema</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Evaluation Result</title>
            <para>
                EvaluationResult is used to document a characteristic of a patient or a
                clinical value being observed. An EvaluationResult may hold the name of a test in
                the ’topic’ (e.g., “heart rate evaluation”, “serum glucose lab test”, etc.)
                and the resulting value of the test in the ‘result’ attribute. Viewed another way,
                the EvaluationResult ‘topic’ holds a question (e.g., "what is the heart rate?", "what
                is the serum glucose?") and the ‘result’ holds the answer. Any clinical statement
                such as a laboratory test, a vital sign, or a questionnaire question that fits this
                pattern of a question and a resulting value can be modeled with the EvaluationResult
                pattern. 
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Assertion vs. Evaluation Result</title>
            <para>
                In most cases, the decision between using the evaluation result pattern and the
                assertion pattern is intuitive and straightforward. “Urine color”, for example, is
                clearly best modeled as an evaluation result because the property being evaluated is
                the color of the patient’s urine and the result of the evaluation is the set of
                codes representing the colors that may be observed. To model urine color as an
                assertion would require the creation of a large number of pre-coordinated concepts –
                the key would be “assertion” and result would be populated with a code from a set of
                codes such as “amber urine” (meaning “the patient has amber urine”), “clear urine”,
                etc. However, this highlights any evaluation model may be transformed into an
                assertion model. (Conversely, any assertion model may be transformed into an
                evaluation model.) In the case of urine color, the decision is intuitive. But in
                other cases, the decision is less clear.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

</section>


    <section>

         <para> Steps for a clinician utilizing CIF might be the following:</para>
         <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clinician collects data using Clinical Input Form</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Data is normalized using a Transformation process from CIF to ANF which is
                        representable/storable in multiple types of databases</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A data analyst who uses or queries the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or
                        working on prevalence statistics) using ANF </para>
                    <para>ANF is how the data is represented or stored in the database; A data
                        analysis must know enough about the data to know what is stored in the topic
                        vs. what is stored as a result or detail.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>CIF Issues with data retrieval</title>
        <para>Ideally, the way the information is presented to clinicians is in a manner that is
            most efficient for the clinicians to use. However, what is an efficient way for
            clinicians to select and enter data may not be the most efficient way for data analysts
            to use when they are querying data once it has been normalized and stored in a database,
            such as when creating a new CDS rule or compiling prevalence statistics. For this, the
            data is normalized using the <emphasis role="italic">Analysis Normal Form (ANF)
            </emphasis>and stored in a database. Again, the ANF is not necessarily a physical
            structure, but is how a data analyst might see the data when they are looking at it in a
            database, and not as clinicians would see it in the user interface (i.e., CIF).</para>
        <para>The more that data is normalized, the simpler it will become to analyze, and the
            likelihood of analysis errors will be reduced. The critical part of this is to ensure
            that information is not lost between the CIF and the ANF data normalization.Without the
            ANF, the probability of patient safety risks is increased. </para>
        <para>Examples of problems that can occur are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110833-0400" comment="Need to decide about leaving these examples here or keep using (and expanding on) the Pulse/BP example
" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T100827-0400" comment="Need to decide about leaving these examples here or keep using (and expanding on) the Pulse/BP example" flag="done" mid="2"?><emphasis
                        role="bold">An inability</emphasis> to determine that two clinical
                    statements are equivalent</para>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110852-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Clearly not the same. What is extra similar is the dose of acetaminophen taken on the condition the two 250 mg tablets are taken at the same time.
" flag="done"?>Taking
                    two 250 mg acetaminophen tablets together contains the same strength of
                    acetaminophen as taking one 500 mg tablet<?oxy_comment_end?> but the analyst
                    only queries for one of the statements, not both.</para>
                <para>If querying for the presence of a dot blot hemorrhage, statements recorded as
                    Present dot blot hemorrhage and 2 dot blot hemorrhages observed are
                    e<?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110917-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Also not quite, except for a query about whether any dot blot hemorrhage is present.
" flag="done"?>qual
                    in regard to presence<?oxy_comment_end?> but the analyst queries only for
                    presence vs. a quantitative finding of dot blot hemorrhages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">An inability </emphasis>to express something that is
                    clinically significant</para>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110937-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
When? If the CIF doesn’t allow it, I don’t see how the ANF would be able to solve that problem
"?>We
                    may not be able to express chest pain on inspiration,<?oxy_comment_end?> which
                    can be a sign of pleurisy. The ability to differentiate cardiac chest pain from
                    other types of chest pain is clinically important. An example of something that
                    needs to be represented is <emphasis role="italic">chest pain that worsens when
                        you breathe, cough, or sneeze</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">An error is made</emphasis> in recording or in querying
                    a repository for clinical statements</para>
                <para>On October 1, 2016, a provider enters a medication order for acetaminophen 250
                    mg for a patient to take 1 tablet twice daily for 2 days starting October 1,
                    2016</para>
                <para>CIF: Provider enters the medication order</para>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110951-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Example obscure: why would the specified request topic be needed in the query for the stated CDS rule? Something missing?
" mid="6"?>
                <para>ANF: Analyst creates a CDS rule to identify all patients ordered acetaminophen
                    during the period September 1 – December 31, 2016. However, while the analyst
                    creates a query to search for a clinical statement (i.e., Request) where
                    acetaminophen was the direct substance and was ordered during the period
                    September 1 – December 31, 2016, the analyst did not include a Request topic of
                    “Administration of drug or medication PO BID for pain.” Thus, the medication
                    order would not be included in the query
                results.</para><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> 
    </section>  -->


