<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110656-0400" comment="•	Keith’s initial Guidance
	Continue the Pulse/BP example here
	Continue to show, how the different ways of recording data are perfectly normal and acceptable and elaborate on the issues for data retrieval and analysis
"?>Clinical<?oxy_comment_end?>
        Input Form</title>
    <para>Ideally, the way the information is presented to clinicians is in a manner that is most
        efficient for the clinicians to use. However, what is an efficient way for clinicians to
        select and enter data may not be the most efficient way for data analysts to use when they
        are querying data once it has been normalized and stored in a database, such as when
        creating a new CDS rule or compiling prevalence statistics. For this, the data is normalized
        using the <emphasis role="italic">Analysis Normal Form (ANF) </emphasis>and stored in a
        database. Again, the ANF is not necessarily a physical structure, but is how a data analyst
        might see the data when they are looking at it in a database, and not as clinicians would
        see it in the user interface (i.e., CIF).</para>
    <para> </para>
    <para>Clinician collects data
        <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110732-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Chain not clear, meaning of ‘’? When is the data normalized?

"?>ð<?oxy_comment_end?>
        Clinical Input Form</para>
    <para>Data is normalized ð Transformation process from CIF to ANF ð Representable/storable in
        multiple types of databases, </para>
    <para>Dataanalyst who is using or querying the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or working on
        prevalence statistics) ð ANF (it is how the data is represented or stored in the database;
        must know enough about the data to know what is stored in the topic vs. what is stored as a
        result or detail)</para>
    <para> </para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110756-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Key here is not to lose information from CIF to ANF.
"?>Thegoal
        of ANF is to enable analysts to understand the data and how it is stored in lieu of having
        to teach them about the thousands of ways data can exist within an isosemantic family (i.e.,
        CIF) and ensure the data that has to be expressed can be expressed in an operable and
        scalable way.<?oxy_comment_end?> The more that data is normalized, the simpler it will
        become to analyze, and the likelihood of analysis errors will be reduced. Without the ANF,
        the probability of patient safety risks is increased. Examples of problems that can occur
        are:</para>
    <para> </para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110833-0400" comment="Need to decide about leaving these examples here or keep using (and expanding on) the Pulse/BP example
"?><emphasis
            role="bold">An inability</emphasis> to determine that two clinical statements are
        equivalent</para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110852-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Clearly not the same. What is extra similar is the dose of acetaminophen taken on the condition the two 250 mg tablets are taken at the same time.
"?>Taking
        two 250 mg acetaminophen tablets is the same as taking one 500 mg tablet<?oxy_comment_end?>
        but the analyst only queries for one of the statements, not both.</para>
    <para>Presenceof dot blot hemorrhage and 2 dot blot hemorrhages observed are
        e<?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110917-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Also not quite, except for a query about whether any dot blot hemorrhage is present.
"?>qualin
        regard to presence and absence<?oxy_comment_end?> but the analyst queries only for presence
        vs. a quantitative finding of dot blot hemorrhages.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">An inability </emphasis>to express something that is clinically
        significant</para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110937-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
When? If the CIF doesn’t allow it, I don’t see how the ANF would be able to solve that problem
"?>Wemay
        not be able to express chest pain on inspiration,<?oxy_comment_end?> whichcan be a sign of
        pleurisy. The ability to differentiate cardiac chest pain from other types of chest pain is
        clinically important. An example of something that needs to be represented is <emphasis
            role="italic">chestpain that worsens when you breathe, cough, or
        sneeze</emphasis>.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">An error is made</emphasis> in recording or in querying a repository
        for clinical statements</para>
    <para>On October 1, 2016, a provider enters a medication order for acetaminophen 250 mg for a
        patientto take 1 tablet twice daily for 2 days starting October 1, 2016</para>
    <para>CIF: Provider enters the medication order</para>
    <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110951-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Example obscure: why would the specified request topic be needed in the query for the stated CDS rule? Something missing?
" mid="7"?>
    <para>ANF: Analyst creates a CDS rule to identify all patients ordered acetaminophen during
        theperiod September 1 – December 31, 2016. However, while the analyst creates a query to
        search for a clinical statement (i.e., Request) where acetaminophen was the direct substance
        and was ordered during the period September 1 – December 31, 2016, the analyst did not
        include a Request topic of “Administration of drug or medication PO BID for pain.” Thus, the
        medication order would not be included in the query
        results.<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?></para>
</chapter>