<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110656-0400" comment="•	Keith’s initial Guidance
	Continue the Pulse/BP example here
	Continue to show, how the different ways of recording data are perfectly normal and acceptable and elaborate on the issues for data retrieval and analysis
"?>Clinical<?oxy_comment_end?>
        Input Form</title>
    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Purpose of this section:</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>To further illustrate, how the different ways of recording
                                    data are perfectly normal and acceptable for users and explain
                                    how this poses issues for data retrieval</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Provide examples where those issues can be patient
                                            safety risks</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction to Clinical Input Form (CIF)</title>
        <para>Ideally, clinical information is represented in a manner that is most efficient for
            use. The problem is that users have many different requirements for clinical information, thus no single
            representation can be the most efficient representation for all the various use cases. Thus, maximum efficiency
            for each use case necessitates that any particular clinical information be available in multiple
            representations. Although different in form, each of these different representations semantically model the same
            information. These are known as isosemantic models.</para>
        <para> The central focus of the CIMI Reference Model is the Clinical Statement. A Clinical
            Statement represents structured electronic communication made about a patient typically
            documented as an 'entry' in the patient record. For example, Clinical Statement can be
            used to represent the following statements made about a patient. </para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient has a diagnosis of congestive heart failure. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient has a family history of breast cancer. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient has a goal of smoking cessation. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient has an order for Physical Therapy. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient has a lab result of Serum Sodium equals 130 mEq/L with delta flag.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient had an appendectomy. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Patient has a paternal uncle with Hemophilia C. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> Clinical Statement, shown in <xref linkend="cif_msg_cstatement_0135"/>, has a ‘key’,
            ‘topic’, ‘context’, and ‘metadata’. The ‘key’ is the terminology meaning binding for the
            entire Clinical Statement. The ‘topic’ is the clinical entity being described. The
            ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which the ‘topic’ should
            be evaluated. Finally, ‘metadata’ is the collection of metadata that is associated with
            the clinical statement: the who, where, why and when information. </para>
        <figure xml:id="cif_msg_cstatement_0135">
            <title>Clinical Statement</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/cif_clinical_statement.png" align="center"
                        format="png" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">Topic</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para> The ‘topic’ is the clinical entity described by the Clinical Statement. A
                        few examples of topic include clinical assertions, evaluation results, and
                        procedures. For each of these topics the information described is quite
                        different. Therefore, CIMI describes topic types that contain the
                        appropriate attributes to describe the required information for the given
                        topic. The number of topic types will change as CIMI progresses. Currently
                        the allowable topic types are listed here. </para>
                    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>ProcedureTopic</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>FindingTopic</para>
                            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>EvaluationResultTopic</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>AssertionTopic</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">Context</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para> The ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which
                        the ‘topic’ should be evaluated. CIMI describes context types that contain
                        the appropriate attributes to describe the required information for the
                        given context. The number of context types will change as CIMI progresses.
                        Currently the allowable context types are listed here. </para>
                    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>ActionContext</para>
                            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>RequestContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>OrderContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>PerformanceContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>FindingContext</para>
                            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>PresenceContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>AbsenceContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>GoalContext</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para> ‘Metadata’ is not actually an attribute of ClinicalStatement, but is
                        intended here to represent the various attributes in a clinical statement
                        that represent metadata about the clinical statement. This includes
                        attribution information relating to the statement itself such as who
                        authored, verified, recorded, or signed the statement or more informally,
                        the who, where, why, and when information. Other attributes include 'subject
                        of record' and 'subject of information'. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>CIF Examples</title>
        <para>Pulse examples with different CIF representations</para>
        <para>BP examples with different CIF representations</para>
        <para> Steps for a clinician utilizing CIF might be the following:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clinician collects data using Clinical Input Form</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Data is normalized using a Transformation process from CIF to ANF which is
                        representable/storable in multiple types of databases</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A data analyst who uses or queries the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or
                        working on prevalence statistics) using ANF </para>
                    <para>ANF is how the data is represented or stored in the database; A data
                        analysis must know enough about the data to know what is stored in the topic
                        vs. what is stored as a result or detail.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>CIF Issues with data retrieval</title>
        <para>Ideally, the way the information is presented to clinicians is in a manner that is
            most efficient for the clinicians to use. However, what is an efficient way for
            clinicians to select and enter data may not be the most efficient way for data analysts
            to use when they are querying data once it has been normalized and stored in a database,
            such as when creating a new CDS rule or compiling prevalence statistics. For this, the
            data is normalized using the <emphasis role="italic">Analysis Normal Form (ANF)
            </emphasis>and stored in a database. Again, the ANF is not necessarily a physical
            structure, but is how a data analyst might see the data when they are looking at it in a
            database, and not as clinicians would see it in the user interface (i.e., CIF).</para>
        <para>The more that data is normalized, the simpler it will become to analyze, and the
            likelihood of analysis errors will be reduced. The critical part of this is to ensure
            that information is not lost between the CIF and the ANF data normalization.Without the
            ANF, the probability of patient safety risks is increased. </para>
        <para>Examples of problems that can occur are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110833-0400" comment="Need to decide about leaving these examples here or keep using (and expanding on) the Pulse/BP example
" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T100827-0400" comment="Need to decide about leaving these examples here or keep using (and expanding on) the Pulse/BP example" flag="done" mid="2"?><emphasis
                        role="bold">An inability</emphasis> to determine that two clinical
                    statements are equivalent</para>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110852-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Clearly not the same. What is extra similar is the dose of acetaminophen taken on the condition the two 250 mg tablets are taken at the same time.
" flag="done"?>Taking
                    two 250 mg acetaminophen tablets together contains the same strength of
                    acetaminophen as taking one 500 mg tablet<?oxy_comment_end?> but the analyst
                    only queries for one of the statements, not both.</para>
                <para>If querying for the presence of a dot blot hemorrhage, statements recorded as
                    Present dot blot hemorrhage and 2 dot blot hemorrhages observed are
                    e<?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110917-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Also not quite, except for a query about whether any dot blot hemorrhage is present.
" flag="done"?>qual
                    in regard to presence<?oxy_comment_end?> but the analyst queries only for
                    presence vs. a quantitative finding of dot blot hemorrhages.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">An inability </emphasis>to express something that is
                    clinically significant</para>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110937-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
When? If the CIF doesn’t allow it, I don’t see how the ANF would be able to solve that problem
"?>We
                    may not be able to express chest pain on inspiration,<?oxy_comment_end?> which
                    can be a sign of pleurisy. The ability to differentiate cardiac chest pain from
                    other types of chest pain is clinically important. An example of something that
                    needs to be represented is <emphasis role="italic">chest pain that worsens when
                        you breathe, cough, or sneeze</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">An error is made</emphasis> in recording or in querying
                    a repository for clinical statements</para>
                <para>On October 1, 2016, a provider enters a medication order for acetaminophen 250
                    mg for a patient to take 1 tablet twice daily for 2 days starting October 1,
                    2016</para>
                <para>CIF: Provider enters the medication order</para>
                <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110951-0400" comment="Comment from WC:
Example obscure: why would the specified request topic be needed in the query for the stated CDS rule? Something missing?
" mid="6"?>
                <para>ANF: Analyst creates a CDS rule to identify all patients ordered acetaminophen
                    during the period September 1 – December 31, 2016. However, while the analyst
                    creates a query to search for a clinical statement (i.e., Request) where
                    acetaminophen was the direct substance and was ordered during the period
                    September 1 – December 31, 2016, the analyst did not include a Request topic of
                    “Administration of drug or medication PO BID for pain.” Thus, the medication
                    order would not be included in the query
                results.</para><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="6"?>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
