<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="gloss">
    <title>Complete Glossary</title>

    <glossentry xml:id="Analysis-Normal-Form">
        <glossterm>Analysis Normal Form</glossterm>
        <acronym>ANF</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An approach to clinical statements that ensures the statement representation is
                reproducible and scalable, with the adherence to principles of being simple,
                reproducible, and use case driven, with immutability and no false
                dichotomies.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Clinical-Decision-Support">
        <glossterm>Clinical Decision Support</glossterm>
        <acronym>CDS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A function for electronic health records systems designed to help sift through
                large amounts of electronic health data to suggest next steps for treatments, alert
                providers to available information they may not have seen, or catch potential
                problems, such as dangerous medication interaction.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>HL7 Clinical Decision Support Workgroup</glossterm>
        <acronym>CDS Workgroup</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A workgroup of Health Level 7 (HL7) that focuses on development of standards to
                support system-agnostic implementations of clinical decision support, including
                messages, services, information models, and knowledge representation formalisms. For
                more information please see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/dss/index.cfm">
                    http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/dss/index.cfm</link>. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Clincal-Information-Modeling-Initiative">
        <glossterm>Clinical Information Modeling Initiative</glossterm>
        <acronym>CIMI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A workgroup of Health Level 7 (HL7) focused on improving the interoperability of
                healthcare systems through shared implementable clinical information models, and a
                sponsor of this whitepaper. For more information please see <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm"
                >http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm</link></para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Solor">
        <glossterm>Solor</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A project sponsored by the Department of Veterans Affairs that represents and
                brings together different terminology standards by using a single model that can
                encompass any customized content. Solor allows informaticists and developers to
                convert user-supplied terminologies into a single model using open source software
                to produce Solor content. For more information please see <link
                        xlink:href="http://solor.io">http://solor.io</link></para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Clinical Statement</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A clinical statement is a general informatics term. It is a definite and clear representation of a
            clinically-significant fact or situation that was observed to exist or happen.
            See Also Statement, Statement Narrative. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Statement">
        <glossterm>Statement</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A representation of a fact or situation was observed to exist or happen.
            See Also Clinical Statement, Statement Narrative.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Statement-Narrative">
        <glossterm>Statement Narrative</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A written account of a fact or situation was observed to exist or happen,
            corresponding to one or more statements. See Also Clinical Statement, Statement. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Normal-Form">
        <glossterm>Normal Form</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A defined standard structure for relational databases in which a relation may not be nested
            within another relation.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Logical Model</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A data model expressed in terms of data structures such as relational tables and columns,
            object-oriented classes, or XML tags. A logical model is expressed independently of a particular database
            management product or storage technology (physical data model).</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Clinical Information Model</glossterm>
        <acronym>CIMI Model</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>A representation of the structured clinical information
            (including relationships, constraints and terminology), that describes a specific clinical concept
            - e.g. a blood pressure observation, a Discharge Summary, or a Medication Order.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Fast-Healthcare-Interoperability-Resource">
        <glossterm>Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resource</glossterm>
        <acronym>FHIR</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>A HL7 interoperability specification for the exchange of healthcare information electronically</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Isosemantic Model</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A model that, while different in structure, represents the same semantic content as another model.
            Any particular detailed clinical model exists within a family of isosemantic siblings. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>International Organization for Standardization</glossterm>
        <acronym>ISO</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>A worldwide federation of national standards bodies from more than 160 countries, with one standards
            body representing each member country. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Detailed Clinical Model</glossterm>
        <acronym>DCM</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>A detailed clinical model is a general informatics term. As it's name suggests, it is a model that
            describes the fine details of specific clinical information. For example, a detailed clinical model
            representing a systolic blood pressure measurement would describe allowable body locations to take this
            measurement and the allowable units of measure. Thus, a detailed clinical model for systolic blood pressure
            would disallow the nonsensical clinical statement of "A systolic blood pressure taken on the femur with a
            result of 3 inches".</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>ISO/TS Detailed Clinical Models</glossterm>
        <acronym>ISO DCM</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>Detailed clinical models, characteristics and processes, is a standard that describes principles,
            requirements, governance, methods and a Logical Model to define Detailed Clinical Models. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="Structured-Clinical-Input-Forms">
        <glossterm>Structured Clinical Input Forms</glossterm>
        <acronym>Input Forms</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>The manner by which clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into
            their organizations’ electronic health record (EHR). Input forms have an impact as to how
            information is presented to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by
            constraining the information to allow only certain values to be entered, such as
            through a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking up large chunks of related
            information into smaller parts.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>HL7 Clinical Document Architecture</glossterm>
        <acronym>CDA</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>an XML-based markup standard intended to specify the encoding, structure and semantics of
            clinical documents for exchange.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>HL7 V2 Messaging Profile</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>HL7's Version 2.x (V2) messaging standard is widely used for electronic data exchange in the
            clinical domain. This messaging standard allows the exchange of clinical data between systems.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>HL7 V3</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A suite of specifications based on HL7's Reference Information Model (RIM). The Version 3 Normative
            Edition represents a new approach to clinical information exchange based on a model driven methodology
            that produces messages and electronic documents expressed in XML syntax.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Pre-coordinated concept</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A notion represented by language, which identifies one idea. These are terms which are
            considered single concepts within the host terminology. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Post-coordinated concept</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A notion represented by language, which identifies one idea. These are terms which are considered
            single concepts within the host terminology. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Topic expression</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The ‘topic’ is the clinical entity described by a clinical statement.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Context expression</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which the ‘topic’ should be evaluated. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>High Reliability Organization</glossterm>
        <acronym>HRO</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>Organizations characterized by high levels of safety under inherently risky, technologically-complex,
            and demanding conditions.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Separation of Concerns</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A design principle that allows a complete system to be subdivided into distinct sections or
            components with well-defined functionality and dependencies. If successful, this approach allows individual
            sections to be able to be reused, as well as worked on and updated independently to address new
            requirements and use cases.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Architectural Foundation</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The Architectural Foundation of the Knowledge Architecture provides the common elements of
            interoperability such as object identity, versioning, modularity, and knowledge representation.
            It includes a) the foundation and building blocks of the common model; (b) how the repeatable transformation
            process of disparate standards into the common model promotes interoperability with other environments;
            and (c) how the modules of the architecture are tightly version controlled over time.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Terminology Knowledge</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The Terminology Knowledge layer is responsible for structured sets of medical terms and codes that
            define concepts of interest, including descriptions, dialects, language, and semantic hierarchy. SNOMED CT,
            LOINC, and RxNorm are part of this layer.  </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Polymorphic model</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A model representing relationships from one class to multiple classes (e.g., observations, procedures,
            encounters, public health reports, supply, medications, exposure)</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>HL7 Service</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Aware Interoperability Framework Canonical Definition (SAIF-CD) – HL7 introduced an architecture to
            allow for a clear separation of concerns among interoperability models and specification from the abstract
            or conceptual to the most precise, implementable, and testable that ensures semantic interoperability.
            [SAIF-CD] defines three SAIF Perspectives: Conceptual, Logical, and Implementable.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Object Management Group</glossterm>
        <acronym>OMG</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>The Object Management Group®  is an international, open membership, not-for-profit technology
            standards consortium.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Model Driven Architecture</glossterm>
        <acronym>MDA</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>An approach to software design, development and implementation spearheaded by the OMG.
            MDA provides guidelines for structuring software specifications that are expressed as models.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Computationally Independent Model </glossterm>
        <acronym>CIM</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>___ TBD ____</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Platform Independent Model </glossterm>
        <acronym>PIM</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>___ TBD ____</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Platform Specific Model</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>___ TBD ____</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>CIMI Clinical Statement</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A CIMI Clinical Statement is a technology construct defined by the HL7 CIMI working group used to
            represent an instance of a clinical statement.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Clinical Terms is a standardized, multilingual
            vocabulary of clinical terminology that is used by physicians and other health care providers for the
            electronic exchange of clinical health information.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Evaluation Result</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Evaluation Result is a design pattern to represent a clinical statement in a form which specifies
            what is being evaluated paired with the result of that evaluation.  Examples would include
            'Heart Rate = 80 bpm' and 'Breath sounds = rales'.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Assertion</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Assertion is a design pattern to represent a clinical statement in a form which specifies what is
            being asserted paired with a form of presence or absence.  Examples would include 'Rales are present'
            and 'Diabetes is not present'.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Constraint Model</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A model which constrains or limits the allowable values of a reference model, or further constrains
            another constraint model.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Unified Modeling Language</glossterm>
        <acronym>UML</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>Unified Modeling Language is an Object Management Group (OMG) specification defining a graphical
            language for visualizing, specifying, constructing, and documenting the artifacts of distributed
            object systems. [defintion from OMG]</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Clinical phenomenom</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>___ TBD ____</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>ANF Topic</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A property of ANF Statemment with a value of a Logical Expression representing WHAT is being
            requested or what was performed</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>ANF Circumstance</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>ANF Circumstance is a property of ANF Statemment with a value representing the HOW, WHY, WHEN, and
            with what RESULT a requested or performed action will be or was carried out.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>ANF Request</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>An ANF Request is an instance of an ANF Statement that represents the request of an action.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>ANF Performance</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>An ANF Performance is an instance of an ANF Statement that represents the
            performance of an action.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>ANF Statement</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>An ANF Statement is a technology construct used to represent an instance of a clinical statement as
            defined by the Analysis Normal Form specification.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Editorial Rule</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>as a rule to aid in the proper modeling of an ANF Statement instance.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Technique</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A technique is a method applied, device used, or a temporary state in which the patient was
            actively placed at the moment in time of the performance of an action. It is clinical information that
            will be modeled as part of the topic of a clinical statement.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Prerequisite</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A prerequisite is a state that must exist prior to the performance of an action. It is clinical
            information that will be modeled as an independent clinical statement which will then be associated with
            other clinical statements that require this clinical information as a prerequisite. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Situation with Explicit Context</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A SNOMED Concept Model that defines the context of a clinical finding or procedure.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Health Level Seven</glossterm>
        <acronym>HL7</acronym>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Understandable, Reproducible, Useful</glossterm>
        <acronym>URU</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>A design principle that defines the solution to be Understandable, Reproducible, and Useful.
            See Also Understandable, Reproducible, Useful</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Understandable</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The content of an ANF statement can be processed by health IT systems and understood by most
            healthcare providers, without reference to private or inaccessible information.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Reproducible</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Multiple users or systems apply the ANF to the same situations and source data
            with the same/similar result. </para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Useful</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The ANF statement has a practical value: analysis, research, outcomes, etc.
            that requires information aggregated across health IT systems.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Measure</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Category</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Statement Model</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Assertional Knowledge</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Procedural Knowledge</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Domain Analysis Model</glossterm>
        <acronym>DAM</acronym>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Subject Matter Expert</glossterm>
        <acronym>SME</acronym>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Domain Expert</glossterm>
        <acronym>DE</acronym>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>openEHR</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>openEHR is an open standard specification in health informatics that describes the management and storage, retrieval and exchange of health data in electronic health records.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>SNOMED CT Expression Constrain Language</glossterm>
        <acronym>ECL</acronym>
        <glossdef><para>The SNOMED CT Expression Constraint Language is a formal language for defining bounded sets of clinical meanings represented by either precoordinated or postcoordinated expressions.</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Meta Object Facility</glossterm>
        <acronym>MOF</acronym>
        <glossdef><para></para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>
</glossary>
