<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xml:id="gloss">
    <title>Complete Glossary</title>
    <glossary>
        <glossentry xml:id="Analysis-Normal-Form">
            <glossterm>Analysis Normal Form</glossterm>
            <acronym>ANF</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An approach to clinical statements that ensures the statement representation
                    is reproducible and scalable, with the adherence to principles of being simple,
                    reproducible, and use case driven, with a clean separation between statement
                    concerns and terminology concerns.</para>
                
                <glossseealso otherterm="Reference"><xref linkend="Reference"/></glossseealso>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Clinical-Decision-Support">
            <glossterm>Clinical Decision Support</glossterm>
            <acronym>CDS</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A function for electronic health records systems designed to help sift through
                    large amounts of electronic health data to suggest next steps for treatments,
                    alert providers to available information they may not have seen, or catch
                    potential problems, such as dangerous medication interaction.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Clincal-Information-Modeling-Initiative">
            <glossterm>Clinical Information Modeling Initiative</glossterm>
            <acronym>CIMI</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para/>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Clinical-Information-Model">CIMI Model</glossseealso>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Clinical-Information-Model">
            <glossterm>Clinical Information Initiative Model</glossterm>
            <acronym>CIMI Model</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A representation of the structured clinical information (including
                    relationships, constraints and terminology), that describes a specific clinical
                    concept - e.g. a blood pressure observation, a Discharge Summary, or a
                    Medication Order.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Solor">
            <glossterm>Solor</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A project sponsored by the Department of Veterans Affairs and Logica Health
                    (formerly HSPC) that represents and brings together different terminology
                    standards by using a single model that can encompass any customized content.
                    Solor allows informaticists and developers to convert user-supplied
                    terminologies into a single model using open source software to produce Solor
                    content. For more information please see <link xlink:href="http://solor.io"
                        >solor.io</link>.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Clinical-Statement">
            <glossterm>Clinical Statement</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A clinical statement is a general informatics term. It is a definite and clear
                    representation that a clinically-significant fact or situation was observed to
                    exist or happened, or that a particular procedure was requested. </para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Statement">Statement</glossseealso>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Statement-Narrative">Statement Narrative</glossseealso>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Statement">
            <glossterm>Statement</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A representation of a fact or situation that was observed to exist or happen
                    or that a particular action was requested.</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Clinical-Statement">Clinical Statement</glossseealso>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Statement-Narrative">Statement Narrative</glossseealso>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Statement-Narrative">
            <glossterm>Statement Narrative</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A written account corresponding to one or more statements. </para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Clinical-Statement">Clinical Statement</glossseealso>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Statement">Statement</glossseealso>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Normal-Form">
            <glossterm>Normal Form</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A well-defined definitional structure that eliminates redundancy and improves
                    data integrity. Normal forms are widely used in database schema design (e.g.
                    Second Normal Form - 2NF).</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Normalization">
            <glossterm>Normalization</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The process of eliminating redundancy and improving data integrity by
                    transforming a data definition (e.g. database schema). </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Logical-Model">
            <glossterm>Logical Model</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A model expressed independently of a particular implementation
                    technology.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Isosemantic">
            <glossterm>Isosemantic Model</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A model that, while different in structure, represents the same semantic
                    content as another model. Any particular detailed clinical model exists within a
                    family of isosemantic siblings. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>International Organization for Standardization</glossterm>
            <acronym>ISO</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A worldwide federation of national standards bodies from more than 160
                    countries, with one standards body representing each member country. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Detailed Clinical Model</glossterm>
            <acronym>DCM</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A detailed clinical model is a general informatics term. As its name suggests,
                    it is a model that describes the fine details of specific clinical information.
                    For example, a detailed clinical model representing a systolic blood pressure
                    measurement would describe allowable body locations to take this measurement and
                    the allowable units of measure. Thus, a detailed clinical model for systolic
                    blood pressure would disallow the nonsensical clinical statement of "A systolic
                    blood pressure taken on the femur with a result of 3 inches".</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>ISO/TS 13972 Detailed Clinical Models</glossterm>
            <acronym>ISO DCM</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>ISO standard for detailed clinical models, characteristics and processes; this
                    describes principles, requirements, governance, methods and a Logical Model to
                    describe the contents of Detailed Clinical Models. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Structured-Clinical-Input-Forms">
            <glossterm>Clinical Input Forms</glossterm>
            <acronym>CIF</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The manner by which clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into
                    their organizations’ electronic health record (EHR). Clinical Input Forms (CIFs)
                    have an impact as to how information is presented to the clinicians and how they
                    enter the data. CIFs might be generated by natural language processing, or may
                    use models that constrain structured input to allow only certain values to be
                    entered, such as through a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking up large
                    chunks of related information into smaller parts.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190731T165606-0400" comment="Just reference HL7 CDA R2 product" flag="done"?>
            <glossterm>HL7 Clinical Document Architecture Release 2</glossterm>
            <acronym>CDA</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para><?oxy_comment_end?>See: HL7 CDA Release 2. Health Level 7 International.
                    Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7"
                        >https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7</link></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>HL7 V2 Message Profile</glossterm>
            <acronym>V2</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>See: HL7 Version 2.x Message Profiling Specification. Health Level 7
                    International. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=244"
                        >https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=244</link></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>HL7 V3</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>See: HL7 Version 3 Product Suite. Health Level 7 International. Available
                    from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186"
                        >https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=186</link><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190731T165744-0400" comment="Reference the product sheet" flag="done"?></para>
            </glossdef><?oxy_comment_end?>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Pre-coordinated concept</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A notion represented by language, which identifies one idea. These are terms
                    which are considered single concepts within the host terminology and are
                    assigned a single code to be used in recording and retrieving data. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Post-coordinated expression</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A notion represented by language, which identifies one idea. These are terms
                    which are considered single concepts within the host terminology but are not
                    assigned a single code. They are composed from existing codes in the host
                    terminology based on a defined concept model. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Topic expression</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The ‘topic’ is the clinical entity described by a clinical statement.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Context expression</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The ‘context’ describes the circumstances that form the setting in which the
                    ‘topic’ should be evaluated. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>High Reliability Organization</glossterm>
            <acronym>HRO</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Organizations characterized by high levels of safety under inherently risky,
                    technologically-complex, and demanding conditions.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Separation of Concerns</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A design principle that allows a complete system to be subdivided into
                    distinct sections or components with well-defined functionality and
                    dependencies. If successful, this approach allows individual sections to be able
                    to be reused, as well as worked on and updated independently to address new
                    requirements and use cases.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Architectural Foundation</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Architectural Foundation of the Knowledge Architecture provides the common
                    elements of interoperability such as object identity, versioning, modularity,
                    and knowledge representation. It includes (a) the foundation and building blocks
                    of the common model; (b) how the repeatable transformation process of disparate
                    standards into the common model promotes interoperability with other
                    environments; and (c) how the modules of the architecture are tightly version
                    controlled over time.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Terminology Knowledge</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Terminology Knowledge layer is responsible for structured sets of medical
                    terms and codes that define concepts of interest, including descriptions,
                    dialects, language, and semantic hierarchy. SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm are
                    part of this layer. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Polymorphic model</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A model representing relationships from one class to multiple classes (e.g.,
                    observations, procedures, encounters, public health reports, supply,
                    medications, exposure).</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>HL7 Service Aware Interoperability Framework Canonical Definition
                (SAIF-CD)</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>HL7 introduced an architecture to allow for a clear separation of concerns
                    among interoperability models and specification from the abstract or conceptual
                    to the most precise, implementable, and testable that ensures semantic
                    interoperability. SAIF-CD defines three distinct perspectives: Conceptual,
                    Logical, and Implementable.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Object Management Group</glossterm>
            <acronym>OMG</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Object Management Group® is an international, open membership,
                    not-for-profit technology standards consortium.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Model Driven Architecture</glossterm>
            <acronym>MDA</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An approach to software design, development and implementation spearheaded by
                    the OMG. MDA provides guidelines for structuring software specifications that
                    are expressed as models.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Computationally Independent Model </glossterm>
            <acronym>CIM</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para> According to Model-Driven Architecture, a Computation Independent model (CIM)
                    corresponds to a view defined by a computation independent viewpoint. It
                    describes the business context and business requirements for the software
                    system(s). </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Platform Independent Model </glossterm>
            <acronym>PIM</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A model of a software system or business system that is independent of the
                    specific technological platform used to implement it. </para><para> Logical models like <xref linkend="Reference"/> are platform-independent.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
         <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>SNOMED CT is a standardized, multilingual vocabulary of clinical terminology
                    that is used by physicians and other health care providers for the electronic
                    exchange of clinical health information.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Evaluation Result</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Evaluation Result is a design pattern to represent a clinical statement in a
                    form which specifies what is being evaluated paired with the result of that
                    evaluation. Examples would include 'Heart Rate = 80 bpm' and 'Breath sounds =
                    rales'.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Assertion</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Assertion is a design pattern to represent a clinical statement in a form
                    which specifies what is being asserted paired with a form of presence or
                    absence. Examples would include 'Rales are present' and 'Diabetes is not
                    present'.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Constraint Model</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A model which constrains or limits the allowable values of a reference model,
                    or further constrains another constraint model.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Unified Modeling Language</glossterm>
            <acronym>UML</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para><link xlink:href="https://www.omg.org/spec/UML/About-UML/">Unified Modeling
                        Language </link>is an Object Management Group (OMG) specification defining a
                    graphical language for visualizing, specifying, constructing, and documenting
                    the artifacts of distributed object systems. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>ANF Topic</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A property of an ANF Statement with a value of a Logical Expression
                    representing WHAT is being requested or what was performed</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>ANF Circumstance</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>ANF Circumstance is a property of an ANF Statement with a value representing
                    the HOW, WHY, WHEN, and with what RESULT a requested or performed action will be
                    or was carried out.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>ANF Request</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An ANF Request is an instance of an ANF Statement that represents the request
                    of an action.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>ANF Performance</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An ANF Performance is an instance of an ANF Statement that represents the
                    performance of an action.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>ANF Statement</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An ANF Statement is a technology construct used to represent an instance of a
                    clinical statement as defined by the Analysis Normal Form specification.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Editorial">
            <glossterm>Editorial Rule</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Methodological rules to describe the proper modeling of an ANF Statement
                    instance.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Technique</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A technique is a method applied, device used, or a temporary state in which
                    the patient was actively placed at the moment in time of the performance of an
                    action. It is clinical information that will be modeled as part of the topic of
                    a clinical statement.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Prerequisite</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A prerequisite is a state that must exist prior to the performance of an
                    action. It is clinical information that will be modeled as an independent
                    clinical statement which will then be associated with other clinical statements
                    that require this clinical information as a prerequisite. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Situation with Explicit Context</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A SNOMED CT Concept Model that defines the context of a clinical finding or
                    procedure.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Understandable, Reproducible, Useful</glossterm>
            <acronym>URU</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A design principle that defines the solution to be Understandable,
                    Reproducible, and Useful. </para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Understandable">Understandable</glossseealso>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Reproducible">Reproducible</glossseealso>
                <glossseealso otherterm="Useful">Useful</glossseealso>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Understandable">
            <glossterm>Understandable</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The content of an ANF statement can be processed by health IT systems and
                    understood by most healthcare providers, without reference to private or
                    inaccessible information.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Reproducible">
            <glossterm>Reproducible</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Multiple users or systems apply the ANF to the same situations and source data
                    with the same/similar result. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Useful">
            <glossterm>Useful</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The ANF statement has a practical value: analysis, research, outcomes, etc.
                    that requires information aggregated across health IT systems.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Measure</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Measure captures measurable elements of clinical statements, e.g. the results
                    of test procedures, time periods, frequencies of repetitions for procedures or
                    medication administrations using an interval (upper and lower bound) as well as
                    a measure semantic representing the meaning of the interval (e.g. milligrams,
                    seconds, count ).</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Statement-Model">
            <glossterm>Statemen Model</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Statement Model layer is responsible for defining how terminology concepts
                    can be combined to create a statement. Within the data structures, additional
                    detail to describe subject, numerical, and categorical information related to
                    concepts can be added in this layer. ANF introduces a statement model specific
                    to analysis and clinical decision support. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Assertional-Model">
            <glossterm>Assertional Knowledge</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Assertional Knowledge layer reuses information based on Statement Model.
                    It is responsible for guidelines and business rules to assist clinical decision
                    making. This includes facts and knowledge upon which concepts and combinations
                    of concepts can assimilate into protocols. ANF statements can be used to support
                    assertional artifacts.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Procedural-Knowledge">
            <glossterm>Procedural Knowledge</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Procedural Knowledge Layer is responsible for information about standard
                    ways to carry out specific procedures as well as other procedural guidelines,
                    e.g. treatment protocols for diseases and order sets focused on particular
                    patient situations. Procedural knowledge, together with assertional knowledge,
                    enables clinical decision support, quality measurement, and supports patient
                    safety. This layer is based on the interoperability infrastructure and
                    terminology layers, incorporates the statement model for information retrieval,
                    and uses the assertional layer to apply rules.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Domain Analysis Model</glossterm>
            <acronym>DAM</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An abstract representation of a subject area of interest, complete enough to
                    allow instantiation of all necessary concrete classes needed to develop child
                    design artifacts.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>openEHR</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>openEHR is an open standard specification in health informatics that describes
                    the management and storage, retrieval and exchange of health data in electronic
                    health records.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>SNOMED CT Expression Constraint Language</glossterm>
            <acronym>ECL</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The SNOMED CT Expression Constraint Language is a formal language for defining
                    bounded sets of clinical meanings represented by either pre-coordinated or
                    post-coordinated expressions.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Meta Object Facility</glossterm>
            <acronym>MOF</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The foundation of OMG's industry-standard environment where models can be
                    exported from one application, imported into another, transported across a
                    network, stored in a repository and then retrieved, rendered into different
                    formats (including XMI™, OMG's XML-based standard format for model transmission
                    and storage), transformed, and used to generate application code.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="Reference">
            <glossterm>ANF Reference Model</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A logical model described herein using Object Management Group (OMG) Unified
                    Modeling Language (UML) 2.0 notation to describe the structure of normalized
                    clinical statements for computational analysis. This logical model may be
                    implemented using any programming language, database technology, or
                    interoperability specification (e.g. FHIR) suitable for analysis. ANF is
                    intended to normalize approaches and methodologies in use across the industry
                    and provide a uniform representation of data to enable analysis.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Electronic Clinical Quality Measures</glossterm>
            <acronym>eCQM</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>An electronic clinical quality measure (eCQM) is a clinical quality measure
                    that is expressed and formatted to use EHR data to measure healthcare quality,
                    specifically data captured in structured form during the process of patient
                    care.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190731T165948-0400" comment="We need to ask Joey/Keith about these" flag="done"?>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Number-Needed-to-Treat</glossterm>
            <acronym>NNT</acronym>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The number of patients you need to treat to prevent one additional bad outcome
                    (death, stroke, etc.)</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Number-Needed-to-Harm</glossterm>
            <acronym>NNH</acronym><?oxy_comment_end?>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A measure of how many people need to be treated (or exposed to a risk factor)
                    in order for one person to have a particular adverse effect. </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
            <glossterm>Knowledge Architecture</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>As defined in this document, a Knowledge Architecture promotes semantics
                    interoperability and enables a clean separation of concerns along the following
                    layers: Foundational Architecture, Terminology Knowledge, <link
                        linkend="Statement-Model">Statement Model</link>, <link
                        linkend="Assertional-Model">Assertional Knowledge</link>, and <link
                        linkend="Procedural-Knowledge">Procedural Knowledge</link>. </para>
                <para><link linkend="Analysis-Normal-Form">ANF</link> is part of the Statement
                    Model.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
    </glossary>
    <para/>
</chapter>
