<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Abbreviated Glossary</title>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Analysis Normal Form</glossterm>
        <acronym>ANF</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An approach to clinical statements that ensures the statement representation is
                reproducible and scalable, with the adherence to principles of being simple,
                reproducible, and use case driven, with immutability and no false
                dichotomies.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Clinical Decision Support</glossterm>
        <acronym>CDS</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A function for electronic health records systems designed to help sift through
                large amounts of electronic health data to suggest next steps for treatments, alert
                providers to available information they may not have seen, or catch potential
                problems, such as dangerous medication interaction.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>HL7 Clinical Decision Support Workgroup</glossterm>
        <acronym>CDS Workgroup</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A workgroup of Health Level 7 (HL7) that focuses on development of standards to
                support system-agnostic implementations of clinical decision support, including
                messages, services, information models, and knowledge representation formalisms. For
                more information please see <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/dss/index.cfm">
                    http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/dss/index.cfm</link>. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Clinical Input Form</glossterm>
        <acronym>CIF</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The manner by which clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into
                their organizations’ electronic health record (EHR). CIF has an impact as to how
                information is presented to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by
                constraining the information to allow only certain values to be entered, such as
                through a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking up large chunks of related
                information into smaller parts. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Clinical Information Modeling Initiative</glossterm>
        <acronym>CIMI</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A workgroup of Health Level 7 (HL7) focused on improving the interoperability of
                healthcare systems through shared implementable clinical information models, and a
                sponsor of this whitepaper. For more information please see <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm"
                    >http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm</link></para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resource</glossterm>
        <acronym>FHIR</acronym>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The newest standard for exchanging healthcare information electronically from
                Health Level 7 (HL7). For more information please see <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html"
                    >https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html</link></para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Normal Form</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Normalization is a design technique that transforms (or reduces) data into a
                standard fundamental form of a statement. The standard fundamental form is referred
                to as a normal form. </para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Solor</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A project sponsored by the Department of Veteran’s Affairs that represents and
                brings together different terminology standards by using a single model that can
                encompass any customized content. Solor allows informaticists and developers to
                convert user-supplied terminologies into a single model using open source software
                to produce Solor content. For more information please see <link
                    xlink:href="http://solor.io">http://solor.io</link></para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
</glossary>
