<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Glossary</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">ANF – Analysis Normal Form</emphasis>, an approach to clinical
        statements that ensures the statement representation is reproducible and scalable, with the
        adherence to principles of being simple, reproducible, and use case driven, with
        immutability and no false dichotomies. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">CDS – Clinical Decision Support</emphasis>, a function for
        electronic health records systems designed to help sift through large amounts of electronic
        health data to suggest next steps for treatments, alert providers to available information
        they may not have seen, or catch potential problems, such as dangerous medication
        interaction. Also a workgroup of Health Level 7 (HL7) that focuses on development of
        standards to support system-agnostic implementations of clinical decision support, including
        messages, services, information models, and knowledge representation formalisms. For more
        information please see <link
            xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/dss/index.cfm"
            >http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/dss/index.cfm</link>.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">CIF – Clinical Input Form</emphasis>, the manner by which clinicians
        author clinical statements and enter them into their organizations’ electronic health record
        (EHR). CIF refers to the manner in which information is presented to the clinicians and how
        they enter the data, such as by constraining the information to allow only certain values to
        be entered, such as through a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking up large chunks of
        related information into smaller parts. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">CIMI – Clinical Information Modeling Initiative</emphasis>, a
        workgroup of Health Level 7 (HL7) focused on improving the interoperability of healthcare
        systems through shared implementable clinical information models, and a sponsor of this
        whitepaper. For more information please see <link
            xlink:href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm"
            >http://www.hl7.org/Special/Committees/cimi/index.cfm</link></para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">EHR – Electronic Health Record, </emphasis>an electronic system that
        allows clinicians providing care in a clinical setting to enter and store data used in
        clinical care in structured or unstructured format for retrieval, exchange and analysis
        according to permitted uses.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">FHIR – Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources</emphasis>, the
        newest standard for exchanging healthcare information electronically from Health Level 7
        (HL7). For more information please see <link
            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html"
            >https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html</link></para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Solor</emphasis> – A project sponsored by the Department of
        Veteran’s Affairs that represents and brings together different terminology standards by
        using a single model that can encompass any customized content. Solor allows informaticists
        and developers to convert user-supplied terminologies into a single model using open source
        software to produce Solor content. For more information please see <link
            xlink:href="http://solor.io">http://solor.io</link></para>

</section>