<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T101734-0400" comment="KC: Don’t put too much effort into this. Describe transformation on a high level. Put the most work into the examples (BP, Pulse etc. earlier in the document)
IS: Big value is the endpoint of data being normalized into ANF. 
KC: We can convince people that ANF has value like 1st normal form and 2nd normal form (Tim has expertise here). 
"?>Transformation<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Purpose of this section:</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Explain how the ANF Model transforms the clinical statements
                                    into normalized data</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <section>
        <title> Transformation</title>
        <para>ANF provides a normal form for clinical information captured using any approach to
            data entry using either standard-based logical models (e.g. CIMI, DCM, etc.) or
            proprietary data entry approaches (See “Structured Clinical Statement” section). ANF
            helps transform clinical data into normalized data that can then be used to: </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>reconcile data that is captured in a variety of mechanisms and making it
                        compatible with other data</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>moving clinical data to another system</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>joining it with other clinical data, or aggregate information in the
                        data</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>facilitate CDS and patient safety. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Clinical data will start off overly post-coordinated but with the data potentially
            spread across multiple fields. By creating an ANF statement, one can take the disparate
            information and organize it so that the post-coordination is mostly contained in the
            topic representation instead of being spread across disparate fields. For instance,
            there may be 1 clinical statement in an EHR for blood pressure measurement and care
            planning that might be 5 observations when represented by FHIR. There are many different
            ways to create the FHIR data structures. </para>
        <para>A current solution to minimize the variation of implementations is by healthcare
            organizations making a choice to either use Assertion style vs. Evaluation Result. When
            transferring data structures between and amongst institutions, these different styles
            may be a problem. The current approach is to solve the problem by conformity rather than
            with technology. </para>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190522T215723-0500" comment="Where do concrete domains fit in?"?>With
            ANF, we will be able to handle concrete domains by increasing the payload in the topic
            representation and by putting all of the topic details in a post-coordinated SNOMED CT
            expression. <?oxy_comment_end?>By using the ANF model, with the increased specificity of
            the topic expression, the variability in representations is reduced since the CIMI
            Evaluation Result style representation of clinical data is eliminated..
            <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190522T220242-0500" comment="Is this true?  What about Status and Priority?  Even Presence and Absence can change the meaning of the topic."?>With
            ANF, the things that change meaning are always in the topic.<?oxy_comment_end?> Whether
            something is a request or has occurred – this is not in the topic. That separation is
            okay because of xxx</para>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190522T220532-0500" comment="Haven&apos;t we described this already?"?>
        <para>Not having coded answers is a big paradigm shift. We need to describe the benefits. If
            ANF topic expression is created in correct way, you can query for all permutations of a
            concept with a single parent concept that can create them. In FHIR, one thing that is
            built in already is ability to search for attribute for resource that comes from a
            published value set.<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190522T134113-0500" comment="Does this belong here?"?>
        <para>With ANF, we are cutting down the choices modelers will have to make, but we do not
            eliminate all the choices. There may still be more than 1 way to represent things in ANF
            and therefore there are the following editorial rules that we recommend to promote
            conformity amongst modelers:
            <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190523T005636-0400" comment="Note from Keith: For the ANF document, we should somewhere describe assumptions about what an ANF implementation requires. For example, ANF requires an ability to classify topic expressions (and expressions that may go in other locations). Maybe a section that describes the requirements of a &quot;mapping&quot; based system with a plethora of statement models, and then what ANF requires above and beyond a mapping system, and what the benefits are. "?>xxx<?oxy_comment_end?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190523T103205-0500" comment="Should we discuss mapping issues here?  Can we reuse some of the Solor slides around mapping to highlight an issue of using mapping?"?>
        <para>The following diagram highlights how clinical statements recorded using a model of
            knowledge (e.g. CIMI model or archetype) are used to enter information that may be
            exchanged using a variety of interoperability artifacts (e.g. HL7 V2 messages, CDA
            documents, FHIR resources). If the information is aggregated and normalized for
            analysis, the ANF clinical statement may be used to extract/query normalized clinical
            statements using ANF-based FHIR template. The diagram illustrates the role each SAIF-CD
            Perspective. <?oxy_comment_end?><figure>
                <title>Applying ANF to analysis of aggregate clinical statements</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/transformation.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%"
                            format="SVG" contentdepth="40%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
    </section>
</chapter>
