<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T101734-0400" comment="KC: Don’t put too much effort into this. Describe transformation on a high level. Put the most work into the examples (BP, Pulse etc. earlier in the document)
IS: Big value is the endpoint of data being normalized into ANF. 
KC: We can convince people that ANF has value like 1st normal form and 2nd normal form (Tim has expertise here). 
"?>Transformation<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
    <para/>
    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Purpose of this section:</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Explain how the ANF Model transforms the clinical statements
                                    into normalized data</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <section>
        <title> Draft Transformation Content</title>
        <para>In this chapter we will discuss how ANF helps transform clinical data into normalized
            data – it can help with reconciling data that is captured in a variety of mechanisms and
            make it compatible with other data, move it to another system, join it with other data,
            or aggregate information in the data. Ultimately, this will assist with use for CDS and
            patient safety. </para>
        <para>EHR data will start off overly post-coordinated with the data potentially spread
            across multiple fields. By creating an ANF statement, one can take the disparate
            information and organize it so that the post-coordination is mostly contained in the
            topic representation instead of being spread across disparate fields. </para>
        <para>For instance, there may be 1 clinical statement in an EHR for blood pressure
            measurement and care planning that might be 5 observations when represented by FHIR.
            There are many different ways to create the FHIR data structures. </para>
        <para><emphasis>Challenges that will likely arise: You may have multiples. How is that a
                challenge? One would have to search for the 1st thing and then return and query that
                to find the next thing…</emphasis></para>
        <para>A current solution to minimize the variation by implementation is that healthcare
            organizations will make a choice to either use Assertion style vs. Evaluation Result and
            will not create the other format. When transferring data structures between and amongst
            institutions, these different styles may be a problem. The current approach is to solve
            the problem by conformity rather than with technology. </para>
        <para>With ANF, we will be able to handle concrete domains by increasing the payload in the
            topic representation and by putting all of the topic details in a post-coordinated
            SNOMED CT expression. With ANF, with the increased specificity of the topic expression,
            there are not several different ways to represent the same clinical statement. In ANF,
            you can’t do the CIMI Evaluation Result style, because you can’t have a coded answer,
            that choice is taken away from you by the constructs of ANF. Qualifiers do change the
            meaning of data. With ANF, the things that change meaning are always in the topic.
            Whether something is a request or has occurred – this is not in the topic. That
            separation is okay because of xxx</para>
        <para>Not having coded answers is a big paradigm shift. We need to describe the benefits. If
            ANF topic expression is created in correct way, you can query for all permutations of a
            concept with a single parent concept that can create them. In FHIR, one thing that is
            built in already is ability to search for attribute for resource that comes from a
            published value set.</para>
        <para>With ANF, we are cutting down the choices modelers will have to make, but we do not
            eliminate all the choices. There may still be more than 1 way to represent things in ANF
            and therefore there are the following editorial rules that we recommend to promote
            conformity amongst modelers: xxx</para>
        <para> </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
