<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

    <title>Putting it Together: Normalization and Transformation</title>


    <para>Normalization of <glossterm baseform="Clinical Statement">clinical statements</glossterm>
        is defined as "the ability to identify every representational format that confers the same
        meaning as being equivalent (i.e., unambiguous representation)." <link linkend="bib8"
            >[12]</link>
    </para>


    <section>
        <title>Data Structures</title>
        <para>Currently, the standard is to define detailed clinical models using different data
            structures for different domains of clinical statements. For example, <glossterm
                baseterm="Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resource">FHIR</glossterm> independently
            defines the resources for Conditions, Observations, Diagnosis, Procedure, Goal,
            Medication Administration, Medication Request, etc. Some implementations, such as FHIR,
            explicitly define the property names for the parts of each data structure tree and other
            formalisms such as Basic Meta Model (BMM), Archetype Definition Language (ADL), and
            Clinical Element Modeling Language (CEML) use a form of key-value pairing to genericise
            the property naming of the data structure tree. But in all these cases, the fact remains
            that the resulting structure of the tree still remains different for different domains
            of clinical statements. Thus, computation and analysis of data instances, that conform
            to these models, requires a prior understanding of the tree structure for each domain. </para>
        <para>

        </para>
        <para><glossterm baseform="Analysis-Normal-Form">ANF</glossterm> seeks to simplify the
            complexity that currently exists in detailed clinical models. As its name suggests,
            Analysis Normal Form provides one normalized data structure to describe clinical
            statements from all domains. ANF accomplishes this simplification by moving the
            complexity  from static statement data structures to dynamic
                <emphasis>pre-coordinated</emphasis>, or <glossterm
                baseform="Post-coordinated concept">post-coordinated</glossterm> terminology
            expressions, as defined by the Terminology Knowledge layer of the architecture. </para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Modeling Style</title>

        <para>Another variation that currently exists is the allowed design choices which can be
            made by model authors. For example, a modeler may choose to model breath sounds as
            'breath sounds' with a coded result of 'rales', or as 'rales' with a result of
            'present'. Currently, organizations try to minimize this type of variation by
            documenting design choice rules in modeling "style guides". For instance, a common style
            guide choice in the <glossterm baseterm="CIMI Clinical Statement">CIMI Clinical
                Statement</glossterm> model is to either use the <glossterm>Assertion</glossterm>
            style or the <glossterm>Evaluation Result</glossterm> style, and <glossterm
                baseterm="Clinical Information Modeling Initiative">CIMI</glossterm> documents which
            types of clinical statement are best suited for each. Assignment of clinical statement
            types into these categories creates false dichotomies, since there are a myriad of
            examples where clinical statement types can readily fit in both categories. </para>
        <para>ANF's approach is to solve the problem by eliminating the need to make choices between
            overlapping statement types. ANF seeks to minimize this variation by only allowing
            quantitative results. This eliminates the choice between Evaluation style versus
            Assertion style clinical statements as coded results are not possible. </para>

        

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Transformation to ANF</title>

        <para>The previous sections have described the variation that can exist in the data
            structure and modeling style of a single standard. Moreover, this variation is
            significantly compounded when simultaneously using data from multiple standards, such as
            when receiving data from multiple institutions. </para>

        <para>Analysis Normal Form can act as a transformation target to normalize these disparate
            representations of clinical statements, shown in <xref
                linkend="transformationToANF_0135" xrefstyle="select: label"/>. Normalization
            implies the ability to recognize all representations that express the same meaning as
            being algorithmically equivalent. </para>

        <para>To be clear, the transformation discussed is a data instance to data instance
            transformation. An example could be John Doe's Systolic Blood Pressure measurement taken
            on June 4, 2019 represented as a FHIR Observation instance, which is then transformed to
            an ANF instance representing this same data. This is not to be confused with a detailed
            clinical model transformation between two formalisms, such as an <glossterm
                baseform="International Organization for Standardization">ISO</glossterm>
            <glossterm baseform="Detailed Clinical Model">DCM</glossterm> for Systolic Blood
            Pressure transformed to a FHIR profile for Systolic Blood Pressure. </para>

        <figure xml:id="transformationToANF_0135">
            <title>Transformation to ANF</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/transformationToAnf.png" align="center" format="png" width="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <caption><para><emphasis>Various isosemantic representations of statement models can be brought together into
                        Analysis Normal Form</emphasis></para></caption>
        </figure>

        <para>Transformation, in this case, is not a simple endeavor that one can hope to automate
            across domains of clinical statements or even within a single domain of clinical
            statements. As presented, it will involve navigating disparate data structure trees and
            include variable representations to then generate a well-formed terminology expression.
            It is most likely possible to target sub-domains for consistent transformation, such as
            all quantitative laboratory results, but in some cases, it may be that each detailed
            clinical model needs its own unique transformation. </para>

        <para> Potential areas of difficulty during transformation:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
                <listitem>
                    <para>One complex statement/assessment may be transformed frequently be
                    transformed to many ANF instances (see <xref linkend="complexExample"/>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Implied clinical meaning or mapping associated with data structures and
                    bound terminology must be transformed into post-coordinated SNOMED CT expression
                    for inclusion as <glossterm>ANF Topic</glossterm> (see <xref
                        linkend="fhirTransform"/> as examples using explicit and implied semantics
                    to normalize clinical statements.) </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>


        <para>Currently, there are three basic categories of errors that might be associated with
            attempts at normalizing clinical statement representation:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> errors associated with normalization of content of the terminology; </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>errors associated with normalization of the semantics of the terminology;
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>errors that result from ambiguous or misleading interaction between the
                    structured clinical input and presentation of compound terminology to clinician
                    end-users. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </section>

        

    <!--
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>reconcile data that is captured in a variety of mechanisms and making it
                        compatible with other data</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>moving clinical data to another system</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>joining it with other clinical data, or aggregate information in the
                        data</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>facilitate CDS and patient safety. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    
        <para>
            Clinical data will start off overly post-coordinated but with the data potentially
            spread across multiple fields. By creating an ANF statement, one can take the disparate
            information and organize it so that the post-coordination is mostly contained in the
            topic representation instead of being spread across disparate fields. For instance,
            there may be 1 clinical statement in an EHR for blood pressure measurement and care
            planning that might be 5 observations when represented by FHIR. There are many different
            ways to create the FHIR data structures. Redundancy in representation of clinical
            statmenets may cause insertion, deletion and, maintenance of anomalies. 
        </para>



            <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190601T180110-0500" comment="I believe this is
            actually the opposite. Normalization will result in the information being spread across more
            clinical statements. For example, in ANF, patient sitting and having urinated will be there
            own associated clinical statements"?><?oxy_comment_end?>

            

        

        <para>
            
        </para>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190530T135125-0400" comment="We need exampes to walk through normalization. "?><?oxy_comment_end?>

        <para>
            With ANF, we aim to reduce the ambiguity and redundancy in model representation of
            clincial statements. ANF
            <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190522T215723-0500" comment="Where do concrete domains fit in?"?>will
            be able to handle concrete domains by increasing the payload in the topic representation
            and by putting all of the topic details in a post-coordinated SNOMED CT expression.
            <?oxy_comment_end?>By using the ANF model, with the increased specificity of the topic
            expression, the variability in representations is reduced since the CIMI Evaluation
            Result style representation of clinical data is eliminated..
            <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190522T220242-0500" comment="Is this true?  What about Status and Priority?  Even Presence and Absence can change the meaning of the topic."?>With
            ANF, the things that change meaning are always in the topic.<?oxy_comment_end?> Whether
            something is a request or has occurred – this is not in the topic. That separation is
            okay because of xxx.
        </para>

        <para>
            With ANF, we are cutting down the choices modelers will have to make, but we do not
            eliminate all the choices. There may still be more than 1 way to represent things in ANF
            and therefore there are the following editorial rules that we recommend to promote
            conformity amongst modelers: <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190523T005636-0400" comment="Note from Keith: For the ANF document, we should somewhere describe assumptions about what an ANF implementation requires. For example, ANF requires an ability to classify topic expressions (and expressions that may go in other locations). Maybe a section that describes the requirements of a &quot;mapping&quot; based system with a plethora of statement models, and then what ANF requires above and beyond a mapping system, and what the benefits are. "?>xxx<?oxy_comment_end?>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190530T135833-0400" comment="Tim&apos;s decision tree?"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
        </para>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190523T103205-0500" comment="Should we discuss mapping issues here?  Can we reuse some of the Solor slides around mapping to highlight an issue of using mapping?"?>
            <para>The following diagram highlights how clinical statements recorded using a model of
                knowledge (e.g. CIMI model or archetype) are used to enter information that may be
                exchanged using a variety of interoperability artifacts (e.g. HL7 V2 messages, CDA
                documents, FHIR resources). If the information is aggregated and normalized for
                analysis, the ANF clinical statement may be used to extract/query normalized clinical
                statements using ANF-based FHIR template. The diagram illustrates the role each SAIF-CD
                Perspective. 
            </para><?oxy_comment_end?>
       
        <figure>
            <title>Applying ANF to analysis of aggregate clinical statements</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/transformation.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%"
                        format="SVG" contentdepth="50%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        
        <para>Normal forms are commonly used to eliminate or reduce redundancy in database tables.
            ANF can have similar benefits on clinical data storage and retrieval:</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">1. First Normal Form</emphasis></para>
        <para>If a relation contain composite or multi-valued attribute, it violates first normal
            form or a relation is in first normal form if it does not contain any composite or
            multi-valued attribute. A relation is in first normal form if every attribute in that
            relation is singled valued attribute.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">2. Second Normal Form</emphasis></para>
        <para>To be in second normal form, a relation must be in first normal form and relation must
            not contain any partial dependency. A relation is in 2NF iff it has No Partial
            Dependency, i.e., no non-prime attribute (attributes which are not part of any candidate
            key) is dependent on any proper subset of any candidate key of the table.</para>
       </section>

    -->
    
    <section>
        <title>Transformation Languages and Architecture</title>
        
        <para>A number of options exist for expressing transformation logic and for executing the
            transformation on specific instances of clinical data for normalization into ANF. These range from transformation languages to expensive middleware options commonly used in healthcare interfaces. The suitability of the chosen language highly depends on the format of the source data, and the quality and accuracy of the transformation is left to the transformation author. One option described here is Model Driven Message Interoperability (MDMI), which is an architecture for transformation that assists in producing semantically accurate transformations.
        </para>


        <section>
            <title>XSLT</title>
            <para>XSLT (eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformations) is a World Wide Web
                Consortium (W3C) standard language for the transformation of structured data. <link
                    linkend="bib9">[13]</link> XSLT transformation scripts take as input any valid
                XML document and produce as output an ASCII-formatted document (including XML, HTML,
                other formatting languages, free text, etc.). The XSLT language specifies
                transformations through declarative, rule-based commands (see below). </para>
            <para>XSLT is widely used in modern information processing, including in health care
                applications. Numerous XSLT transformation engines exist, including commercial and
                open-source versions. These implementations are mature, stable, and
                high-performance, and are available as runtime libraries or embedded in XLST
                authoring/editing applications. Excellent documentation and training are available
                for XSLT. </para>
            <para>XSLT scripts operate over source “trees” containing the structured contents
                of parsed XML documents. These trees contain as their nodes the various
                constructs of specific XML documents, i.e., the named elements, attributes, and
                text values that appear in the documents, and upon parsing, becomes a source
                tree for XSLT transformations.</para>
            <para>XSLT uses the sub-language “XPath” to reference portions of the XML source tree
                for purposes of navigating the tree and selecting specific parts of it to translate.
                    <link linkend="bib10">[14]</link> XPath is essentially a query language for
                identifying and retrieving XML sub-trees that match specified criteria. </para>
            <para>The actual transformation logic in XLST scripts is specified as a series of
                “templates”. Each template matches to a specified sub-part of the source tree
                and specifies what output will be generated for that sub-part. Templates are
                generally called from within other templates via a declarative template-matching
                process, and a recursive traversal and transformation of the input tree occurs
                through this template-invocation model. The transformation logic within
                templates may include various conditional, branching, and formatting constructs,
                as well as calls to external functions written in various programming languages
                (such as Java). </para>
                <para>XSLT is effective in representing and executing the transformation logic
                    needed for clinical translations. In general, XSLT provides various advantages,
                    as well as limitations, for this task. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A powerful language</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Declarative – automated matching of templates to data</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Extensible via extension functions and external function calls</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Many mature implementations</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Good tooling (e.g., Eclipse plugin, XMLSpy)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Good documentation</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Limitations</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Transformation specifications are verbose and hard to
                            read/understand/debug/maintain</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Transformations are entirely syntactic</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Limited to XML input – instances rendered in other formats cannot be
                            translated</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>FHIR Mapping Language</title>
            <para>The FHIR mapping language (FML) <link linkend="bib11">[15]</link> is a relatively
                new, bespoke transformation language specifically designed to transform HL7 FHIR
                resources to alternative representations, including different FHIR resources, C/CDE
                documents, etc. The mapping language was created by the FHIR Management Group as a
                specification of the QVT framework for model-transformation languages (see <xref
                    linkend="_Ref494462079"/>). </para>
                 <para>Conceptually, FML is similar to XSLT in that it (a) consists of declarative
                rules that are automatically matched to input data, (b) includes a sub-language
                (“FHIRPath”) to reference parts of source parse trees, and (c) has the ability to
                reference external functions written in different languages. There are also notable
                differences between FML and XSLT. The source input of FML is not limited to XML
                documents, but may include any object models and rendering syntaxes conformant with
                    <glossterm baseform="Object Management Group">OMG’s</glossterm>
                <glossterm baseform="Meta Object Facility">Meta Object Facility (MOF)</glossterm>
                language. <link linkend="bib12">[16]</link> MOF is a general formalism for
                representing object models as directed acyclic graphs (DAGs), and MOF-compliant
                models can use various syntactic constructs to represent the classes, attributes,
                and attribute values of such graphs. </para>
                <para>Hence, in FML, there is no built-in notion of source trees containing XML
                    “elements”, “attributes”, “comments”, “namespaces”, etc. In fact, FML
                    transformation rules do not specify any target syntax for inputs or outputs,
                    just the general concepts of named classes, class members, and member values.
                    This flexibility would allow transformation source inputs used in the
                    normalization to ANF to be represented in different formats than XML, were that
                    to be deemed preferable. For example, instances rendered using JSON, ODIN, or
                    ASN1 syntax could be the inputs of FML transformations. </para>
                <para>The output of an FML transformation is not a text-rendered document (unlike
                    XSLT), but an internally stored DAG consistent with the specified output model.
                    Subsequently, the DAG may be rendered in any number of syntaxes, including XML,
                    JSON, or the tables and fields of a relational database. </para>
            
                <para>The FHIR Mapping Language may also be effective in representing and executing
                    the transformation logic needed
                    for normalization to ANF. As with XSLT, however, there
                    exist certain trade-offs in its use.
                </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Support for input formats other than XML</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Transformation logic produces semantic DAGs, which can be subsequently
                            rendered in a variety of syntaxes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The mapping specifications are more concise and easier to
                            read/understand than XLST</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Limitations</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Inputs/outputs other than FHIR <glossterm baseform="Logical Model">logical models</glossterm> currently require
                            additional custom programming</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Only XML and JSON are currently supported as output syntaxes without
                            custom programming</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Only one implementation to date (as a library)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Limited tools for authoring/editing transformation scripts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Limited sources of documentation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Few knowledgeable programmers</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="_Ref494462079">
            <title>QVT</title>
            <para>A third alternative is to develop a new transformation language customized to
                support the requirements of a normalization to ANF, 
                based on the QVT language used to develop the FHIR Mapping Language. </para>
                <para>QVT <link linkend="bib13">[17]</link> is a general model-transformation
                framework and language developed by the Object Management Group. It includes both an
                imperative (“QVT-O”) and a declarative (“QVT-R”) version, and offers considerable
                flexibility in defining the constructs of purpose-specific transformation languages.
                Although QVT is intended for the transformation of data <emphasis>models</emphasis>
                rather than data instances, the FHIR Mapping Language shows that it can be applied
                to the latter task as well. </para>
                <para>A number of implementations of QVT exist as open-source and commercial
                    software offerings. These include: </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ATL (open source). Probably the most widely used and maintained of the
                            available implementations. Includes a library of existing QVT
                            transformations, to serve as examples and templates. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Eclipse M2M Project (open source). An Eclipse project that includes
                            authoring tools for QVT transformations, as well as various
                            transformation engines (including the one from ATL). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ModelMorf (proprietary)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Others (see <link linkend="bib13">[17]</link>) </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages</emphasis></para>
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>QVT is very abstract, which confers great
                        flexibility and configurability to create custom transformation languages.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Limitations</emphasis></para>
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>The abstractness also makes QVT quite difficult to understand and learn,
                        and there are limited resources to assist in the learning process.</para>
                </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
            <!-- MDMI  -->

            <title>Model Driven Message Interoperability (MDMI)</title>

            <para>MDMI is an Object Management Group Standard for the transformation of data in one
                format to data in another format. MDMI Standard is not a language. The MDMI Standard
                is a specification for addressing this problem and was developed by multiple domain
                experts. The specification contains two major sections: the MDMI Transformation
                Metamodel and the MDMI Semantic Element Exchange Repository (SEER). </para>

            <figure xml:id="transformation_mdmi_standard_0135">
                <title>MDMI Standard</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/mdmi_standard.png" align="center" format="png" width="100%" scale="70"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <caption>
                    <para><emphasis>The MDMI Transformation Metamodel.</emphasis></para>
                </caption>
            </figure>

            <para>
                The MDMI Transformation Metamodel is composed of a syntax model and a semantic model. The syntax model contains the syntactical representation of each data element in a format and the semantic model contains the semantic concept represented by the data element. The syntax model is used to compose a collection of semantic representations into a target file format or to decompose a source file into its semantic representations. The syntax model can be used for any format. XML, JSON, HL7 V.2, CVS, various EDI payment, and proprietary formats have been used.
            </para>

            <para>
                The semantic model captures the semantic concepts in the format and the relationships between the semantic concepts in a format. Probably the most important relationship is the containership relationships. The semantic model of the MDMI is also used to capture other relationships and rules required to create unambiguous semantic representations. An example of this is a data element that can have multiple semantics concepts that must be disambiguated based on other values contained in format. 
            </para>

            <para>The MDMI SEER is a repository for the semantically unique concepts, called
                Business Elements, that are exchanged in healthcare transformations. One can view
                the MDMI SEER as a bag of unique, atomic semantic concepts exchanged, primarily
                driven by the <glossterm baseterm="HL7 V2 Messaging Profile">HL7 standards of v.2</glossterm>, <glossterm baseform="HL7 Clinical Document Architecture">CDA</glossterm>, and FHIR that are used to exchange
                information. If there is a new semantic concept that does not exist in the SEER,
                then a new Business Element is simply added. Each MDMI Transformation Model uses the
                MDMI SEER to create an iso-semantic relationship with its own semantic concepts and
                a Business Element. </para>

            <figure xml:id="transformation_mdmi_process_0135">
                <title>MDMI Transformation Process</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/mdmi_transformation_process.png" align="center" format="png" width="100%" scale="70"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <caption><para><emphasis>The MDMI Transformation Process</emphasis></para></caption>
            </figure>


            <para> There is a project underway in the OMG to extend the MDMI SEER. The Business
                Elements in the MDMI SEER are <glossterm baseform="Pre-coordinated concept"
                    >pre-coordinated semantic concepts</glossterm> represented in industry standard
                healthcare ontologies and terminologies. The project is using the ANF Statement
                Model as a Reference Model to develop a semantic model that can precisely define the
                meaning of the Business Element in a detailed, structured, unambiguous, computable
                formalism. </para>

            <para>An open source implementation of MDMI started in the Open Healthcare Tools
                organization which built an MDMI compliant tooling for healthcare. The MDMI Open
                Source Project continues today in GitHub and has been and is being used in HL7
                projects as well as in commercial implementations. </para>


        

            <para>MDMI is a model driven approach. Having a formal model, the open source project
                has been able to develop tooling based on the MDMI model as well as leverage other
                modeling efforts. Examples are Information Models such as FHIR and the
                <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190717T182730-0500" comment="From Stephanie K:

Probably should define FHIM since it hasn&apos;t been used previously in the document and/or include in the glossary."?>FHIM<?oxy_comment_end?>
                using the model driven MDHT tooling and Ontological Models such as ANF / <glossterm baseform="Solor">Solor</glossterm>. </para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">Advantages</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Any-to-Any transformations versus point-to-point language mappings
                        allow reuse of transformation models for different use cases.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>It minimizes change. If one MDMI Model changes (e.g. FHIR 4 to FHIR 5), this does not require changes to other existing MDMI Models such as CCDA 2.1, HL7 V2.8, or a proprietary model.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>It simplifies development. Tooling exists to develop and maintain individual MDMI Models by SMEs who do not need to be developers. The scope of expertise is further reduced because the knowledge one needs to create a MDMI Model is primary to know what the data in their format means. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>It enables automation tooling for creating MDMI models, for creating computable artifacts, and generating reports.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>There are Open Source Models for HL7 formats as well as the MDMI tooling.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Limitations</emphasis></para>
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>MDMI has limited experience with transformations of detailed clinical models.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>User Documentation of MDMI is lacking.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The MDMI runtime tool is complex.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    
                </itemizedlist>

        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
