<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    
    <title>Reading for Proposed Background Section *DELETE BEFORE SUBMISSION*</title>
    
    <xi:include href="standards.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="cem_model.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="cimi_model.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="clinical-data-elements-article.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    
    <section>
        <title>Excerpts from Post-Coordination Paper from Komet Repo </title>
        <para>Background</para>
        <para>Although very useful, post-coordination creates a number of practical challenges for
            information systems that support this capability. The foremost challenge, and the one
            that has been most studied, is the design of user interfaces that enable clinicians to
            create post-coordinated expressions efficiently, intuitively, and in a manner that is
            consistent with the SNOMED CT terminology model. However, another important set of challenges
            pertain to the management of post-coordinated expressions after they have been specified
            by clinicians. These management tasks include the appropriate persistence of
            post-coordinated observations in a patient database and efficient subsumption testing
            against records that include post-coordinated observations. This report addresses those
            data-management challenges, which include:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Determining the degree of transformation and normalization to apply to
                    post-coordinated expressions when they are persisted in a database. What
                    transformations and normalizations appropriately balance the needs of storage
                    efficiency, retrieval performance, terminology evolution, and medicolegal
                    requirements?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Determining the specific structure and syntax for representing
                    post-coordinated expressions when they are persisted in a database. What
                    structure and syntax appropriately balance the needs of storage efficiency,
                    retrieval performance, interoperability, and software evolution?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Determining the appropriate way to represent the contextual modifiers for
                    observations within post-coordinated expressions. For example, representing
                    modifiers that indicate whether an observation is a current diagnosis for the
                    patient, a past medical problem of the patient, or a disorder in the patient’s
                    family history.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Determining appropriate strategies for optimizing the performance of
                    subsumption testing against post-coordinated expressions (a critical but
                    inherently costly operation). Potential strategies include maintaining a
                    transitive closure of the SNOMED CT hierarchy and incorporating post-coordinated
                    concepts into the SNOMED CT terminology model (“just-in-time pre-coordination”).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Other Lit Review</title>
        <para>**********5.4.2019. RC -<emphasis> I perused references that may be relevant to the
                background. The following is textual excerpts which I cut &amp; pasted from the
                various references..</emphasis>**********</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Following text is from DCM Ballot of September 2010
                Introduction: </emphasis></para>
        <para>From &lt;<link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Detailed_Clinical_Models"
                >http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Detailed_Clinical_Models</link>> </para>
        <para> "Increasingly, the hypothesis is uttered that data from an EHR can be reused for
            other purposes, such as continuity of care and decision support on the individual level,
            and quality measurement, management of healthcare institutions, epidemiology, among
            other purposes for secondary data use, based on comparison of populations and healthcare
            systems. Such hypothesis can only be confirmed if certain conditions are met. One sine
            qua non condition is adherence to privacy regulations and data security measures. That
            is assumed here, but not explored further. Another assumption is that the data to be
            aggregated are comparable indeed. That is the driving assumption for this standard,
            because it does require preciseness in meaning and in use in applications. The third
            assumption is that each purpose on an aggregate level requires its own context to be
            taken into account for valid and reliable decision making. In particular, algorithms,
            calculations for proper data handling, but also potential influencing factors. For
            management data management from EHR for instance, one needs to have knowledge on the
            architecture of the building in which care takes place, the workforce and so on. If data
            are interpreted for quality measurement, one needs to be aware of case-mix and
            regulations to interpret scores properly. For epidemiology, the characteristics of the
            population are core for proper interpretation of study data.</para>
        <para> All purposes, both on clinical and aggregate levels, have in common that the
            semantics, the context, the care process, and the use in decision making determine how
            data are collected, stored, managed in an EHR and communicated.</para>
        <para>Healthcare is used to classifications and terminologies to help in purposes of data
            collection. To a large extend, classifications can be seen as mainly developed for the
            aggregate purposes, and terminologies for clinical data in the EHR. However, these
            functions are more and more overlapping. Similarly, we see assessment sheets for
            clinical practice and registry forms, like minimum data sets, for the data collection.
            We also see that information modeling is applied as tool to organize data in healthcare
            information technology in general, and the EHR in particular. Two core examples are the
            Health Level Seven Reference Information Model, and the IS 13606-1 reference
            information model for the Electronic Health Record.</para>
        <para> The underlying assumption for this standard on Detailed Clinical Models is that to
            use, exchange and reuse data, and to obtain meaningful information from it for each
            purpose, data need to be handled consistently. This consistent use is required on both
            the mono and multidisciplinary health professional level. But of course, consistency is
            not only necessary at the human level, but also at systems level such as the EHR itself,
            data exchange for continuity of care, and data warehouses or registries where the
            aggregated data are stored."</para>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Following text is from this 2012 Word Doc I found on a Google
                search. It looks like a CIMI document? </emphasis><link
                xlink:href="http://informatics.mayo.edu/CIMI/images/5/5b/CIMI_Informatics-Modeling_Terms%2C_Tools_and_Their_iEHR_Use.docx"
                >http://informatics.mayo.edu/CIMI/images/5/5b/CIMI_Informatics-Modeling_Terms%2C_Tools_and_Their_iEHR_Use.docx</link></para>
        <para>"Archetype advocates may argue that DCMs, without a reference model, can be
            inconsistent across organizations; while, DCM advocates may argue that archetypes have
            implementation details in their “PIMs.” </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This implies that, the openEHR and CIMI Reference Models (RMs) start with
                        the universe of possible classes (and data elements (is this true for
                        archetype data elements?)); then, they are constrained-down to meet specific
                        clinical domain requirements; while, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DCMs start with nothing or with subsets of classes from the FHIM or HL7
                        RIM; then, the class attributes are augmented by domain-specific and
                        implementation-paradigm inheritance. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>CIMI productivity and reusability will be limited till its partners converge
                    on consistent informatics terms and model representations, processes,
                    governance, configuration management, system-of-record repository, and
                    “isosemantic” model transformations. The proposed OMG </para>
                <para>AML</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> (Archetype Modeling Language) profile for UML, which includes ADL like
                    features, to constrain models, is intended to help catalyze sharing of
                    isosemantically equivalent ADL and UML models. The objective of OMG’s AML UML
                    profile is to to support the CIMI modeling requirements. </para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>AML supports model-to-model transformations (ADL or CDL archetypes
                                to UML and vice-a-versa)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>AML UML specifications support MDHT and commercial tool venders to
                                include the AML UML-Profile</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>OMG has already created a profile to support NIEM called NIEM
                                UML</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>NIEM UML is not sufficient to create healthcare models; but, AML
                                UML will subsume NIEM UML</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Models based upon AML can be transformed into other modeling
                                paradigms and structures</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>AML to ADL, CDL, CDA, NIEM, XML, JSON, IDL, etc.</para>
                                    <para>Other modeling paradigms can be transformed into a subset
                                        of AML models</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>AML includes ADL, CDL, CDA, NIEM constructs</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>This paper will be periodically updated to facilitate understanding-of-differences as
            we harmonize CIMI processes and products required to efficiently support the CIMI goal
            of international reusable models. </para>
        <para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="clip_image001_-1649578188.png" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
                               contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>Figure 3: Archetype Modeling Language (AML) UML-Profile</para>
        <para>AML Profile Requirements-Specification Capability exceeds the capabilities of ADL, CDA
            &amp; NIEM; noting that</para>
        <para>Transformation among models and implementation of models are done separately (e.g., by
            MDHT)"</para>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">The following is from a paper by William Goossen:
                "</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Detailed Clinical Models: Representing Knowledge,
                Data and Semantics in Healthcare Information Technology" </emphasis><emphasis
                role="bold">From</emphasis> &lt;<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/"
                >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/</link>> </para>
        <para>"In the early nineties, a group of smart scientists in the area of health informatics
            invented an approach to the development of EHRs which was called two level modeling
                [<link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/#B4"
                >4</link>]. In this approach, the generic functions of record systems, such as
            entering, storing, presenting, managing, communicating, and adding generic data, such as
            patient name and ID, location, time, professional (e.g., through the login), where
            separated out from the clinical details. And, these clinical details can be millions,
            and only need specific descriptions to distinguish these from each other. <link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/figure/F1/">Figure
                1</link> illustrates the distinction [<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/#B5">5</link>].<mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="clip_image002_2092618099.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
                               contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para> </para>
        <para>From &lt;<link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/"
                >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/</link>> </para>
        <para> With the DCM approach the benefits of the two level modeling are respected and the
            enormous efforts that went into the clinical modeling efforts are also acknowledged. The
            idea dates back to 2007 where during a workshop, an overarching approach called Detailed
            Clinical Modeling emerged, using a term from Huff et al. [<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/#B1">1</link>].
            This approach takes the commonalties of the various specifications to keep the
            conceptual descriptions and the logical models of data elements, code binding,
            relationships, data type specifications and such [<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/#B9">9</link>].
            However, it does not go to the level of physical specification, and even, the logical
            model can easily be converted to reference model based approaches as Health Level 7
            Reference Information Model (HL7 RIM) or OpenEHR or reference models.</para>
        <para> Due to the interoperability issues among these clinical modeling approaches and the
            investments already made, there currently is an approach trying to harmonize the
            existing work. This is carried out by the Clinical Information Modeling Initiative
            (CIMI). Their goal is to create a harmonized reference model for clinical knowledge
            models using both the ADL and UML formalisms. From these baseline formats, any kind of
            technical artifact can potentially be derived. CIMI also works on an EHR clinical model
            repository as open content. However, in practice, with all good intentions, CIMI has
            created yet another reference model and yet another dialect of ADL. Nevertheless, other
            initiatives seem to start picking these harmonization results up.</para>
        <para> Concept level: example Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS)</para>
        <para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="clip_image003_-406149578.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
                               contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>Finally, the UML representation of a DCM is shown (<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/figure/F7/">Figure
                7</link>) and a preliminary representation using the recent HL7 Fast Healthcare
            Interoperability Resources (FHIR) approach (<link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/figure/F8/">Figure
                8</link>). Note that a DCM can be expressed in any logical modeling method. UML is
            just for the illustration of the commonalties and differences. An example DCM is
            represented in <link
                xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4141130/figure/F7/">Figure
                7</link>, using UML."<mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="clip_image004_60462841.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
                               contentdepth="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject></para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
