<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Introduction<?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T093902-0400" comment="Note from Keith: For the ANF document, we should somewhere describe assumptions about what an ANF implementation requires. For example, ANF requires an ability to classify topic expressions (and expressions that may go in other locations). Maybe a section that describes the requirements of a &quot;mapping&quot; based system with a plethora of statement models, and then what ANF requires above and beyond a mapping system, and what the benefits are. 
Re-using some of the work in the interoperability paper is probably wise. I think a distillation of key concepts should be part of the HL7 ballot document. We need to motivate why an ANF approch is necessary as opposed to the status quo.
"?><?oxy_comment_end?></title>
  <section>
    <title>Acknowledgements </title>
    <para>The project team would like to acknowledge the contributions and assistance received from
      the following:</para>
  </section>
  <section> <title>Motivation</title> 
  <para>Health care organizations are striving to become high reliability organizations (HROs),
      characterized by high levels of safety under inherently risky, technologically-complex, and
      demanding conditions.( <link
        xlink:href="https://www.healthit.gov/sites/default/files/medstar_hit_safety_1_29_v2.pdf"
        >https://www.healthit.gov/sites/default/files/medstar_hit_safety_1_29_v2.pdf</link>) Chassin
      and Loeb published a conceptual framework for assessing progress towards becoming a HRO and
      included the safe use of health IT and review of quality measures, which are dependent on data
      from Electronic Health Record (EHR) systems. (<link
        xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3790522/"
        >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3790522/</link>) Deployment of EHR systems is
      nearly ubiquitous in the US and there is increasing opportunity to leverage a substantial
      number of extant EHR mapped data sets to improve population health through quality measures,
      case reporting, and decision support. </para>
    <para>Pragmatically, these electronic tools are implemented by manually mapping the right
      clinical data stated in specifications from the right sources in the EHR to generate a report.
      While there are published, standardized specifications of measures, reports, and alerts with
      machine-readable, human-readable, and value set specifications, there is currently vast
      variation seen in implementations of these tools across the healthcare system (refs xxx). Some
      of this variation is due to discrepancies in how implementers of these reports interpret the
      expression-logic of specifications. However, even if the implementations of query logic were
      standardized there is still existing variation in the representation of how clinical data
      within an EHR is organized, the clinical terminology that is applied, the value range that is
      valid, which units of measurement may be used, and which data values are required (<link
        xlink:href="http://www.snu-dhpm.ac.kr/pds/files/1-s2.0-S1386505612001906-main.pdf"
        >http://www.snu-dhpm.ac.kr/pds/files/1-s2.0-S1386505612001906-main.pdf</link>). </para>
    <para>To assist with these challenges, The Clinical Information Modeling Initiative (CIMI) is an
      HL7 group that is defining a library of de- tailed clinical information models using a common
      modeling formalism. CIMI was established to improve the interoperability of healthcare
      information systems through shared implementable clinical information models that can be used
      to generate platform-specific model specifications such as FHIR profiles or CDA templates.
      These models are grouped into semantically equivalent (or ‘isosemantic’) families of clinical
      models, which capture the same clinical meaning using different combinations of concept
      pre-coordination and corresponding information model structure. The central focus of the CIMI
      Reference Model is the Clinical Statement. A Clinical Statement represents structured
      electronic communication made about a patient typically documented as an 'entry' in the
      patient record. For example, Clinical Statement can be used to represent the following
      statements made about a patient. This can be the statement of a condition being present, a
      request for a procedure to be done, the results of lab tests or the patient’s family history
      of cancer.<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Patient has a diagnosis of congestive heart failure</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Patient has a family history of breast cancer</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Patient has a goal of smoking cessation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Patient has an order for Physical Therapy</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Patient had an appendectomy</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>Let's consider the following example for blood pressure measurement and the clinical
      statement that may be entered to represent this information.</para>
    <para>“Systolic blood pressure 120 mmHg, taken on right brachial artery, using adult size blood
      pressure cuff, patient in sitting position for at least 5 minutes, urinated no more than 30
      minutes prior to measurement”. For the user, this would be the easiest way to document the
      measurement. However, the various parts of information about the body site, the blood pressure
      cuff, patient position etc. would be lost to any attempt of data retrieval. Rather than
      selecting this information all at once with a single item, the user could choose the various
      parts of information pertinent to the blood pressure measurement in various ways. </para>
    <para>Clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into their organization’s EHR
      systems. Clinical statements can be expressed and documented in many different ways in EHR
      systems, where Clinical Input Forms provide different options to document the same clinical
      statement. These differences pose challenges for data retrieval, data analysis and data
      analysts in their attempts to extract accurate clinical analysis results. </para>
    <para>Clinicians enter clinical statements into their organization’s EHR typically in a manner
      that we call here structured data capture, or the manner in which information is presented to
      the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by constraining the information to allow
      only certain values to be entered, e.g. through a drop-down list or radio button, or breaking
      up large chunks of related information into smaller parts.</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">The following examples illustrate Structured
          Data Capture:</emphasis></emphasis></para>
    <para><emphasis>Systolic Blood Pressure 120 mmHg, taken on right brachial artery, using BP cuff
        adult size, patient in sitting position for at least 5 minutes, urinated not more than 30
        minutes prior to measurement</emphasis></para>
    <para>The current guidance for blood pressure measurements for adults includes the body site,
      the blood pressure cuff size to use as well as some prerequisites. The patient should be in a
      sitting position for at least 5 minutes and should have urinated no more than 30 minutes
      before the measurement.</para>
    <para>For example, a EHR could display a text field for the result and lists of choices for the
      body site:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Right brachial artery</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Left brachial artery</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Or it could be diplayed with the site and allow further refinement to specify the
      laterality:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Brachial artery</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Right</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Left</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In addition to specifiying the body site a list of choices for the blood pressure cuff
      size used would also be selected, for example:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Adult size Small</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Adult size Medium</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Adult size Large</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The same could be true for the display and documentation option for the patient position
      (sitting yes/no, how long, urinated yes/no, how long prior to measurement), which could differ
      between systems. There are different ways the measurement result could be entered into a form
      in an EHR. Display options for the user could be, e.g. a text field to enter the measurement
      result (e.g. 120 mmHg) with the label of the complete guideline. </para>
    <para>Ideally,clinical information is modeled in a manner that is most efficient for use. This is
      a problem because there are many different use cases for clinical information with a wide
      range of requirements. There is no single model that can be the most efficient model for all
      the various use cases. Maximum efficiency for each use case necessitates that any particular
      clinical information be available in multiple modeled forms. These models, although different
      in form, semantically represent the same information, and are known as isosemantic models. Any
      particular detailed clinical model exists within a family of isosemantic siblings. </para>
    <para>Different isosemantic models can support different purposes, such as clinical data input,
      clinical data storage, clinical data querying, clinical data analysis, and modeler preference. </para>
    <para>Here, we introduce a new isosemantic representation that is designed to aid in the
      analysis of clinical information and will represent one member in each isosemantic family of
      detailed clinical models. This representation is called Analysis Normal Form (ANF). A FHIR
      implementation guide can eventually be developed. </para>
    <para>ANF is not necessarily a physical structure, but is how a data analyst might see the data
      when they are looking at it in a database, and not as clinicians would see it in the user
      interface (i.e., structured data capture). </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
      <listitem>
        <para>Clinician collects data &#x21D2; Clinical Input Form</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data is normalized &#x21D2; Transformation process from CIF to ANF  &#x21D2; Representable/storable in multiple types of databases.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data analyst who is using or querying the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or working on prevalence statistics) &#x21D2; ANF (it is how the data is represented or stored in the database; must know enough about the data to know what is stored in the topic vs. what is stored as a result or detail)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The goal of ANF is to enable analysts to understand the data and how it is stored in lieu
      of having to teach them about the thousands of ways data can be entered and ensure the data
      that has to be expressed, can be expressed in an operable and scalable way. The more that data
      is normalized, the simpler it will become to analyze, and the likelihood of analysis errors
      will be reduced. Without the ANF, the probability of patient safety risks is increased.</para>
    <para>The following document will discuss how the ANF Model provides the clinical data
      normalization capabilities to support accurate data retrieval and analysis.</para>
  </section>
  <section><title> Purpose </title>
    <para>The purpose of ANF is as follows xxx</para><para> </para> <section><title> Concrete Objectives </title>
     <para> </para>   </section>
    <section>
      <title> Usage</title> <para> </para>
    </section>  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190507T221927-0400" comment="Add historical context of CIMI modeling efforts"?>Background<?oxy_comment_end?>
    </title>
    <para>Clinical Event Model </para>
    <para>Clinical Element Model</para>
    <para>OpenEHR</para>
    <para>13606</para>
    <para>HL7v3</para>
    <para>CDA</para>
    <para>DCMs</para>
    <para>FHIR</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Scope</title>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T094055-0400" comment="Joey Coyle:
Do you want this for later sections, or do you want to explain it here?
"?>This
      document will present the specification of the Analysis Normal Form (ANF), how it is used to
      create detailed clinical models (DCMs), and how it differs
      from<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T105315-0400" comment="KC: Work with Joey and Ioana on what this is exactly;"?>
      CIMI's current standard modeling paradigm<?oxy_comment_end?>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
