<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Introduction<?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T093902-0400" comment="Note from Keith: For the ANF document, we should somewhere describe assumptions about what an ANF implementation requires. For example, ANF requires an ability to classify topic expressions (and expressions that may go in other locations). Maybe a section that describes the requirements of a &quot;mapping&quot; based system with a plethora of statement models, and then what ANF requires above and beyond a mapping system, and what the benefits are. 
Re-using some of the work in the interoperability paper is probably wise. I think a distillation of key concepts should be part of the HL7 ballot document. We need to motivate why an ANF approch is necessary as opposed to the status quo.
"?><?oxy_comment_end?></title>
  <section>
    <title>Acknowledgements </title>
    <para>The project team would like to acknowledge the contributions and assistance received from
      the following:<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Keith E. Campbell</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Richard Esmond</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Tim Williams</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Raja A. Cholan</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Ioana Singureanu</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Joey Coyle</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Walter Sujansky</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Werner Ceusters</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Kirsten Haake</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Andy Wang</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Benson Chang</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Motivation
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190529T090453-0400" comment="KC: 5/28/19: We want to try to introduce the concept of high reliability systems, and high reliability data management. One of things to emphasize, figuring out how to normalize the data in a high reliability framework in mind. They hire every terminology mapping provider who is out there, compare the results, and then abstract out generalized part of data to work off of. We are trying to set a higher bar. Then, reference that when we talk about transformations. Patient safety implications for the transforms…"?></title><?oxy_comment_end?>
    <section>
      <title>Context</title>
       <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190601T180110-0500" comment="What is the purpose of the Context
       Section, and how is that different than the Representation of Clinical Statement section below. Context seems to state models are represented in every which way, and so do the following sections.  Also the clinical statement and the structured clinical imput section seem to have overlapping information."?><?oxy_comment_end?>
      <para>Health care organizations are striving to become high reliability organizations (HROs),
        characterized by high levels of safety under inherently risky, technologically-complex, and
        demanding conditions.<citation>HRO_HIT</citation> Chassin and Loeb published a conceptual
        framework for assessing progress towards becoming a HRO and included the safe use of health
        IT and review of quality measures, which are dependent on data from Electronic Health Record
        (EHR) systems.<citation>Chassin</citation> Deployment of EHR systems is nearly ubiquitous in
        the US and there is increasing opportunity to leverage a substantial number of extant EHR
        mapped data sets to improve population health through quality measures, case reporting, and
        decision support. </para>
      <para>Pragmatically, these electronic tools are implemented by manually mapping EHR clinical data to 
        the appropriate clinical data stated in specifications to generate a
        report. While there are published, standardized specifications of measures, reports, and
        alerts with machine-readable, human-readable, and value set specifications, there is
        currently vast variation seen in implementations of these tools across the healthcare system
          .<citation>concepts</citation><citation>Cholan_specs</citation><citation>lookback</citation><citation>Hemler</citation><citation>Dorr</citation>
        Some of this variation is due to discrepancies in how implementers of these reports
        interpret the expression-logic of specifications. However, even if the implementations of
        query logic were standardized there is still existing variation in the representation of how
        clinical data within an EHR is organized, the clinical terminology that is applied, the
        value range that is valid, which units of measurement may be used, and which data values are
          required.<citation>DCM_Quality</citation>
         <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190601T180110-0500" comment="I'm not following the flow here.
          What do you mean my interpret the expression-logic of specifications, and how that jumps to query logic"?><?oxy_comment_end?>

      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190601T180110-0500" comment="Started editing the following sections,
      but realized we may need a different direction.  Would be better to clearly separate and present the fact that there are 
      data structures with properties and there is terminology. Both can be be pre and post-coordinated. Clinical information can exist either at the data structure property level or the terminology level or a mix of both.  Then show the infinite
      variations a modeler can choose"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
      <title>Representation of Clinical Statements</title>
      <para>To assist with these challenges, The Clinical Information Modeling Initiative (CIMI) is
        an HL7 group that is defining a library of detailed clinical information models using a
        common modeling formalism. CIMI was established to improve the interoperability of
        healthcare information systems through shared implementable clinical information models that
        can be used to generate platform-specific model specifications such as FHIR profiles,CDA
        templates, OpenEHR Archetypes, 13606 Archetypes, ISO DCMs, or Intermountain CEMs. These CIMI 
        models are grouped into semantically equivalent (or ‘isosemantic’) families
        of detailed clinical models, which capture the same clinical meaning using different
        combinations of concept pre and post-coordination and corresponding information model structure. The
        central focus of the CIMI Reference Model is the Clinical Statement. A Clinical Statement
        represents structured electronic communication made about a patient typically documented as
        an 'entry' in the patient record. For example, Clinical Statement can be used to represent
        the following statements made about a patient. This can be the statement of a condition
        being present, a request for a procedure to be done, the results of lab tests or the
        patient’s family history of cancer.  
        <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190601T180110-0500" comment="I think platform-specific is not really correct, maybe just be more generic and say something like other modeling specifications"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Patient has a diagnosis of congestive heart failure</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Patient has a family history of breast cancer</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Patient has a goal of smoking cessation</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Patient has an order for Physical Therapy</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Patient had an appendectomy</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>Let's consider the following example for blood pressure measurement and the clinical
        statement that may be entered to represent this information.
      </para>
      <para>"Systolic blood pressure 120 mmHg, taken on the right brachial artery".</para>
      <para>For the user, the easiest way to document the measurement is in narrative text. However,
        the various parts of information about the artery, laterality, or measurement would require 
        natural language processing and would be lost to any attempt of data retrieval. Another option to
        document the measurement would be to choose various parts of information
        pertinent to the blood pressure measurement and arrange them in various states of 
        pre and post-coordination.
      </para>
      <para>"Systolic blood pressure taken on the right brachial artery" = 120 mmHG</para>
      <para>"Systolic blood pressure" 'body location'='brachial artery' 
        'body location laterality'='right' = 120 mmHG
      </para>
      <para>Because CIMI defines several different isosemantic detailed clinical models, there is
        currently a decreased chance that modelers of clinical statements apply pre and post-coordinated
        terminology concepts and models consistently. </para>
      <para>Let's consider the same example with additional information about the blood pressure
        cuff:</para>
      <para>“Systolic blood pressure 120 mmHg, taken on right brachial artery, using adult size
        blood pressure cuff”. </para>
      <para>One modeler may choose to structure this as one complex clinical statement (or a
        compound clinical statement) with various concepts and consituent expressions included
        within in it.  This is also referred to as 'compositionality' in which a complex statement
        is determined by the meanings of its constituent expressions and rules used to combine them.
        In other words, some compound clinical statements should in fact be broken down into a
        number of simpler clinical statements to improve reproducibility of the detailed clinical
        model. 
      </para>
      <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190601T180110-0500" comment="This is not a good example for this, as I don't think anyone would model this as a compound set of individual statements, as none of these extra elements can stand alone, and instead are clearly qualifiers."?><?oxy_comment_end?>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190529T090042-0400" comment="Clinical Input Form is one that has value in preserving but per Joey, we should not confuse CIF with CIMI models. So how do we articulate these all in a coherent way?"?>Structured<?oxy_comment_end?>
        Clinical Input</title>
      <para>Not only is there a potential for a lack of consistency with representing clinical
        statements with current detailed clinical modeling efforts, but there is also further
        variation in how the data is entered into information systems by end-users. Clinicians
        author clinical statements and enter them into their organization’s EHR systems as
        "Structured Clinical Input". This concept describes any data entry mechanism used by
        clinicians to record clinical statements. An instance of a clinical statement may be created
        using one or more forms. Vendors compete on usability for seamless Structured Clinical Input
        but, in some cases, structured clinical statement are based on standard-based models (e.g.
        CIMI, openEHR archetypes, etc.) but they may also be based on proprietary models. For the
        purposes of this document, the type or usability of data structure used for capture or
        display of clinical statements is not in scope. We assume that <emphasis role="bold">any
          suitably encoded</emphasis> structured clinical statement may be suitable for
        normalization for analysis. </para>
      <para>Therefore, clinical statements can be expressed and documented in many different ways in
        EHR systems, where input forms provide different options to document the same clinical
        statement. These differences pose challenges for how the data is modeled, how the data is
        stored, and therefore has implications on data retrieval, data analysis,accuracy of clinical
        analysis results. </para>
      <para>Clinicians enter clinical statements into their organization’s EHR typically in a manner
        that we call here structured clinical input, or the manner in which information is presented
        to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by constraining the information to
        allow only certain values to be entered, e.g. through a drop-down list or radio button, or
        breaking up large chunks of related information into smaller parts.</para>
      <para>For example, a EHR could display a text field for the result and lists of choices for
        the body site:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Right brachial artery</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Left brachial artery</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Or it could be diplayed with the site and allow further refinement to specify the
        laterality:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Brachial artery</para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Right</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Left</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>In addition to specifiying the body site a list of choices for the blood pressure cuff
        size used would also be selected, for example:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem spacing="compact">
          <para>Adult size Small</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Adult size Medium</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Adult size Large</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The same could be true for the display and documentation option for the patient position
        (sitting yes/no, how long, urinated yes/no, how long prior to measurement), which could
        differ between systems. There are different ways the measurement result could be entered
        into a form in an EHR. Display options for the user could be, e.g. a text field to enter the
        measurement result (e.g. 120 mmHg) with the label of the complete guideline. </para>
      <para>The following is an example of two distinct user interfaces for capturing a set of
        “clinical statements" related to Blood Pressure. </para>
      <figure>
        <title> Blood Pressure Statement recorded using structured clinical statement 1</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/BP data capture.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
              contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title> Blood Pressure Statement recorded using structured clinical statement 2</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/EHR-2.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
              contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>In the first wireframe, the structured clinical input has separate drop down constraints
        to enter the artery and laterality as distinct concepts. In the second wireframe, the
        structured clinical input has combined the artery and laterality into a compond concept.
        This variation present in the structured clinical input may also have implications on the
        how the clinical statement is modeled. </para>
      <para>Ideally,clinical information is modeled in a manner that is most efficient for use. This
        is a problem because there are many different use cases for clinical information with a wide
        range of requirements. There is no single model that can be the most efficient model for all
        the various use cases. Maximum efficiency for each use case necessitates that any particular
        clinical information be available in multiple modeled forms. These models, although
        different in form, semantically represent the same information, and are known as isosemantic
        models. Any particular detailed clinical model exists within a family of isosemantic
        siblings. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title> Purpose
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190529T235034-0400" comment="RC Suggestion: We should probably mention that there is a goal to normalize data in a high reliability framework in mind. "?></title><?oxy_comment_end?>
    <para>Here, we introduce a new isosemantic representation that is designed to aid in the
      analysis of clinical information and will represent one member in each isosemantic family of
      detailed clinical models. This representation is called Analysis Normal Form (ANF). A FHIR
      implementation guide can eventually be developed. </para>
    <para>ANF is not necessarily a physical structure, but is how a data analyst might see the data
      when they are looking at it in a database, and not as clinicians would see it in the user
      interface (i.e., structured data capture). </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Clinician collects data &#x21D2; Clinical Input Form</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data is normalized &#x21D2; Transformation process from Structured Clinical Input to
          ANF &#x21D2; Representable/storable in multiple types of databases.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data analyst who is using or querying the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or working
          on prevalence statistics) &#x21D2; ANF (it is how the data is represented or stored in the
          database; must know enough about the data to know what is stored in the topic vs. what is
          stored as a result or detail)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The goal of ANF is to enable analysts to understand the data and how it is stored in lieu
      of having to teach them about the thousands of ways data can be entered and ensure the data
      that has to be expressed, can be expressed in an operable and scalable way. The more that data
      is normalized, the simpler it will become to analyze, and the likelihood of analysis errors
      will be reduced. Without the ANF, the probability of patient safety risks is increased.</para>
    <para>ANF aims to allow highly postcoordinated compositional terminologies to provide greater
      content coverage in a complete and consistent way than terminology content that is restricted
      to relying on precoordinated concepts. While postcoordinated compositional terminologies can
      be expressively powerful, they may generate expressions whose  equivalency cannot be easily
      determined. ANF aims to assist by providing comparable data in a normalized manner with
      respect to the content and semantics. Ideally, precoordinated experssions should retain the
      same representational structure as postcoordinated expressions. What is required with
      knowledge representation of postcoordinated compositional statements is the ability to
      faithfully expand from a reduced form or compare to other statemetns with ease and no loss of
      semantic integrity. Elkin wrote about what is needed in order for postcoordinated statements
      to be comparable and captured one of ANF's key objectives: "to be a formal terminological
      composition and decomposition mechanism for lossless information representation such that both
      explicit and implicit information can be faithfully recovered, maintained, and modified with
      ease." (Elkin, pg 14) </para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">purpose of ANF</emphasis> is suggested as follows:</para>
    <para>The purpose of ANF is to provide precise semantic consistent data and terminology
      specification that are comparable and sharable between multiple care providers, health
      enterprises and standards-based Healthcare Information Technology (HIT).</para>
    <para>ANF can be used for multiple objectives. Examples of such objectives are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>clinical data collection and communication</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>clinical care</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>continuity of care</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>electronic exchange of information</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>lifetime storage and retrieval linked to the context in which this took place</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>quality measurement</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>research</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>management and policy making</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>aggregation of data for other purposes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>among others.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>ANF is intended to be agnostic or neutral with respect to reference model and platform.
      For ANF to be used in applications, it needs to be transformed into platform specific
      artefacts, for example HL7 FHIR Resources.</para>
    <section>
      <title> Concrete Objectives </title>
      <para>ANF specifies clinical information for one or more sets of clinical concepts and their
        corresponding data elements and terminology. This with the goal of supporting the semantic
        interoperability between standards and technologies by means of representing<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the topic,</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>the circumstance,</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>the measure and result,</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>interpretation of values and ranges,</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title> Usage</title>
      <para>Overall, ANF supports the following functions:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for use in EHR</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for use in HL7 messages, FHIR and CDA</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for User Interfaces</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for use in Medical Devices</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for use as Quality Measures and National Registries</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content and knowledge for use in Healthcare Guidelines and
            Protocols</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for use in Medical, Health Care and Epidemiological
            Research</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify clinical content for use in Clinical Decision Support Systems</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>such that these specifications on the same concept are consistent for all these
        functions that it tries to achieve.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Background </title>
    <section>
      <title>HL7 Version 3 Clinical Statement </title>
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190530T120903-0400" comment=" Needs better transition from the previous section."?>
      <para><?oxy_comment_end?>Starting with HL7 Version 3, the minimum requirements for the
        interoperable clinical statement is: </para>
      <para>“Clinical Statement for the care of patients (persons, animals and other entities)
        is:</para>
      <para>An expression of a discrete item of clinical, clinically-related or public health
        information that is recorded because of its relevance to the care of a patient or other
        entities. Clinical or public health information can be expressed with different levels of
        granularity and therefore the extent and detail conveyed in a single statement may vary. To
        be regarded as a Clinical Statement, a concept must be associated with a patient or other
        entity in a manner which makes clear:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Its temporal context</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Its relationship to the entity or entities</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>In the case of an observation, its mood and presence, absence or value</para>
      <para>In the case of a procedure, its mood and status</para>
      <para>This clarity may be achieved by:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Explicit representation; or</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Implicit application of defaults ONLY where explicitly modeled rules state the
            appropriate defaults." </para>
          <para><citation>HL7v3</citation> HL7 Version 3 Standard: Clinical Statement CMETs Release
            1</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The V3 Clinical Statement Model is applied across CDA implementation guides including
        the US-Realm Consolidated CDA (C-CDA) to represent CDA document entries. As seen in Figure
        1, the V3 Clinical Statement Model is a polymorphic model: it can represent observations,
        procedures, encounters, public health reports, supply, medications, exposure, and
        derivations of clinical acts. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>HL7 Service-Aware Interoperability Framework Canonical Definition (SAIF-CD)
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190530T120829-0400" comment="Can we make this section more concise and more pertinent to ANF specifically? Can we reduce the number of aronyms we use?"?></title><?oxy_comment_end?>
      <para>To augment the HL7 Version 2 and Version 3 representations, HL7 introduced an
        architecture to allow for a clear separation of concerns among interoperability models and
        specification from the abstract or conceptual to the most precise, implementable, and
        testable that ensures semantic interoperability.</para>
      <para>SAIF-CD specification <citation>SAIF-CD</citation> defines three SAIF Perspectives:
        Conceptual, Logical, and Implementable. These perspective are not formally equivalent with
        Object Management Group’s (OMG) levels-of-abstraction in Model-Driven Architecture (MDA)
        even though it reuses the same derivation. Therefore, the Implementable Perspective is
        derived from the Logical Perspective and the Logical Perspective is derived from the
        Conceptual Perspective. This approach ensures that any implementable artifacts (i.e. service
        specifications, implementation guides) are traceable to business/clinical requirements and
        logical models of knowledge.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Model Derivation according to SAIF</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Perspectives.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="100%"
              contentdepth="65%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <!-- <figure>
        <title>Model Derivation according to
          SAIF-<?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190522T180111-0400" comment="Need to fix SVG"?>CD<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Perspectives.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
              contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure> -->
      <para>However, the SAIF Conceptual Perspective is not completely equivalent to the MDA concept
        of Computationally Independent Model (CIM), the Logical Perspective is not equivalent to the
        MDA Platform Independent Model (PIM), nor is the Implementable Perspective equivalent to the
        MDA Platform Specific Model although this Perspective is the SAIF Perspective that most
        closely aligns with an MDA analogue.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Conceptual Perspective</title>
        <para>The artifacts of the Conceptual Perspective are of interest to and readable by Domain
          Experts (DEs) or Subject Matter Experts (SMEs). In the context of typically clinicians and
          business analysts. These artifacts are most commonly focused on the “Problem-Space” rather
          than the “Solution Space,” and contain explicit, unambiguous descriptions of the various
          dimensions of the component (e.g. clinical statement) or system being specified. </para>
        <para>Artifacts of the Conceptual Perspective are normally developed by “outward-facing
          analysts” who have reasonable domain knowledge and can facilitate dialogues with DEs and
          SMEs. These analysts also take the results of such dialogues and represent the content in
          structured artifacts which remain understandable to DEs or SMEs. These sometimes formally
          structured artifacts may include clearly-stated business rules, concept maps, and simple
          UML class or activity diagrams. </para>
        <para>A fully-specified Conceptual Perspective thus should be both readable and traceable by
          DEs and SMEs and rigorous enough to serve as input into the development in the Logical
          Perspective.</para>
        <para>In HL7, the Conceptual Perspective is represented by Domain Analysis Models (DAMs) and
          business models that represent stakeholder requirements analyzed by SMEs and DEs. This
          perspective that precede the development of either logical or implantable artifacts and
          it’s a key to successful testing of implementations. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Logical Perspective</title>
        <para>Artifacts in the Logical Perspective represent traceable translations of
          Conceptual-level artifacts into a form and format, usable by and useful to architects and
          “inward-facing analysts.” Also included are additional specification materials required by
          architects preparing artifacts for consumption by developers. </para>
        <para>Note that there is no firm or fixed line that definitively and unambiguously
          determines where the Conceptual Perspective ends and the Logical Perspective begins. The
          same is true of the lack of definitive boundaries between the Logical and Implementable
          Perspectives. Therefore, it’s important for organizations such as HL7 to standardize
          logical models used to generate/create implementable artifacts (i.e. implementation
          guides, profiles, and templates).</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Implementable Perspective</title>
        <para>Artifacts in the Implementable Perspective are typically defined by developers or
          standards implementers, often through discussion with software designers, architects, or
          system integrators. Note that the artifacts in the Implementable Perspective are not
          actual implementations, but rather implementable in a number of implementation instances.
          Thus, all the necessary technical bindings, including data types, value sets, class
          libraries, and interface specifications are part of the Implementable Perspective. FHIR
          implementation artifact include
          <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190522T173538-0400" comment="Check with Ioana to finish sentence. "?>xxx<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Scope</title>
    <para>Here, we define ANF, an isosemantic representation of detailed clinical models that is
      designed to aid in the analysis of clinical information. Different isosemantic models can
      support different purposes, such as clinical data input, clinical data storage, clinical data
      querying, clinical data analysis, and modeler preference. ANF intends to assist with logical
      modeling or within the "Logical Perspective" in the SAIF-CD Framework.
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190530T120752-0400" comment="RC: I am braindumping some ideas here. We may want to discuss this."?></para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../../introduction/src/docbkx/clip_image002_-1458651199.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>I think a figure inspired by this Goosen image showing where/how ANF fits in and
            highlights the SAIF-CD Perspectives (Concept/Logical/Implementation) could help with the
            transition back to DCM and ANF. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In some ways, the "columns" in the Goosen figure above are analagous to the SAIF-CD
            Perspectives: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Conceptual = DCM Repository + Entry and Presentation</para>
              <para>Logical = Terminology/coding + Store/Process</para>
              <para>Implementation =Medical Knowledge + Communication</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Highlight here at a high-level why ANF is better than alternative DCMs. What is the
            higher bar that we are trying to achieve. <?oxy_comment_end?></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>In order to define comparison functions for postcoordinated expressions, normalization of
      both the contents and the semantics of the contents of the terminology needs to be
      accomplished by an appropriate knowledge representation format (ANF) that facilitates the
      process. In addition the representation format that permits such a functional comparison
      requires a storage and messaging paradigm robust enough to represent completely the explicit
      or implicit information contained within compound compositional clinical statements. ANF
      presents a formalism for storing and representing postcooridnated compositional clinical
      statements. </para>
    <para>The following document will discuss the following specific aims:
      <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190530T121125-0400" comment="Specific Aims need editing/improvement"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
    <para>(1) how the ANF Model provides the clinical data normalization capabilities to support
      accurate data retrieval and analysis; </para>
    <para>(2) how ANF is used to create detailed clinical models (DCMs); and, </para>
    <para>(3) how it differs from CIMI's current standard modeling paradigm. </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
