<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>The Clinical Information Modeling Initiative (CIMI) is an HL7 group that is defining a
            library of de- tailed clinical information models using a common modeling formalism.
            CIMI was established to improve the interoperability of healthcare information systems
            through shared implementable clinical information models that can be used to generate
            platform-specific model specifications such as FHIR profiles or CDA templates. These
            models are grouped into semantically equivalent (or ‘isosemantic’) families of clinical
            models, which capture the same clinical meaning using different combinations of concept
            pre-coordination and corresponding information model structure.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Isosemantic Models</emphasis></para>
        <para>Ideally,clinical information is modeled in a manner that is most efficient for use.
            This is a problem because there are many different use cases for clinical information
            with a wide range of requirements. There is no single model that can be the most
            efficient model for all the various use cases. Maximum efficiency for each use case
            necessitates that any particular clinical information be available in multiple modeled
            forms. These models, although different in form, semantically represent the same
            information, and are known as isosemantic models. Any particular detailed clinical model
            exists within a family of isosemantic siblings. </para>
        <para>Different isosemantic models can support different purposes, such as clinical data
            input, clinical data storage, clinical data querying, clinical data analysis, and
            modeler preference. </para>
        <para>Here, we introduce a new isosemantic representation that is designed to aid in the
            analysis of clinical information and will represent one member in each isosemantic
            family of detailed clinical models. This representation is called Analysis Normal Form
            (ANF).</para>
        <para>A FHIR implementation guide can eventually be developed.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>The purpose of this document is to inform the CIMI community about ANF and why it is
            needed as an additional standard isosemantic representation of models within
            CIMI.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">From Ioana:</emphasis></para>
        <para>I believe the ANF specification can start answer the question: how do we describe a
            “clinical statement” in a paradigm-neutral way to support clinical decision support and
            patient safety?</para>
        <para>There are tens of examples of <emphasis role="bold">Clinical Statements</emphasis> in
            the Consolidated CDA specification that was adopted by all the MU-certified EHR vendors.
            If we could demonstrate how ANF could be used to encode those clinical statements in an
            implementation-neutral way and perhaps even how that ANF expression can be used migrate
            to FHIR, we could provide a potent business case for ANF and Solor. </para>
        <para>I see an opportunity to say that the ANF specification provides harmonization across
            HL7 paradigms and perhaps foreshadow how this ANF specification can help. A work group
            to address these inconsistencies was established and then merged into Orders and
            Observation (O&amp;O) Work Group. If we want to present this ballot to the HL7
            membership at-large.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Scope</title>
        <para>This document will present the specification of the Analysis Normal Form (ANF), how it
            is used to create detailed clinical models (DCMs), and how it differs from CIMI's
            current standard modeling paradigm.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Audience</title>
        <para>The intended audience for this document are all HL7 members.</para>
    </section>
    
    
    
</chapter>
