<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>This document describes how information systems can improve patient safety and outcomes by
    increasing the precision of clinical information using a normal form to enhance and support
    accurate data retrieval and analysis.</para>
  <section>
    <title> Background </title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Analysis Normal Form</emphasis> (ANF) is a logical model intended to
      represent a <emphasis role="bold">normalized</emphasis> view of aggregate clinical statements
      for analysis, research, clinical decision support, and other purposes. ANF can be used to
      represent any isosemantic clinical statements irrespective of how the information was captured
      at its source (i.e. information systems or medical devices). ANF could be used in conjunction
      with other models intended to ensure that clinical information is structured and complete at
      the time of entry (e.g. CIMI models, ISO Detailed Clinical Models) or exchanged among systems
      (e.g. HL7 CDA templates, HL7 V2 message profiles, FHIR profiles). </para>
    <para>Clinicians, integrators, and researchers face different priorities, forcing trade-offs to
      be made that optimize data entry brevity at the cost of computability. ANF represents a
      collection of patterns and approaches to provide predictable transformations between sets of
      models and can be optimized for clinical input and models - thereby improving computability
      through normalization. The more normalized the data is, the simpler it will become to analyze,
      and errors will be reduced. Post-coordinated compositional statements using ANF introduce the
      ability to faithfully expand from a reduced form or compare to other statements with ease and
      no loss of semantic integrity. Elkin wrote about what is needed in order for post coordinated
      statements to be comparable and captured one of ANF's key objectives: "to be <emphasis
        role="bold">a formal terminological composition and decomposition mechanism</emphasis> for
      lossless information representation such that both explicit and implicit information can be
      faithfully recovered, maintained, and modified with ease." (Elkin, pg 14) </para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">main purpose</emphasis> of ANF is providing a normalized
      representation of clinical statements from a heterogeneous source using an objective
      quantitative <emphasis role="bold">measure</emphasis> to help evaluate the result, presence,
      and magnitude of a specific finding, request or observation.</para>
    <para>ANF requires an ability to classify topic expressions (and expressions that may go in
      other locations) and thus it depends on systems that can produce structured information
      reducible to ANF. These systems may create normal data natively or transform other
      representations of clinical statements (e.g. C-CDA templates, FHIR profiles) to normal form -
      ANF.</para>
    <para>Overall, ANF allows healthcare enterprises to normalize information aggregated across
      multiple sources to better support a set of analysis.</para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify clinical content extracted from EHR systems using FHIR</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Providing a common analysis form of data exchangeHL7 messages, FHIR and CDA</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specifying clinical content for User Interfaces</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Enhancing information clinical content for use as </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Clinical Decision Support Systems</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Quality Measures and National Registries</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Healthcare Guidelines and Protocols </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Epidemiological Research</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Clinical Statement Representations </title>
      <para>Clinical statement standardization has been a long-standing concern for HL7 and reuse of
        these content models across paradigms (e.g. messages, documents, services). Standardization
        has relied on model-driven approaches requiring a separation of concerns along with
        conceptual, logical, and implementation perspectives.</para>
      <section>
        <title>HL7 Version 3 Clinical Statement </title>
        <para>Starting with HL7 Version 3, the minimum requirements for the interoperable clinical
          statement: </para>
        <para>“Clinical Statement for the care of patients (persons, animals and other entities)
          is:</para>
        <para>An expression of a discrete item of clinical, clinically-related or public health
          information that is recorded because of its relevance to the care of a patient or other
          entities. Clinical or public health information can be expressed with different levels of
          granularity and therefore the extent and detail conveyed in a single statement may vary.
          To be regarded as a Clinical Statement, a concept must be associated with a patient or
          other entity in a manner which makes clear:</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Its temporal context</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Its relationship to the entity or entities</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>In the case of an observation, its mood and presence, absence or value</para>
        <para>In the case of a procedure, its mood and status</para>
        <para>This clarity may be achieved by:</para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Explicit representation; or</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Implicit application of defaults ONLY where explicitly modeled rules state the
              appropriate defaults." </para>
            <para><citation>HL7v3</citation> HL7 Version 3 Standard: Clinical Statement CMETs
              Release 1</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The V3 Clinical Statement Model is applied across CDA implementation guides including
          the US-Realm Consolidated CDA (C-CDA) to represent CDA document entries. As seen in Figure
          1, the V3 Clinical Statement Model is a polymorphic model: it can represent observations,
          procedures, encounters, public health reports, supply, medications, exposure, and
          derivations of clinical acts. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>HL7 Service-Aware Interoperability Framework Canonical Definition (SAIF-CD) </title>
        <para>To augment the HL7 Version 2 and Version 3 representations, HL7 introduced an
          architecture to allow for a clear separation of concerns among interoperability models and
          specification from the abstract or conceptual to the most precise, implementable, and
          testable that ensures semantic interoperability.</para>
        <para>SAIF-CD specification <citation>SAIF-CD</citation> defines three SAIF Perspectives:
          Conceptual, Logical, and Implementable. These perspective are not formally equivalent with
          Object Management Group’s (OMG) levels-of-abstraction in Model-Driven Architecture (MDA)
          even though it reuses the same derivation. Therefore, the Implementable Perspective is
          derived from the Logical Perspective and the Logical Perspective is derived from the
          Conceptual Perspective. This approach ensures that any implementable artifacts (i.e.
          service specifications, implementation guides) are traceable to business/clinical
          requirements and logical models of knowledge.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Model Derivation according to SAIF</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Perspectives.svg" format="SVG" scalefit="1" width="60%"
                contentdepth="65%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <!-- <figure>
        <title>Model Derivation according to SAIF-CD</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Perspectives.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" format="SVG"
              contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure> -->
        <para>However, the SAIF Conceptual Perspective is not completely equivalent to the MDA
          concept of Computationally Independent Model (CIM), the Logical Perspective is not
          equivalent to the MDA Platform Independent Model (PIM), nor is the Implementable
          Perspective equivalent to the MDA Platform Specific Model although this Perspective is the
          SAIF Perspective that most closely aligns with an MDA analogue.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Conceptual Perspective</title>
          <para> These artifacts are most commonly focused on the “Problem-Space” rather than the
            “Solution Space,” and contain explicit, unambiguous descriptions of the various
            dimensions of the component (e.g. clinical statement) or system being specified. </para>
          <para>A fully-specified Conceptual Perspective thus should be both readable and traceable
            by Domain Experts and Subject Matter Experts and rigorous enough to serve as input into
            the development in the Logical Perspective.</para>
          <para>In HL7, the Conceptual Perspective is represented by Domain Analysis Models (DAMs)
            and business models that represent stakeholder requirements analyzed by SMEs and DEs.
            This perspective that precede the development of either logical or implantable artifacts
            and it’s a key to successful testing of implementations. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Logical Perspective</title>
          <para>Artifacts in the Logical Perspective represent traceable translations of
            Conceptual-level artifacts into a form and format, usable by and useful to architects
            and “inward-facing analysts.” Also included are additional specification materials
            required by architects preparing artifacts for consumption by developers. </para>
          <para>There are no definite boundaries between the Logical and Implementable Perspectives.
            Therefore, it’s important for organizations such as HL7 to standardize logical models
            used to generate/create implementable artifacts (i.e. implementation guides, profiles,
            and templates). CIMI Clinical Statements, ISO Detailed Clinical Models, and ANF statements
            all belong in this perspective.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Implementable Perspective</title>
          <para>Artifacts in the Implementable Perspective are typically defined by developers or
            standards implementers, often through discussion with software designers, architects, or
            system integrators. Note that the artifacts in the Implementable Perspective are not
            actual implementations, but rather implementable in a number of implementation
            instances. Thus, all the necessary technical bindings, including data types, value sets,
            class libraries, and interface specifications are part of the Implementable Perspective.
            FHIR implementation requires a combination of profiles and test cases to ensure that
            implementations meet the requirements used to derive the conceptual and logical
            models.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CIMI Models</title>
        <para>The Clinical Information Modeling Initiative (CIMI) is defining a library of logical
          clinical information models using a common modeling formalism. CIMI intends to improve the
          interoperability of healthcare information systems through shared detailed clinical
          information models that can be used to generate platform-specific model specifications
          such as FHIR profiles, CDA templates, OpenEHR Archetypes, 13606 Archetypes, ISO DCMs, or
          Intermountain CEMs. CIMI models are grouped into semantically equivalent (or
          ‘isosemantic’) families of detailed clinical models, which capture the same clinical
          meaning using different combinations of pre and post-coordinated concepts and
          corresponding information model structure. The central focus of the CIMI Reference Model
          is the CIMI Clinical Statement. A CIMI Clinical Statement represents structured electronic
          communication made about a patient typically documented as an 'entry' in the patient
          record. For example, CIMI Clinical Statement can be used to represent the following statements made about a patient. This can be the statement of a condition being present, a request for a procedure to be done, the results of lab tests or the patient’s family history of cancer. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Problem</title>
    <para>Healthcare organizations are striving to become high reliability organizations (HROs),
      characterized by high levels of safety under inherently risky, technologically-complex, and
      demanding conditions.<citation>HRO_HIT</citation> Chassin and Loeb published a conceptual
      framework for assessing progress towards becoming a HRO and included the safe use of health IT
      and review of quality measures, which are dependent on data from Electronic Health Record
      (EHR) systems.<citation>Chassin</citation> Deployment of EHR systems is nearly ubiquitous in
      the US and there is increasing opportunity to leverage a substantial number of extant EHR
      mapped data sets to improve population health through quality measures, case reporting, and
      decision support. </para>
    <para>Information systems record and manage clinical statements using a variety of standard or
      ad-hoc models. However, both treatment and analysis of clinical statements require consistency
      not only at the format level (e.g. CDA, FHIR, V2) but also the content model (i.e. an instance
      of an ISO DCM, CIMI model, etc.). In most cases the data quality is the greatest obstacle to
      analysis, but even in the case of structured, semantically-clear information, inconsistency
      across sources of information raises obstacles to analysis and research. Analysis of aggregate
      information managed by health information networks poses the greatest challenge today because
      a meaningful use of data for patient outcomes or research requires a common format and level
      of semantic clarity.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Why ANF? </title>
    <para>Not only is there a potential for a lack of consistency with representing clinical
      statements with current detailed clinical modeling efforts, but there is also further
      variation in how the data is entered into information systems by end-users. This reality has a
      direct impact on patient safety if a clinical statement is recorded and displayed differently
      across the continuum of care: Clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into their
      organization’s EHR systems as "Structured Clinical Input". This concept describes any data
      entry mechanism used by clinicians to record clinical statements. An instance of a clinical
      statement may be created using one or more forms. Vendors compete on usability for seamless
      Structured Clinical Input but, in some cases, structured clinical statements are based on
      standard-based models (e.g. CIMI, openEHR archetypes, etc.) but they may also be based on
      proprietary models. For the purposes of this document, the type or usability of data
      structures used for capture or display of clinical statements is not in scope. We assume that
        <emphasis role="bold">any suitably encoded</emphasis> structured clinical statement may be
      suitable for normalization for analysis. </para>
    <para>Therefore, clinical statements can be expressed and documented in many different ways in
      EHR systems, where input forms provide different options to document the same clinical
      statement. These differences pose challenges for how the data is modeled, how the data is
      stored, and therefore has implications on data retrieval, data analysis, accuracy of clinical
      analysis results. </para>
    <para>Clinicians enter clinical statements into their organization’s EHR typically in a manner
      that we call here structured clinical input, or the manner in which information is presented
      to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by constraining the information to
      allow only certain values to be entered, e.g. through a drop-down list, radio buttons, or
      breaking up large chunks of related information into smaller parts.</para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190621T232719-0400" comment="Edited to address Stephanie&apos;s question on the intent of the numbers in the wireframe, further explained the variations across systems."?>For
      example, <link linkend="CIF_EHR_1">data collected by an EHR</link> combines information
      reported by devices with findings and interpretation: <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A vital signs monitor transmits the systolic and diastolic blood pressure including
            date/time and the id of the device, </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The nurse marks the measurement as "verified". </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Next, the nurse documents how the measurement what performed: </para>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para>using an adult cuff size</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>in prone position</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>brachial artery</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>on the left size</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>the micturition context is left empty/unknown/</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Next, the physician adds an interpretation. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="CIF_EHR_1">
      <title> Blood Pressure Statement recorded by an EHR systems</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/BP data capture.svg" scalefit="1" width="60%" format="SVG"
            contentdepth="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para><link linkend="Display_EHR_2">Another EHR system</link> may capture or display a subset of
      information about the blood pressure measurement - omitting "micturition context" and
      pre-coordinates site and laterality as:</para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Right brachial artery</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Left brachial artery</para>
        <para/>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para> Another distinct user interfaces for capturing a set of “clinical statements" related to
      Blood Pressure. </para>
    <figure xml:id="Display_EHR_2">
      <title> Alternative Blood Pressure representation in a second EHR system</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/EHR-2.svg" scalefit="1" width="60%" format="SVG"
            contentdepth="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure><?oxy_comment_end?>
    <para>In the first case, the structured clinical input has separate drop-down constraints to
      enter the artery and laterality as distinct concepts. In the second wire frame, the structured
      clinical input has combined the artery and laterality into a compound concept. This variation
      present in the structured clinical input may also have implications on the how the clinical
      statement is modeled. </para>
    <para>Ideally, clinical information is modeled in a manner that is most efficient for use. This
      is a problem because there are many different use cases for clinical information with a wide
      range of requirements. There is no single model that can be the most efficient model for all
      the various use cases. Maximum efficiency for each use case necessitates that any particular
      clinical information be available in multiple modeled forms. These models, although different
      in form, semantically represent the same information, and are known as isosemantic models. Any
      particular detailed clinical model exists within a family of isosemantic siblings. </para>
    <section>
      <title> Assumptions</title>
      <para>ANF provides a precise, consistent semantic data and terminology specification that is
        comparable and sharable between multiple care providers, health enterprises, and
        standards-based Healthcare Information Technology (HIT). </para>
      <para>ANF relies on highly post-coordinated compositional terminologies to provide greater
        content coverage in a complete and more consistent way than terminology content that is
        restricted to relying on pre-coordinated concepts. While post-coordinated compositional
        terminologies can be expressively powerful, they may generate expressions whose equivalency
        cannot be easily determined. ANF can help manage aggregate post-coordinated content in a
        normalized manner with respect to the content and semantics with the same representational
        structure as post-coordinated expressions used as input. </para>
      <para>Successful analysis requires relatively high data quality that allows systems to define
        a precise topic, category, and clear measure or result of what was observed, requested, or
        assessed during treatment. ANF can be applied to any input data and any formalism as long as
        the data semantics and terminology are sufficiently precise to define the elements mandatory
        for analysis. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Approach: Separation of Concerns</title>
      <para> Increased reliance on computerized health records, including Electronic Health Records
        Systems, require standardized medical terminology to encode health information consistently
        across systems and enterprises. Clinicians require not only objective quantitative
        measurements (e.g. 90 beats per minute for a patient's pulse) but also contextual or
        procedural context (e.g. pulse oximetry, manual) about past observations or requests for
        future interventions. While two quantitative measurements may be the same, the procedural
        information could indicate meaningful semantic differences and lead to different clinical
        interpretation and treatment. As information is exchanged across systems, the solution
        requires a common understanding of data and a method to support knowledge representation and
        clinical decision rules based on a common terminology and statements. Each component must
        address an aspect and, together they need to address the requirements of clinicians.</para>
      <para>Breaking up the solution across components or sections with a specific purpose is a
        foundational design principle for software development: Separation of Concerns. It allows a
        complete system to be subdivided into distinct sections or components with well-defined
        functionality and dependencies. If successful, this approach allows individual sections to
        be able to be reused, as well as worked on and updated independently to address new
        requirements and use cases. This is especially useful and important in a medical context
        given how many different health information and clinical terminology projects are ongoing at
        any given time. Efforts that are often uncoordinated and led by disparate and unrelated
        standards development organizations. </para>
      <para>The following diagram shows how the concept of Separation of Concerns can be applied to
        the problem systematically:</para>
      <para/>
      <figure>
        <title>Separation of Concerns: Knowledge Architecture</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/SoC.png" scale="50"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Architectural Foundation</emphasis> – Provides an interoperable,
        integrated common terminology model which concerns (a) the foundation and building blocks of
        the common model; (b) how the repeatable transformation process of disparate standards into
        the common model promotes interoperability with other environments; and (c) how the modules
        of the architecture are tightly version controlled over time. </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Terminology Knowledge</emphasis> – Structured sets of medical terms
        and codes that define concepts of interest, including descriptions, dialects, language, and
        semantic hierarchy. This layer also incorporates logical operators and description logic
        such as ‘representation of absence’. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Statement Model</emphasis> – Packaging of the terminology content
        in standardized data structures so that they can be readily consumed by the information
        retrieval process for analysis. Within the data structures, additional detail to describe
        subject, numerical, and categorical information related to concepts can be added in this
        layer. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Assertional Knowledge</emphasis> – Translation of guidelines to
        assist clinical decision making. This includes facts and knowledge upon which concepts and
        combinations of concepts can assimilate into protocols.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Procedural Knowledge</emphasis>e – Information about standard ways
        to carry out specific procedures as well as other procedural guidelines, e.g. treatment
        protocols for diseases and order sets focused on particular patient situations. Procedural
        knowledge, together with assertional knowledge, enables clinical decision support, quality
        measurement, and supports patient safety. This layer integrates the architectural and
        terminology layers, incorporates the statement model for information retrieval, and uses the
        assertional layer to apply rules.</para>
      <para>Examining a clinical procedure for controlling hypertension illustrates each of the
        layers of the informatics architectural separation of concerns. At the Terminology layer,
        there may be various codes and terms from disparate source terminologies to define the
        hypertension concept. For example, the concept “essential hypertension” is defined by the
        ICD-10 CM code I10 and 59621000 in SNOMED CT. Ideally, these overlapping codes and terms
        would be oriented to the same parent concept during the transformation and integration
        process at the Foundational layer (e.g., Solor). Furthermore, any updates over time to code
        sets or value sets that define hypertension (in the NLM’s Value Set Authority Center for
        instance) would be maintained by continuous integration at the Architectural Foundation
        layer. Moving to the statement layer, blood pressure measurement values may be packaged as a
        numerical measurement (e.g., systolic BP = 140 mmHg) or the categorical data (e.g.,
        pregnancy induced hypertension vs. renal hypertension) within a standard data structure to
        facilitate information exchange or retrieval, such as within a FHIR Observation Resource. At
        the Assertional layer, guidelines such as the recommendation to control hypertension to
        under 140/90 mmHg might be translated into a clinical workflow facilitated by Health
        Information Technology (HIT). If HIT is involved with programmed Clinical Decision Support,
        there may be additional rules to suggest hypertension medications (e.g., beta-blockers, ACE
        inhibitors) while also including rules to avoid medication contraindications. Finally, at
        the Procedural-level, there may be a treatment protocol for different kinds of hypertension,
        including the considerations of, e.g. patient age, co-morbidities etc., which can be
        generated by an electronic clinical decision support system (Statement + Assertional
        layers).</para>
      <para>ANF is intended to achieve a clean separation of concerns, especially in regard to an
        isosemantic representation in the Statement Model layer. ANF can help the modeling of
        clinical statements achieve the following design features: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Understandable: The meaning of a clinical statement can be understood, without
            reference to private or inaccessible information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reproducible: Multiple users can apply the clinical statement model to the same
            situations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Useful: The clinical statement has a practical value to users that is self-evident
            or can be readily explained.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Intended Audience</title>
      <para> ANF is intended to support projects that aggregate clinical statements from a variety
        of sources, independent of formalism or approach used by the source system. The users of
        this specification and subsequent implementation guidance are developing solutions that
        support clinical decision support, patient safety, and research. </para>
      <para>The Learning EHR, 21st Century Cures, Patient-Centered Outcomes Research, and other
        national initiatives are all relying on interoperable, reusable, analysis-ready information
        that can improve outcomes, produce new therapies, and put into practice "precision
        medicine".</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
