<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Implications—Improving Patient Safety and Outcomes</title>
  <para><glossterm baseform="Analysis Normal Form">ANF</glossterm> has implications on
    <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190717T183011-0500" comment="Comment from Stephanie K:
There isn&apos;t a sub-section for patient safety. There is one for population health. Should it be renamed to include both?" flag="done"?>clinical
    data quality, <glossterm baseform="Clinical Decision Support">clinical decision support</glossterm>, patient safety and population health because it
    promotes the reuse of information aggregated to derive new information about treatment quality,
    patient safety, and outcomes. </para><?oxy_comment_end?>
  <section>
    <title>Improved Data Quality </title>
    <para>Information systems record and manage clinical statements using a variety of standard or
      ad-hoc models and formats. However, analysis of clinical statements requires consistency, not
      only at the
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190722T175052-0700" comment="Should we add semantic consistency here as seperate from format consistency, content consistency, adn semantic consistency? 

Or maybe reference back to the interoperability levels, of which semantic was the highest? " flag="done"?>format
      level (e.g. <glossterm baseform="HL7 Clinical Document Architecture">CDA</glossterm>, FHIR,
        <glossterm baseform="HL7 V2 Messaging Profile">V2</glossterm>), but also at the content and
      semantic levels (i.e. ANF, <glossterm baseform="Clinical Information Model">CIMI
        model</glossterm>, etc.)<?oxy_comment_end?>. In most cases, the data quality is the greatest
      obstacle to analysis. Analysis Normal Form aims to minimize data quality challenges and
      provide a common format with semantic clarity to allow for meaningful secondary uses of
      clinical data. </para>
    <para>The design of
      <?oxy_comment_start author="kec" timestamp="20190722T175226-0700" comment="As I read this, it is more restating Khan, that saying how ANF supports data quality in ways that Khan says are important. Need to redraft to be more of how ANF supports data quality, for each way we support data quality, pile on that Kahn thinks it important, and other references that we can point to as well..." flag="done"?>ANF
      is based on research into data quality frameworks <link linkend="bib16">[20]</link> which
      identified that information conformance, completeness, and plausibility are all necessary to
      analysis. </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><?oxy_comment_end?><emphasis role="bold">Conformance</emphasis>: Conformance
            describes how well a system or implementation meets a specification. ANF provides a
            logical structure and constraints of clinical data for value conformance, relational
            conformance, and computational conformance irrespective of data representation (e.g.
            CDA, FHIR).</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Value Conformance: Value conformance seeks to determine if recorded data
                elements are in agreement with a predefined, constraint-driven data architecture.
                Internal data constraints are typically imposed by the <glossterm
                  baseform="ANF Reference Model">ANF Reference Model</glossterm>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Relational Conformance: Relational conformance seeks to determine if the
                recorded data elements are in agreement with additional information referenced by a
                  <glossterm baseform="Clinical Statement">clinical statement</glossterm>. An
                  <glossterm baseform="ANF Statement">ANF Statement</glossterm> may reference other
                information about patients, practitioners, encounters, etc. to provide context to
                the topic and result recorded.</para>
            </listitem>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190622T100303-0400" comment="ANF is abstracted above a relational database, in fact no relational database is required. Any kind of datastore will work." flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
            <listitem>
              <para>Computational Conformance: Computational conformance seeks to determine if
                computations used to create derived values from existing variables yield the
                intended results either within a data set (Verification) or between data sets
                (Validation), when programs are based on identical specifications. Computational
                conformance focuses on the correctness of the output value of calculations against
                technical functional specifications. ANF highlights the measure in which an action,
                finding, or observation was either requested or performed to a common "measure" thus
                supporting the development of computational, assertional, and procedural
                predicates.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Completeness</emphasis>: Completeness focuses on features that
            describe the frequencies of data attributes present in a data set without reference to
            data values. Completeness measures assess the absence of data at a single moment over
            time or when measured at multiple moments over time. ANF disambiguates the date a
            statement was made/asserted from the timing of the circumstances in which the underlying
            action, observation, or finding occurred. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold"
            >Plausibility:</emphasis><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190726T135001-0400" comment="We address deduplication via normalization - transform to ANF will..." flag="done"?>
            Plausibility focuses on features that describe the believability or truthfulness of data
            values. For this category, plausibility is determined by a variable’s value, when a
            value is placed within the context of another variable (i.e., two independent variables
            assessing the same construct), or a temporal sequence or state transition (e.g., patient
            follow-up treatment for a disease must be preceded by a corresponding
            diagnosis).<?oxy_comment_end?>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Uniqueness Plausibility<emphasis role="bold">:</emphasis> The Uniqueness
                subcategory seeks to determine if objects (entities, observations, facts) appear
                multiple times in settings where they should not be duplicated or cannot be
                distinguished within a database (Verification) or when compared with an external
                reference (Validation). Duplication frequently occurs when disparate data streams
                that contain overlapping objects are combined. ANF provides the contextual data
                needed to de-duplicate clinical statement prior to analysis.</para>
            </listitem>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="jcoyle" timestamp="20190622T100303-0400" comment="Can we change database to data repository or something more generic" flag="done"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
            <listitem>
              <para>Atemporal Plausibility: Atemporal Plausibility seeks to determine if observed
                data values, distributions, or densities agree with local or “common” knowledge
                (Verification) or from comparisons with external sources that are deemed to be
                trusted or relative gold standards (Validation). For example, in the case of
                systolic blood pressure, an independent verification of the value measured by a
                device is provided by the practitioner who conducts performance. ANF clinical
                statements support results that are evaluated based on a "reference range" of
                plausible values based on patient status, device-supported ranges, or human
                physiology.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Temporal Plausibility: Temporal plausibility seeks to determine if time-varying
                variables change values as expected based on known temporal properties or across one
                or more external comparators or gold standards. Temporal properties that establish
                expectations in this subcategory include temporal stability (do values vary over
                time as expected), temporal continuity (do values persist over time as expected),
                state transitions (do sequences of events occur as expected), and temporal
                dependencies between time-varying variables.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Enhanced Clinical Decision Support</title>
    <para>A 2012 Literature Review commissioned by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality
      (AHRQ) found evidence showing that CDS had a positive impact on process measures and
      increasing user knowledge relevant to a medical condition. <link linkend="bib17"
      >[21]</link></para>
    <para>Additional studies show that well-executed CDS can <link linkend="bib17">[21]</link>
      :</para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact" >
      <listitem>
        <para>reduce adverse drug-drug interaction events and medication errors; </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>decrease unnecessary laboratory testing;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>reduce cardiovascular risk in patients with type 2 diabetes; </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>improve practitioner performance; </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>increase cardiovascular disease risk assessment in routine primary care practice; </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>improve public health outcomes associated with outbreaks of food-borne illness; </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>and, produce cost savings associated with hospital-based pharmacy
          interventions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Taken together, the available evidence shows that CDS—when implemented in the right
      context, and when governed with formal management—can reduce errors, improve the quality of
      care, reduce cost, and ease the cognitive burden on health care providers.<link
        linkend="bib17">[21]</link> As a result, the impetus for achieving standardized, widespread
      adoption of CDS across health systems is clear.</para>
    <para>A report entitled “<emphasis role="italic">Optimizing Strategies for Clinical Decision
        Support: Summary of a Meeting Series</emphasis>” <link linkend="bib17">[21]</link> was
      produced out of the collaboration between the Office of the National Coordinator for Health
      Information Technology (ONC) and the National Academy of Medicine (NAM). The report states
      that there are at least four important technical challenges to sharing and therefore
      standardizing implementations of CDS content: <link linkend="bib17">[21]</link></para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">(1) insufficient standardization of patient data representation;
      </emphasis></para>
    <para>(2) insufficient standardization of CDS knowledge representation; </para>
    <para>(3) insufficient standardization of CDS integration mechanisms; </para>
    <para>(4) a need to align with broader standardization initiatives. </para>
    <para>One of the reasons that CDS interventions are difficult to implement between health care
      systems is because disparate EHR systems and health care systems utilize different underlying
      patient data models and clinical statement representation mechanisms. Even distinct
      instantiations of use of the same EHR systems differ in how they encode patient data and in
      how they represent clinical statements. The ONC and NAM report states that "[b]ecause CDS
      relies on inferencing using patient data, this heterogeneity in patient data representation
      poses an immense obstacle to sharing CDS." <link linkend="bib17">[21]</link>
    </para>
    <para>ANF aims to reduce the variability of clinical data managed by clinical information
      systems and stored in data repositories. The standardization of clinical observations in a
      manner that supports automated processing requires a formal clinical statement model, such as
      ANF. The most important requirements of such a statement model are that (1) it can represent
      any clinician-specified observation accurately and precisely and (2) it can support automated
      query and retrieval operations correctly and efficiently.</para>
    <para>ANF aims to reduce the variability of clinical data within the value sets and clinical
      decision rules managed by EHR systems and modeled/stored in data repositories. For example, a
      clinician could document that a patient has “bacterial pneumonia caused by
      methicillin-resistant Staph. Aureus” by combining the pre-existing concept “bacterial
      pneumonia” with the pre-existing concept “Methicillin Resistant Staph. Aureus” and specifying
      that the latter is the “causative agent” of the former. The patient’s medical record would
      then contain an entry consisting of the following expression: </para>
    <para>Bacterial Pneumonia (ConceptID = 53084003) : Causative Agent (ConceptID=246075003) =
      Methicillin Resistant Staph. Aureus (ConceptID=115329001)</para>
    <para>If specified correctly, post-coordinated expressions also support subsumption testing.
      Hence, the patient whose record contains the expression above would also be identified by the
      query “find all patients with a diagnosis of any infectious disease (Infectious Disease :
      ConceptID = 40733004) in their record.”</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Increasing Population Health</title>
    <para><glossterm baseform="Electronic Clinical Quality Measures">Electronic clinical quality
        measures (eCQMs)</glossterm> and CDS alerts are triggered by clinical data that is
      represented in data repositories by clinical statements represented by detailed clinical
      models with data elements encoded by standards-based clinical terminologies. Because these
      measures and alerts intend to promote evidence-based clinical processes, variations in
      clinical data caused by having inaccurate, incomplete, or antiquated implementations of
      underlying logical models may impact the ability of clinicians to assess care and improve
      quality. Health information technology-supported quality improvement (QI) initiatives can
      decrease disparities for some chronic disease management and preventive measures QI. <link
        linkend="bib18">[22]</link> Data-driven QI efforts rely heavily on patient-level data
      generated by eCQM reports or CDS alerts, which are dependent upon standards-based encoded
      clinical data. If clinicians rely on inaccurate implementations of eCQMs and CDS, then they
      may have lists/alerts with patients intended to be excluded from a measure/alert, and may
      therefore, target inappropriate patients for therapies, such as recommending aspirin use for
      someone at high-risk for a fatal bleeding event. Similarly, life-saving treatment may be
      denied or
      delayed.<?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190717T183701-0500" comment="From Stephanie K.

Would you want to state that the opposite could be true as well, where patients who should have been on the list were incorrectly excluded?" flag="done"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
    <para>Implementation research shows that variations in implementations of eCQM specifications
      for cardiovascular event prevention could result in potential lives saved or harms avoided in
      quality improvement activities. <link linkend="bib19">[23]</link> For aspirin use for
      secondary prevention of heart attacks, <glossterm baseform="Number-Needed-to-Treat"
        >Number-Needed-to-Treat (NNT)</glossterm> statistics show that of patients with known
      cardiovascular risk who took aspirin, 1.3% were helped by preventing a non-fatal heart attack,
      and 0.25% were harmed by a major bleeding event. An implementation study <link linkend="bib19"
        >[23]</link> against clinical data from two primary care clinics shows that 121 (92%) of the
      patients were inappropriately included in a measure’s denominator. These patients were also
      taking an anticoagulant medication, so the <glossterm baseform="Number-Needed-to-Harm"
        >Number-Needed-to-Harm (NNH)</glossterm> statistic for this subset of patients for aspirin
      usage is likely much higher, and for this study, 1 to 2 people may have been harmed if the
      inaccurate implementation persisted, as evidence shows that patients with combinations of
      aspirin, warfarin, and clopidogrel are associated with up to a three-fold higher risk of
      bleeding for patients on dual therapy and triple therapy. With another measure for statin
      therapy, 1 in 21 people have a repeat heart attack, stroke or death avoided, so even 10 missed
      people have significant risk of events. Similarly, 10% are harmed by muscle damage or pain, or
      ~1 of the 14 inappropriately included in the study. <link linkend="bib19">[23]</link> Even in
      the small eCQM implementation study <link linkend="bib19">[23]</link> with data from two
      primary care clinics, failure to include or exclude patients could have led to real harm. </para>
    <para>With eCQM implementation and QI infrastructure increasing, the problem of having, and
      using, inaccurate eCQM implementations or CDS implementations could have significant potential
      negative impact on population health by not avoiding adverse events and harm to patients. ANF
      reduces these erroneous implementations. Without a precise logical model for clinical data
      like ANF, comparability of eCQMs for payment programs and utility of CQM data for targeted
      quality improvement may be limited.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para>In conclusion, Analysis Normal Form (ANF) presents a simple reproducible approach to
      modeling clinical statements specifically for data analysis. It reduces clinical statements to
      two types, Performance of an action, finding, or observation and Request for Action, both
      clinical statement types with topics. ANF is compatible with other work in statement
      representation models such as the CIMI Clinical Statement approach, with its focus on more
      traditional complex structured trees, whereas ANF focuses on structuring data in a way that
      CDS systems can extract data in an unambiguous way. ANF provides a single, normalized, form
      for clinical statements that may be used to create assertional or procedural knowledge
      artifacts, such as clinical decision support rules and clinical alerts.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
