<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Pragmatic Usage and Next Steps</title>
    <para>Like other <glossterm baseform="Clinical Information Modeling Initiative">CIMI</glossterm>
        <glossterm baseform="Isosemantic Model">isosemantic models</glossterm>, <glossterm
            baseform="Analysis Normal Form">ANF</glossterm> is a <glossterm baseform="Logical Model"
            >logical model</glossterm> and therefore it may be implemented using relevant
        implementable models and technology (see <link linkend="SAIF-CD-diagram"
            ><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190729T170311-0400" comment="Add reference to intro" flag="done"?>SAIF-CD<?oxy_comment_end?></link>).
        Thus, this project will expand on the use of ANF alongside preexisting information exchange
        HL7 standards (i.e. <glossterm baseform="HL7 V2 Messaging Profile">HL7 V2
            messaging</glossterm>, <glossterm baseform="HL7 Clinical Document Architecture">CDA
            documents</glossterm>) and HL7 standards-based APIs (i.e., FHIR resources). In practice,
        ANF is applicable to systems normalizing or creating normalized data to support <link
            linkend="SoC_Section"><glossterm baseform="Assertional Knowledge"
                >Assertional</glossterm></link> and <link linkend="SoC-diagram"><glossterm
                baseform="Procedural Knowledge">Procedural</glossterm></link> knowledge (e.g.
        clinical alerts, workflow, data analysis, decision support). These need to aggregate data
        from many isosemantic source models into a single analysis format.</para>
    <para>Implementers may use the logical model and methodology in this document to design software
        components, databases, or APIs that support reuse and analysis of treatment information
        captured using best practices (e.g. <glossterm baseform="Clinical Information Model">CIMI
            models</glossterm>) and exchanged using interoperability specifications required across
        the US (e.g. FHIR US Core, Consolidated CDA). Since information sharing already relies on a
        variety of clinical statement approaches and syntax representations, it will become
        necessary to create normalized instances of those clinical statements intended for reuse.
        Not all the data produced by a system is necessary for analysis; and, the ANF model—like
        other CIMI models—is focused on
        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190726T125624-0400" comment="True?  Quality measures combine clinical and admnistrative info sometimes so it would be useful to say, if true, that other types of data may be combined." id="rvl_2mj_43b" flag="done" mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190729T103421-0400" comment="Administrative info is part of the infrastructure of Knowlege Architecture." parentID="rvl_2mj_43b" flag="done"?>clinical
        information<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?>. ANF does not require a specific
        input form syntax; its focus is on implementations where data quality and semantics and on
        implementations that require information must be aggregated from many and diverse sources. </para>

    <para>The ANF logical model can be used to create practical implementation guidance (i.e.
        implementation guide, profiles, value sets based on standard terminology) and can be applied
        to design data analysis solutions. Implementation specifications include vocabulary bindings
        based on standard terminologies (e.g. SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm) to support the Terminology
        layer of the<?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190731T020015-0400" comment="Link to intro"?>
        <link linkend="SoC_Section"><glossterm baseform="Knowledge Architecture">Knowledge
                Architecture</glossterm></link>.<?oxy_comment_end?> For simplicity, SNOMED CT is
        used for all logical expressions and examples in this specification but ANF implementation
        may require LOINC, RxNorm, or other standard terminology.</para>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>ANF FHIR implementation</title>
        </info>

        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="bechang" timestamp="20190426T225012-0600" comment="Need Ioana to expand upon what would be next after successful balloting of this whitepaper in September 2019" flag="done"?>ANF
            is a logical model intended to represent any clinical data using a complete yet simple
            normal form. It allows other software modules to reuse the information and derive new
            knowledge from it. Examples of ANF's benefits include improved ability to (1) analyze
            the care that was delivered, (2) find out what type care leads to the best patient
            outcomes, and (3) use rules and business triggers to automate clinical decision and
            workflow steps. <?oxy_comment_end?>ANF could be used to design standards-based
            Application Programming Interfaces (APIs) optimized for a specific analysis purpose. ANF
            APIs may be implemented using FHIR resources, profiles, and extensions to access
            clinical decision support, clinical quality measures, and to support workflow automation
            by triggering reminders and clinical notifications.</para>
        <para>ANF statements may be created from existing clinical statements and patient-entered
            data to support APIs intended for analysis or to automate information derived from
            device measurements, clinician inputs, and patient-generated data.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Analysis API</title>
                    <para>The typical implementation of ANF will be a system that normalizes
                clinical information (e.g. FHIR, CDA documents) to be used by business and decision
                support rules. Healthcare enterprises may use middleware, standards-based
                transformation and terminology servers to normalize a variety of observations,
                orders, diagnoses, medications, procedure notes, and other interventions to a set of
                        <glossterm baseform="ANF Performance">Performance</glossterm> or <glossterm baseform="ANF Request">Request</glossterm> statements. Narrative clinical statements may not be
                immediately reducible to ANF and it may require natural language processing and
                other methods of augmentation and enhancement.</para>

                    <para>ANF-specific resources and implementation guidance can be tested during
                        FHIR Connectathons to validate that the logical model outlined in this
                        specification is suitable to data aggregation and supports the analysis
                        objectives of researchers, before proposing them as new resources for future
                        versions of FHIR and as extensions and profiles for current versions. Both
                        approaches may be desirable.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="ANF-FHIR-API">
                    <title>ANF-based FHIR API </title>
                    
                    <mediaobject role="bordered">
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/ANF-FHIR-API.png" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para><emphasis>ANF-based information can be used to create data warehouses
                                and support data mining</emphasis>.</para></caption>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </section>

               <section>
                   <title>Automated Data Analysis</title>
                   <para>ANF statements may be created as an outcome of evaluating device,
                clinician, and patient-entered data (e.g. questionnaires) automatically and in
                near-real-time. For example, specific answers to a PHQ-9 screening tool along with
                previous assessments could trigger a specific type of follow-up screening regarding
                substance use treatment or further evaluation, consideration of<emphasis> Social
                    Determinants of Health</emphasis> (<link
                    xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/socialdeterminants/index.htm">SDOH</link>), or
                alert to a provider. While ANF statements are not intended as an input form, such
                statements could be automatically generated by Learning Health Systems <link
                    linkend="bib14">[18] </link>using a combination of pre-existing clinical data,
                clinical guidelines/rules, medical device observation and patient-generated data.
                The promise of the <emphasis>Learning Health System </emphasis><link linkend="bib14"
                    >[18]</link> is the ability to learn new knowledge from previous clinical
                statements and latest scientific developments. This approach is also conducive to
                tailoring treatment consistent with <emphasis>precision medicine</emphasis>
                <link linkend="bib15">[19]</link> and reducing provider burden through
                automation.</para>
                   <para>
                       <figure xml:id="ANF-derivation">
                           <title> Deriving ANF Statements </title>
                           
                           <mediaobject role="bordered">
                               <imageobject>
                                   <imagedata fileref="images/derivation.png" scale="40"/>
                               </imageobject>
                           </mediaobject>
                           <caption>
                               <para><emphasis>ANF statements may be derived from other data inputs
                                and combined to support near-real-time analysis.</emphasis></para></caption>
                       </figure>
                   </para>
               </section>
       
    
    </section>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>Other platforms</title>
        </info>
        <para>Big data analytics, data mining, business intelligence, healthcare quality programs,
            registries etc. all require large data sets of consistent structure and semantics that
            can be analyzed and aggregated for the benefit of individual patients, to evaluate an
            organization, or to establish new facts. </para>
        <figure xml:id="ANF-DATA-MINING">
            <title>Data Mining using ANF statements </title>
            
            <mediaobject role="bordered">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/data-mining.png" scale="40"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <caption>
                <para><emphasis>Standards-based information may be normalized to ANF to be used for
                        clinical decision support.</emphasis></para></caption>
        </figure>
        <para>Interoperability standards sometimes pose challenges due to the use of
            synthetics/abstract data types that attempt to capture the complexity of healthcare
            data. ANF simplifies the statement structure by using a small set of primitive types
            (e.g. float, varchar, boolean) and a sophisticated terminology. Data warehousing and
            mining solutions rely on a consistent simple representation of data organized along
            facts and axes. ANF borrows from database normalization the idea that
                "<emphasis>normalization</emphasis>" reduces data redundancy and improves data
            integrity. The ANF logical model can be used to design "fact-based" dimensional schemas
            for databases which enable analysis of a specific set of facts and dimensions, such as
            evaluation of outcomes associated with the use of a specific therapy, device, or
            medication.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
