<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Implications</title>
    <para>A 2012 Literature Review commissioned by The Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality
        (AHRQ) found evidence showing that CDS had positive impact on process measures and
        increasing user knowledge relevant to a medical condition. (Lobach et al., 2012)
            <citation>CDSOptimize</citation></para>
    <para>Additional studies show that well-executed CDS can
        <citation>CDSOptimize</citation>:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>reduce adverse drug-drug interaction events and medication errors (Smithburger et
                al., 2011; Sonnichsen et al., 2016) (Fritz et al., 2012); </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>decrease unnecessary lab testing (Felcher et al., 2017);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>reduce cardiovascular risk in patients with type 2 diabetes (Cleveringa et al.,
                2008); </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>improve practitioner performance (Garg et al., 2005); </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>increase cardiovascular disease risk assessment in routine primary care practice
                (Wells et al., 2008); </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>improve public health outcomes associated with outbreaks of foodborne illness (Wu
                et al., 2012); </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>and, produce cost savings associated with hospital-based pharmacy interventions
                (Calloway et al., 2013).</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Taken together, the available evidence shows that CDS —when implemented in the right
        context, and when governed with formal management—can reduce errors, improve the quality of
        care, reduce cost, and ease the cognitive burden on health care providers.
            <citation>CDSOptimize</citation> As a result, the impetus for achieving standardized,
        widespread adoption of CDS across health systems is clear.</para>
    <para>A report entitled “<emphasis role="italic">Optimizing Strategies for Clinical Decision
            Support: Summary of a Meeting Series</emphasis>” was produced out of the collaboration
        between the ONC and the National Academy of Medicine (NAM). The report states that there are
        at least four important technical challenges to sharing and therefore standardizing
        implementations of CDS content: <citation>CDSOptimize</citation></para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">(1) insufficient standardization of patient data representation;
        </emphasis></para>
    <para>(2) insufficient standardization of CDS knowledge representation; </para>
    <para>(3) insufficient standardization of CDS integration mechanisms; </para>
    <para>(4) a need to align with broader standardization initiatives. </para>
    <para>One of the reasons that CDS interventions are difficult to implement between health care
        systems is because disparate EHR systems and health care systems utilize different
        underlying patient data models and clinical statement representation mechanisms. Even
        distinct instantiations of use of the same EHR systems differ in how they encode patient
        data and in how they represent clinical statements. The ONC and NAM report states that
        "[b]ecause CDS relies on inferencing using patient data, this heterogeneity in patient data
        representation poses an immense obstacle to sharing CDS."
        <citation>CDSOptimize</citation></para>
    <para>ANF aims to reduce the variability of how clinical data within the value sets and CDS
        rules are inputted into EHR systems and modeled/stored in data repositories. The
        standardization of clinical observations in a manner that supports automated processing
        requires a formal clinical statement model, such as ANF. The most important requirements of
        such a statement model are that (1) it can represent any clinician-specified observation
        accurately and precisely and (2) it can support automated query and retrieval operations
        correctly and efficiently.</para>
    <para><?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190619T182046-0400" comment="Needs to be reviewed/updated."?>Importantly,
        ANF supports the ability to enable clinicians who use SCT to express observations that do
        not appear as pre-defined concepts in the terminology, thereby vastly increasing the
        expressive power of clinical terminologies. For example, a clinician could document that a
        patient has “bacterial pneumonia caused by methicillin-resistant Staph. Aureus” by combining
        the pre-existing concept “bacterial pneumonia” with the pre-existing concept “Methicillin
        Resistant Staph. Aureus” and specifying that the latter is the “causative agent” of the
        former. The patient’s medical record would then contain an entry consisting of the following
        expression: </para>
    <para>Bacterial Pneumonia (ConceptID = 53084003) : Causative Agent (ConceptID=246075003) =
        Methicillin Resistant Staph. Aureus (ConceptID=115329001)</para>
    <para>If specified correctly, post-coordinated expressions also support subsumption testing.
        Hence, the patient whose record contains the expression above would also be identified by
        the query “find all patients with a diagnosis of any infectious disease (Infectious Disease
        : ConceptID = 40733004) in their record.”<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    <para>If specified correctly, shareable CDS and Quality Measure implementations can have a
        positive <emphasis role="italic">Impact on population health.</emphasis></para>
</chapter>
