<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="CSS/docbook.xml.css"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Implications &amp; Discussion</title>
    <section>
        <title>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110521-0400" comment="From Ioana:
I think it would be valuable if we could show how ANF can improve the precision of “clinical statements”.
Both C-CDA and FHIR US core specify profiles intended to represent data captured by EHRs. If we could show how an EHR-produced “result” could be represented in ANF.
We could propose this improvement to Orders&amp;Observations, Patient Care, and Clinical Decision Support work groups.
" id="c2z_fxv_lhb" mid="1"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110533-0400" comment="KH: Ioana, could you elaborate on this, please?" parentID="c2z_fxv_lhb" mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T110613-0400" comment="&quot;the precision of &apos;clinical statements&apos;&quot; Keith: Probably is about reproducibility." parentID="c2z_fxv_lhb"?>Precisio<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_end mid="1"?>n
            of Clinical Statements Using ANF (*DRAFT*)</title>
        <para>The representation of clinical data across disparate healthcare organizations is
            highly variable; due to the various networks, communication channels, set of
            transformations, and different organizations of clinical data that currently exist.
            Despite the fact that there are mandated and widely implemented clinical terminology
            standards, standardized representation of clinical data is non-trivial because each
            standard has different semantics models, and use different formalisms and tools for
            their representation, have separate release cycles, and different versioning mechanisms.
            These terminologies are often used in an inconsistent way across implementations of the
            same underlying systems, and the minimal integration of systems such as SNOMED CT and
            LOINC and RxNorm is an area requiring considerable attention if we want to support safe
            and effective portability of software components and the ability to reuse code across
            healthcare organizations. </para>
        <para>One implementation of a decision support alert of quality measure query at the
            Veterans Health Administration, for instance, is not completely transferrable to another
            institution; analysts at each organization will have to modify the underlying query
            which might be in Structured Query Language (SQL) for instance so that it is computable
            against their respective clinical database structure. Furthermore, all of the
            standards-based encoded concepts are not recorded in the same way in different EHR
            implementations; what may be structured in one system and represented by LOINC may be
            represented in another system by SNOMED CT, and yet another system may represent the
            concepts using free text.</para>
        <para>The standardization of clinical observations in a manner that supports automated
            processing requires a formal terminology model. The most important requirements of such
            a terminology model are that (1) it can represent any clinician-specified observation
            accurately and precisely and (2) it can support automated query and retrieval operations
            correctly and efficiently.</para>
        <para>Importantly, ANF use of SOLOR supports the ability to express new medical concepts by
            combining pre-existing ones. This process, called post-coordination, enables clinicians
            who use SCT to express observations that do not appear as pre-defined concepts in the
            terminology, thereby vastly increasing the expressive power of clinical terminologies.
            For example, a clinician could document that a patient has “bacterial pneumonia caused
            by methicillin-resistant Staph. Aureus” by combining the pre-existing concept “bacterial
            pneumonia” with the pre-existing concept “Methicillin Resistant Staph. Aureus” and
            specifying that the latter is the “causative agent” of the former. The patient’s medical
            record would then contain an entry consisting of the following expression: </para>
        <para>Bacterial Pneumonia (ConceptID = 53084003) : Causative Agent (ConceptID=246075003) =
            Methicillin Resistant Staph. Aureus (ConceptID=115329001)</para>
        <para>If specified correctly, post-coordinated expressions also support subsumption testing.
            Hence, the patient whose record contains the expression above would also be identified
            by the query “find all patients with a diagnosis of any infectious disease (Infectious
            Disease : ConceptID = 40733004) in their
            record.”<?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190607T180609-0400" comment="RC: adding comment to test email notification"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
        <para>RC: Test</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
