<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Pragmatic Usage and Next Steps</title>
    <para>Like other CIMI isosemantic models, ANF is a logical model and therefore it may
        implemented using relevant implementable models and technology (see <link xpref="SAIF-CD-diagram">SAIF-CD</link>). Therefore this project will expand on the use
        of ANF alongside preexisting information exchange HL7 standards (i.e. HL7 V2 messaging, CDA
        documents) and HL7 standard-based APIs (I.e.. FHIR resources). In practice, ANF is
        applicable to systems normalising or creating normalized data to support Assertional and
        Procedural knowledge (e.g. clinical alerts, workflow, data analysis, decision support).
        These needs to aggregate data from many isosemantic source models into a single analysis
        format.</para>
    <para>Implementers may use the logical model  and methodology  in this document to design
        software components, databases, or APIs that support reuse and analysis of treatment
        information captured using a best practices (e.g. CIMI models) and exchanged using
        interoperability specifications. </para>
    <para>This project will expand on the use ANF to support emerging US Realm specifications that
        will drive the adoption of FHIR-based APIs in the near future. As information sharing will
        rely on a variety of clinical statement approaches and syntax representations, it will
        become necessary to create normalized instances of those clinical statements intended for
        reuse. Not all the data produced by a system is necessary for analysis and the ANF model,
        like other CIMI models, is focused on
        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190726T125624-0400" comment="True?  Quality measures combine clinical and admnistrative info sometimes so it would be useful to say, if true, that other types of data may be combined."?>clinical
        information<?oxy_comment_end?>.  ANF does not require a specific input form syntax , its
        focus are implemetnations where data quality  and semantics and information is aggregated
        from many and diverse sources. </para>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>FHIR implementation</title>
        </info>
        
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="bechang" timestamp="20190426T225012-0600" comment="Need Ioana to expand upon what would be next after successful balloting of this whitepaper in September 2019"?>We
            believe that ANF represents an approach to statement representation that next needs to be
            refined into a normative set of editorial guidelines that can eventually also be expanded upon
            into the latest standards, such as creating an HL7 FHIR Implementation
            Guide<?oxy_comment_end?> .</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>Other platforms</title>
        </info>
    </section>
</chapter>
