<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Pragmatic Usage and Next Steps</title>
    <para>Like other CIMI isosemantic models, ANF is a logical model and therefore it may
        implemented using relevant implementable models and technology (see <link
            linkend="SAIF-CD-diagram"
            ><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190729T170311-0400" comment="Add reference to intro" flag="done"?>SAIF-CD<?oxy_comment_end?></link>).
        Therefore, this project will expand on the use of ANF alongside preexisting information
        exchange HL7 standards (i.e. HL7 V2 messaging, CDA documents) and HL7 standards-based APIs
        (i.e., FHIR resources). In practice, ANF is applicable to systems normalizing or creating
        normalized data to support <link linkend="SoC_Section">Assertional</link> and <link
            linkend="SoC-diagram">Procedural</link> knowledge (e.g. clinical alerts, workflow, data
        analysis, decision support). These need to aggregate data from many isosemantic source
        models into a single analysis format.</para>
    <para>Implementers may use the logical model and methodology in this document to design software
        components, databases, or APIs that support reuse and analysis of treatment information
        captured using best practices (e.g. CIMI models) and exchanged using interoperability
        specifications required across the US (e.g. FHIR US Core, Consolidated CDA). Since
        information sharing already relies on a variety of clinical statement approaches and syntax
        representations, it will become necessary to create normalized instances of those clinical
        statements intended for reuse. Not all the data produced by a system is necessary for
        analysis; and, the ANF model - like other CIMI models - is focused on
        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190726T125624-0400" comment="True?  Quality measures combine clinical and admnistrative info sometimes so it would be useful to say, if true, that other types of data may be combined." id="rvl_2mj_43b" flag="done" mid="2"?><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190729T103421-0400" comment="Administrative info is part of the infrastructure of Knowlege Architecture." parentID="rvl_2mj_43b" flag="done"?>clinical
        information<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="2"?>. ANF does not require a specific
        input form syntax , its focus is on implementations where data quality and semantics and
        information is aggregated from many and diverse sources. Implementers will be able to
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rcholan" timestamp="20190730T130415-0400" comment="Incomplete sentence"?>pt<?oxy_comment_end?>
    </para>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>ANF FHIR implementation</title>
        </info>
        
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="bechang" timestamp="20190426T225012-0600" comment="Need Ioana to expand upon what would be next after successful balloting of this whitepaper in September 2019" flag="done"?>ANF
            is a logical model intended to represent any clinical data using a complete yet simple
            normal form. It allows other software modules to reuse the information and derive new
            knowledge from it. Examples of ANF's benefits include improved ability to (1) analyze
            the care that was delivered, (2) find out what type care leads to the best patient
            outcomes, and (3) use rules and business triggers to automate clinical decision and
            workflow steps. <?oxy_comment_end?>ANF could be used to design standards-based
            Application Programming Interfaces (APIs). Therefore, ANF could be implemented using
            FHIR resources, profiles, and extensions to create an API that can retrieve information
            intended for clinical decision support, clinical quality measures, and to support
            workflow automation by triggering reminders and clinical notifications.</para>
        <para>ANF statements may be created from existing clinical and patient-entered data:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The typical implementation of ANF will be a system that normalizes
                        clinical information (e.g. FHIR, CDA documents) to be used by business and
                        decision support rules. Healthcare enterprises may use middleware,
                        standards-based transformation and terminology servers to normalize a
                        variety of observations, orders, diagnoses, medications, procedure notes,
                        and other interventions to a set of Performance or Request statements.
                        Narrative clinical statements may not be immediately reducible to ANF and it
                        may require natural language processing and other methods of augmentation
                        and enhancements.</para>
               
                            <para>ANF-specific resources and implementation guidance can be tested
                        during FHIR Connectathons to validate that the logical model outlined in
                        this specification is suitable to data aggregation and supports the analysis
                        objectives of researchers, before proposing them as new resources for future
                        versions of FHIR and as extensions and profiles for current versions. Both
                        approaches may be desirable.</para>
                </listitem>
                   
                <listitem>
                    <para>ANF statements may be created as an outcome of evaluating device,
                        clinician, patient-entered data (e.g. questionnaires) automatically and in
                        near-real-time. For example, specific answers to a PHQ-9 screening tool
                        along with previous assessments could trigger a specific type of follow-up
                        screening regarding substance use treatment or further evaluation,
                        consideration of Social Determinants of Health, or alert to a provider.
                        While ANF statements are not intended as an input form, such statements
                        could be automatically generated by learning EHR systems
                            <citation>ehr</citation> using on a combination of pre-existing clinical
                        data, clinical guidelines/rules, medical device observation and
                        patient-generated data. The promise of the
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190729T155826-0400" comment="Add reference
to https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/22/1/43/834511" flag="done"?>Learning
                        EHR<?oxy_comment_end?> system <citation>ehr</citation> is the ability to
                        learn new knowledge from previous clinical statements and latest scientific
                        developments. This approach also conducive to tailoring treatment consistent
                        with
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190729T155918-0400" comment="Add reference to
https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/precision-medicine
optional:
https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/the-press-office/2015/01/30/fact-sheet-president-obama-s-precision-medicine-initiative" flag="done"?>Precision Medicine<?oxy_comment_end?>
                        <citation>cancer</citation>  and reducing provider burden through
                        automation.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para/>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <info>
            <title>Other platforms</title>
        </info>
        <para>Big data analytic, data mining, business intelligence, healthcare quality programs,
            registries etc. all require large data sets of consistent structure and semantics that
            can be analysed I aggregated for the benefit of individual patients, to evaluate an
            organization, or to establish new facts. </para>
        <para>Interoperability standards sometimes pose challenges due to the use of
            synthetics/abstract data types that attempt to capture the complexity of healthcare
            data. ANF simplifies the statement structure by using a small set of primitive types
            (e.g. float, varchar, boolean) and a sophisticated terminology . Data warehousing and
            mining solutions rely need a consistent simple representation of data organized along
            facts and axes. ANF borrows from Database Normalization the idea that "normalization"
            can . ANF  could be used to deisgn database schemas that enable analysis..</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
