<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Introduction to
        <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T105747-0400" comment="KC: How is “clinical statement” defined here and how are we different from what exists, e.g. in HL7 clinical statement. (get pointer from Ioana), also work with Joey on this"?>Clinical
        <?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190418T105724-0400" comment="•	Keith’s initial guidance:
o	Should be written at a higher level for general understanding of the problem
o	Non-technical explanation of issues around clinical content and data analysis
o	Explain, how same piece of clinical data can be recorded in multiple different ways (CIF).
o	Start with simple examples of “Pulse” (Pulse by method, Pulse by patient status) and Blood Pressure (Systolic BP 120 mmHg, taken on right brachial artery), then go into some more complex examples
	Cite reference study about importance of patient position, micturition etc.
" mid="1"?>Statements<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="1"?></title>
    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Purpose of this section:</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>To provide a general understanding of clinical statements and
                                    the challenges of data retrieval and analysis</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Describe at a high level (not too technical) what
                                            clinical statements are a</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Explain issues with data analysis of clinical
                                            content</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <section>
        <title>Clinical Statement Definition</title>
        <para>A <emphasis role="italic">clinical statement</emphasis> represents an entry in the
            patient record that documents in a structured/computable manner clinical information
            about a subject of information, such as a patient or a relative of the patient, and that
            is asserted by a particular source, recorded, and potentially verified. In a general
            sense, a clinical statement is any statement about a subject of record, e.g. the
            patient, made by healthcare provider, e.g. a nurse or a physician. This can be the
            statement of a condition being present, a request for a procedure to be done, the
            results of lab tests or the patient’s family history of cancer. There are a number of
            implementations which fit this description, e.g. the current normative definition
            of<?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190617T140910-0400" comment="Add referece/hyperlink to Introduction."?>
            Clinical Statements in HL7 V3 describes principles and constraints for Clinical
            <?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190617T140934-0400" comment="Footnote should be replaced by a reference." mid="3"?>Statements. <?oxy_comment_end?><footnote>
                <para>
                    <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=40"
                        >http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=40<?oxy_comment_end mid="3"?></link>
                </para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para>Clinical Statements are used to model all “entries” in a Clinical Document
            Architecture (CDA) document section. The Clinical Statement “Common Model Element Type”
            (CMET) is the base model for the all Consolidated CDA “clinical statement” templates
            that are still mandatory for Electronic Health Record (EHR) vendors. The concept of
            “clinical statement” is widely understood though there is an issue with consistency
            across HL7 paradigms: V3, CDA, and FHIR.
            <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>Placeholder HERE for
            more detail about other paradigms later in the document (maybe forward link for more
            detail here?)<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
        <para>Let's consider the following example for blood pressure measurement and the clinical
            statement that may be entered to represent this information.</para>
        <para>“Systolic blood pressure 120 mmHg, taken on right brachial artery, using adult size
            blood pressure cuff, patient in sitting position for at least 5 minutes, urinated no
            more than 30 minutes prior to measurement”. For the user, this would be the easiest way
            to document the measurement. However, the various parts of information about the body
            site, the blood pressure cuff, patient position etc. would be lost to any attempt of
            data retrieval. Rather than selecting this information all at once with a single item,
            the user could choose the various parts of information pertinent to the blood pressure
            measurement in various ways. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Clinical Input Statements</title>
        <para>Clinicians author clinical statements and enter them into their organization’s EHR
            systems. Clinical statements can be expressed and documented in many different ways in
            EHR systems, where Clinical Input Forms provide different options to document the same
            clinical statement. These differences pose challenges for data retrieval, data analysis
            and data analysts in their attempts to extract accurate clinical analysis results. </para>
        <para>Clinicians enter clinical statements into their organization’s
            EHR<?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T095907-0400" comment="Joey Coyle:
We need a better term than CIF, as Classic CIMI is not CIF. Classic CIMI is as post-coordinated as is reasonable for the purpose of making queries and analysis easier. A clinical input form is the opposite and is usually as pre-coordinated as is reasonable. During data input, these pre-coordinated instances would then need to be transformed to a post-coordinated form before being stored in a repository.

The main problem is that both ANF and highly post-coordinated models are for analysis. ANF may be more reproducibly consistent and better for analysis, but to assert that CIMI models are designed to aid in clinical input is an error.

This should be decided sooner than later.

The big difference I see is that ANF has a pure and consistent coded topic with a numerical result, whereas Classic Cimi can have a complex structured tree of codes for parts of the topic and/or the result, where positioning in the tree may imply semantic meaning.

Maybe…
Structured Coded Form
" id="hhx_wxf_nhb" mid="4"?><?oxy_comment_start author="kmaulden" timestamp="20190423T095920-0400" comment="KC: Supports general idea. In CIMI we allow expression tree both in topic and in the value, which creates problem like the dot blot hemorrhages. We should get 1 or two examples of statements and how ANF uses it, how CIMI uses it and what it looks like in CIF. Let this emerge through worked examples. We need to explain, how ANF is different from CIMI. Need example of what “classic CIMI” is. Add to BP and Pulse example one more that has a non-numeric result." parentID="hhx_wxf_nhb"?>
            typically in a manner that we call here the clinical input form (CIF). However, the CIF
            is not a literal form<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="4"?> that clinicians
            select and enter data in. Rather, it refers to the manner in which information is
            presented to the clinicians and how they enter the data, such as by constraining the
            information to allow only certain values to be entered, e.g. through a drop-down list or
            radio button, or breaking up large chunks of related information into smaller
            parts.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">The following examples illustrate
                    this paradigm of CIF and/or Structured Coded Form:</emphasis></emphasis></para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Pulse Rate 68 bpm, taken by pulse oximeter</emphasis></para>
                <para>Clinicians can measure a patient’s pulse rate by different methods, e.g. by
                    palpation of the radial pulse or by using a doppler ultrasound device. The
                    recording of the pulse rate to be entered in a CIF of different EHR systems  in
                    different ways. </para>
                <para>One EHR could display a set of options to choose from:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pulse rate by Palpation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pulse rate by Doppler</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pulse rate by Finger Tip Pulse Oximeter</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>The clinician would make a choice and then record the measurement result in a text
                    field.</para>
                <para>A different EHR could display a text field with a label “Pulse Rate” to enter
                    the measurement result and in addition offer options to choose from to record
                    the method:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Palpation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Doppler</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Finger Tip Pulse Oximeter</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>In addition to the kind of device used, there could be a choice of the measurement
                    being taken at rest or exercised. Again, this could be displayed in different
                    ways.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Systolic Blood Pressure 120 mmHg, taken on right
                        brachial artery, using BP cuff adult size, patient in sitting position for
                        at least 5 minutes, urinated not more than 30 minutes prior to
                        measurement</emphasis></para>
                <para>The current guidance for blood pressure measurements for adults includes the
                    body site, the blood pressure cuff size to use as well as some prerequisites.
                    The patient should be in a sitting position for at least 5 minutes and should
                    have urinated no more than 30 minutes before the measurement.</para>
                <para>For example, a EHR could display a text field for the result and lists of
                    choices for the body site:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Right brachial artery</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Left brachial artery</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Or it could be diplayed with the site and allow further refinement to specify
                    the laterality:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Brachial artery</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Right</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Left</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>In addition to specifiying the body site a list of choices for the blood
                    pressure cuff size used would also be selected, for example:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Adult size Small</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Adult size Medium</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Adult size Large</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>The same could be true for the display and documentation option for the
                    patient position (sitting yes/no, how long, urinated yes/no, how long prior to
                    measurement), which could differ between systems. There are different ways the
                    measurement result could be entered into a form in an EHR. Display options for
                    the user could be, e.g. a text field to enter the measurement result (e.g. 120
                    mmHg) with the label of the complete guideline:</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Acetaminophen 250 mg for a patient to take 1 tablet twice daily for 2
                    days</emphasis></para>
                <para>When a clinician orders a medication, rather than selecting this information
                    all at once with a single item, they will choose the various parts of the
                    medication order, such as</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kind of drug and strength (e.g., Acetaminophen 250 mg)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Amount and how often the patient should take the medication (e.g., 1
                            tablet twice daily)</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Duration (2 days)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Any constraints can also be represented (e.g., do not exceed a total
                            daily dosage of 600 mg)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Analysis Clinical Statements</title>
        <para>Ideally, the way the information is presented to clinicians is in a manner that is
            most efficient for the clinicians to use. The ways in which data is entered determines
            how data is stored in the EHR databases. However, what is an efficient way for
            clinicians to select and enter data may not be the most efficient way for data analysts
            to use when they are querying data once it has been normalized and stored in a database,
            such as when creating a new clinical decision support rule or compiling prevalence
            statistics. For this, the data should be normalized using an <emphasis role="italic"
                >analysis normal form (ANF)</emphasis> and stored in a database in such a way to
            optimize retrieval. The ANF is not necessarily a physical structure, but is how a data
            analyst might see the data when they are looking at it in a database, and not as
            clinicians would see it in the user interface (i.e., CIF).</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clinician collects data → Clinical Input Form (CIF)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data is normalized → Transformation process from CIF to Analysis Normal Form
                    (ANF) → Representable/storable in multiple types of databases, which <emphasis
                        role="underline">could</emphasis> include
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="timowilliams" timestamp="20190502T125824-0500" comment="Should we mention VistA here or just change it to EMR?" id="h42_3dr_c3b"?><?oxy_comment_start author="Ioana" timestamp="20190617T140755-0400" comment="We should &quot;EHR System&quot; - EMR is outdated and VistA is too specific." parentID="h42_3dr_c3b" mid="8"?>VistA<?oxy_comment_end mid="8"?><?oxy_comment_end?>
                    but a separate process would need to be performed to make that happen.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data analyst who is using or querying the data (e.g., creating a CDS rule or
                    working on prevalence statistics) →  ANF (it is how the data is represented or
                    stored in the database; must know enough about the data to know what is stored
                    in the topic vs. what is stored as a result or detail)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The goal of ANF is to enable analysts to understand the data and how it is stored in
            lieu of having to teach them about the thousands of ways data can be entered (i.e., CIF)
            and ensure the data that has to be expressed, can be expressed in an operable and
            scalable way. The more that data is normalized, the simpler it will become to analyze,
            and the likelihood of analysis errors will be reduced. Without the ANF, the probability
            of patient safety risks is increased.</para>
        <para>The following chapters will discuss how the ANF Model provides the clinical data
            normalization capabilities to support accurate data retrieval and analysis.</para>
    </section>    
</chapter>
